<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Enshū Yokosuka Mikumano Shrine Grand Festival</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17827</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3593486</id>
      <parentid>3569367</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:42:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3593486</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6587" sha1="00c15z5zqf6gzkprectbf323npa4z3e" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:遠州横須賀三熊野神社大祭]]



Enshū Yokosuka Mikumano Shrine Grand Festival (遠州横須賀三熊野神社大祭) is a festival held in Yokosuka, Kakegawa City, Shizuoka Prefecture, during the first weekend of April. The festival preserves traditional elements of Edo's Tenka Matsuri.
== Overview ==
The festival is the annual celebration of {{ill|Mikumano Shrine (Kakegawa)|ja|三熊野神社 (掛川市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mikumano Shrine (Kakegawa)|qq=}}, located in Yokosuka Castle town. It takes place every year on the first Friday, Saturday, and Sunday of April&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Mikumano Shrine Grand Festival Neri Procession |url=https://kunishitei.bunka.go.jp/heritage/detail/312/00000962 |website=National Cultural Heritage Database |access-date=2024-02-11 |publisher={{ill|Agency for Cultural Affairs|en|Agency for Cultural Affairs|qid=Q1009519|lt=Agency for Cultural Affairs (Japan)|1=Agency for Cultural Affairs}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;. 
Records suggest that a dance-based festival existed in the Genroku era (1688-1704)&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Enshū Yokosuka Mikumano Shrine Grand Festival - Tourism Information |url=https://www.city.kakegawa.shizuoka.jp/kanko/docs/7469.html |website=Kakegawa City Tourism Office |access-date=2024-02-11 |publisher={{ill|Kakegawa, Shizuoka|en|Kakegawa, Shizuoka|qid=Q823988|lt=Kakegawa|1=Kakegawa, Shizuoka}} Tourism and Cultural Promotion Division}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The current form of the festival dates back to the Kyōhō era (1716-1736) when the 14th lord of Yokosuka Castle, Nishio Tadanao, introduced elements from the Edo festivals, such as the Kanda Matsuri and Sannō Matsuri, into Yokosuka&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;.
The festival floats (禰里, Neri) of Yokosuka preserve an ancient Edo-style float design called the "Ipponbashira Mando-gata" (一本柱万度型). The Sanja Festival Hayashi (三社祭礼囃子), the traditional festival music played during the procession, was designated as Shizuoka Prefecture’s first Intangible Folk Cultural Property&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;. 
In 2019 (Heisei 27), the Neri procession was selected as a Nationally Designated Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property (記録作成等の措置を講ずべき無形の民俗文化財).
Additionally, Mikumano Shrine is venerated as a deity of childbirth and fertility, and a special fertility rite is performed during the festival.
== The Festival as a Floats Festival ==
The festival floats of Yokosuka are commonly referred to as "Neri" (禰里) in the region&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;. The "Ipponbashira Mando-gata" (一本柱万度型) design, unique to this area, has also spread to nearby regions between the Ōi River and the Tenryū River, where similar floats exist. 
Today, this float style remains only in the Yokosuka region and its neighboring areas&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;.
=== Structure of the Neri Floats ===
{{Unreferenceded|section=1|date=2024-02}}
The floats feature a single central column called the Shingen-bō (心源棒), topped with floral decorations and a lantern ornament called "Mando" (万度). The Mando features inscriptions of proverbs from Chinese classics, and on top of it, a festival doll (山車人形) is placed. 
Since these floats reach nearly six meters in height, modifications to traffic signals and power lines have been made in Yokosuka Town to accommodate their movement.
In 1996 (Heisei 8), a "return to Edo" event was held at the Kanda Matsuri, where Yokosuka floats were paraded in Tokyo. Since 2003 (Heisei 15), two of these floats have participated biennially in a Tokyo procession from Hibiya Park to Marunouchi as part of the Edo 400-Year Anniversary Festival. 
In May 2015, they also joined the Kanda Myōjin’s 400th Anniversary Procession.
=== Festival Music ===
The festival music (祭囃子) of Yokosuka originated from the Edo period, when the Nishio clan retainers learned Edo-style music during their sankin-kōtai (alternate attendance duty). Over time, the music evolved into a unique Yokosuka festival style&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;.
It is known as the Sanja Festival Hayashi (三社祭礼囃子).
The repertoire includes:  
* Three procession tunes – Ōma (大間), Yatai-shita (屋台下), and Baka-bayashi (馬鹿囃子)
* Three ceremonial taiko drumming pieces – Shōden (昇殿), Kamakura (鎌倉), and Yonchōme (四丁目)&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  
While pulling the floats, participants chant "Shita Shita"&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;. This phrase is derived from daimyō processions, where attendants announced "Shita ni Shita ni" (Make way, make way). The chanting style of Yokosuka’s festival has also spread to neighboring two-wheeled festival floats.
Because this style of music is the origin of two-wheeled festival floats' music, it was designated as Shizuoka Prefecture’s first Intangible Folk Cultural Property in 1955 (Shōwa 30)&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;.
== Fertility Festival ==
{{Unreferenceded|section=1|date=2024-02}}
Mikumano Shrine is famous for its fertility rituals, as it is believed to grant childbirth blessings.  
The shrine was established in 701 (Taihō 1) when Empress Fujiwara no Miyako enshrined Kumano Hongū's deity in this area to pray for the birth of her child, Emperor Shōmu.
During the festival, a special fertility ritual is performed in addition to the float processions.
The ritual involves carrying a sacred doll known as "O-Nenneko-sama" (おねんねこさま) through Yokosuka Town, receiving purification blessings at Mikumano Shrine. Many visitors travel from afar to receive these blessings, making it one of the most well-known aspects of the festival.
== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== See Also ==
* {{ill|Two-Wheeled Festival Floats|ja|二輪屋台|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Two-Wheeled Festival Floats|1=Two-Wheeled Festival Floats|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11371811}}
{{Japan Cultural Property}}

{{translated page|ja|遠州横須賀三熊野神社大祭|version=104337871|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:遠州横須賀三熊野神社大祭]]

&lt;!--Enshū Yokosuka Mikumano Shrine Grand Festival--&gt;

&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q11642088}}
[[Category:Festivals in Shizuoka Prefecture]]
[[Category:Float festivals of Japan]]
[[Category:Intangible Folk Cultural Properties that need measures such as documentation of Japan]]
[[Category:Kakegawa, Shizuoka]]
[[Category:Prefecturally designated intangible folk cultural property]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]
[[Category:Pages with 50+ untranslated japanese characters]]</text>
      <sha1>00c15z5zqf6gzkprectbf323npa4z3e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
