<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Akiba Gongen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10611</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592167</id>
      <parentid>3591589</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:27:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592167</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="14456" sha1="s09s9qmwbhecjkg326bn3w5bx5sb13c" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:秋葉権現]][[zh:秋葉權現]]
{{Infobox deity|venerated_in={{ill|Shugendō|qid=Q1483875|1=Shugendō}}|deity_of=Kami of {{ill|fire protection|qid=Q41399|1=Fire protection}}}}

{{otheruseslist|Akiha Gongen|Akiha Shrine|Akiha Shrine|qq=}}
'''Akiha Gongen'''' ({{ill|Akiba Gongen|ja|秋葉権現|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Akiha Gongen|qq=}}) is a deity of syncretic worship—a fusion of the mountain worship of {{ill|Mount Akiha|en|Mount Akiha|qid=Q501183|lt=Akihayama (Shizuoka)|1=Mount Akiha}} and the practices of Shugendō—exemplifying the union of Shinto and Buddhist beliefs. Renowned for its miraculous power in fire prevention, Akiha Gongen became widely venerated; in the early modern period, branch shrines were enshrined nationwide and religious associations called Akiha-kō were formed. Furthermore, following the great fires that struck Tokyo in December of Meiji 2, when the government erected fire-prevention shrines (spiritual fire-control facilities), the original divine form was overlooked as the people instead came to revere Akiha Gongen. Consequently, the firebreaks installed to curb the spread of flames came to be known as "Akiha no Hara," and later the name "Akihabara" was adopted for the area.
== Various Theories of Akiha Gongen ==
[[File:Akiba jinja 17.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The Akiha Shrine of Tōshū, known as {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akiha Shrine, Motomiya Honmiya Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}} (located in {{ill|Shizuoka Prefecture|en|Shizuoka Prefecture|qid=Q131320|lt=Shizuoka Prefecture|1=Shizuoka Prefecture}}, {{ill|Hamamatsu|en|Hamamatsu|qid=Q185125|lt=Hamamatsu City|1=Hamamatsu}})]]
[[File:Akiba Jinja, Tochio 01.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen in Tochio, Echigo ({{ill|Niigata Prefecture|en|Niigata Prefecture|qid=Q132705|lt=Niigata Prefecture|1=Niigata Prefecture}}, {{ill|Nagaoka, Niigata|en|Nagaoka, Niigata|qid=Q540312|lt=Nagaoka City|1=Nagaoka, Niigata}})]]
The origins and legends concerning Akiha Gongen vary in the literature. Yoshida Toshihide organized these diverse accounts into three categories:&lt;ref&gt;田村貞雄監修、中野東禅, Yoshida Toshihide ed. ''秋葉信仰'' (民衆宗教史叢書第31巻, 雄山閣, 1998)&lt;/ref&gt;
# The indigenous mountain deity of Akihayama in Tōshū (i.e. Tōen, present-day Shizuoka Prefecture).
# The deification of a Shugendō practitioner from Akihayama, known as Sanshakubō (i.e. Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen).
# A synthesis of the above two.
Furthermore, in earlier times several temples and shrines claimed to be the head temple. Because Sanshakubō was famed for his efficacy in fire prevention, many temples from various regions sought to enshrine him. For instance, the abbot of {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akiha Shrine, Motomiya Honmiya Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}} in Echigo (Tochio, Niigata) consented to the enshrinement of Sanshakubō; this, however, prompted another temple in Tōshū—claiming to be the true head temple—to file a lawsuit. In the Edo period, temple magistrates adjudicated the matter by recognizing Akiha Gongen as a dual sacred mountain deity, with Tōshū’s Akiha Shrine becoming the "Current Root" and Echigo’s Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen, where ritual practices are fulfilled, being regarded as the "Ancient Root."&lt;ref&gt;http://tochiokankou.jp/rekishi/akiba.html　◆秋葉神社と秋葉三尺坊&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Literature Treating Akiha Gongen and Sanshakubō as Distinct Spirits ===
==== Akiha Jiki ====
In the "Akiha Jiki" (whose original text is lost but is excerpted in Ban Shinyū's ''神名帳考証'' (established in Bunkyō 10, 1813) and in Akirizasa Rōjima's ''東海道名所図会'' (established in Kansei 9, 1797)), the principal deities are set forth as follows:
* The main hall enshrines Seikan-nyo (attributed to Gyōki), while Akiha Daikongen (the guardian of the mountain) is enshrined with the deity {{ill|Ōkuninushi|ja|大己貴命|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ōkuninushi|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 大国主}} (alternatively said to be enshrined at Shikinai Kuni Shrine), and Sanshakubō is identified as the guardian deity worshipped by the Akiha community.
In this account, Akiha Daikongen and Sanshakubō are presented as distinct divine entities.
==== Tōshu Akihayama Honchi Seikan Sanshakubō Ryaku Engi ====
In the "Tōshu Akihayama Honchi Seikan Sanshakubō Ryaku Engi" (established in Kyōhō 2, 1717) produced at Daidōzan Akihadera (Shūyō-ji), the title "Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen" is used, identifying Akiha Gongen with Sanshakubō. In this narrative, the bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara ({{ill|Avalokiteśvara|en|Avalokiteśvara|qid=Q193849|lt=Kannon Bodhisattva|1=Avalokiteśvara}}) is regarded as the local Buddha, and the deity is depicted in the form of a crow tengu riding a white fox, wielding a sword and a rope, and is said to be accompanied by 75 attendant deities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kasuisai.or.jp/event/firefestival.html 秋葉総本殿可睡斎 - 秘法七十五膳御供式]&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the legend, Sanshakubō originated in Shinshu; his mother was a devout follower of Kannon. After ordination, he took refuge at one of the twelve halls of the {{ill|Echigo|ja|越後|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Echigo|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 越後国|1=Echigo Province|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q666514}} region’s {{ill|Kanamine Shrine|ja|長岡蔵王権現|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kanamine Shrine|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, and assumed leadership as Sanshakubō. Through rigorous ascetic training, at dawn his "sacred manifestation"—described as possessing two crow-like wings and carrying a sword and rope—appeared, endowing him with supernatural abilities akin to those of a tengu, and he was recognized as an incarnation of Kannon.&lt;ref&gt;秋葉総本殿可睡斎御縁起&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, a white fox subsequently appeared, and the location where it settled was designated as his permanent abode.
It is said that he first arrived at Akihayama in Daidō in 809 AD, and later, beginning in 811 AD, he traveled widely to benefit all sentient beings, ultimately returning in 1294 AD.
Historical scholar {{ill|Tamura Sadawo|ja|田村貞雄|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Tamura Sadawo|1=Sadao Tamura|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11577024}}, after comparing various genealogies, criticized the "Akiha Jiki" and supported the "Sanshakubō Ryaku Engi."&lt;ref&gt;田村貞雄『秋葉信仰の新研究』岩田書院、2014th year &lt;/ref&gt;
==== The Three Great Vows of Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen ====
The three major vows associated with Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen are:
* If one places faith in the self, one will be spared from fire, conflagration, and all fire-related calamities.
* If one places faith in the self, one will be rescued from illness, disaster, and all suffering.
* If one places faith in the self, one will be granted livelihood, fulfillment of one’s innermost desires, and complete satisfaction.
== Devotees, Shrines, and the Spread of Faith ==
During the Edo period, Tōshū Akihayama was served by priests, monks (from the Sōtō school), and Shugendō practitioners (from the Tōzan-ha). The head priest was a Sōtō monk. Although Akiha-dera was originally part of the Shin'gi Shingon sect, it became affiliated with Sōtō from the Edo period onward. This shift began when, by order of {{ill|Tokugawa Ieyasu|en|Tokugawa Ieyasu|qid=Q171977|lt=Tokugawa Ieyasu|1=Tokugawa Ieyasu}}, Mochibata Morinrin was dispatched from Kasuisai to serve as the head priest. In Kan'ei 2 (1625), when Rōgetsu Genshū was abbot, an internal conflict arose between the Zen monks and the Shugendō practitioners; the Zen faction sought assistance from Kasuisai (Sōtō), while the Shugendō faction turned to Nitta-bō of the Tōzan-ha, resulting in litigation. The temple magistrate ultimately ruled in favor of the Zen faction, and Akiha-dera was re-assigned to the Sōtō sect as a subsidiary temple of Kasuisai.&lt;ref name="jiten"&gt;日本の神仏の辞典, 2001st year 6月, ISBN 978-4469012682&lt;/ref&gt;
From the Akiha Festival of Jōkyō 2 (1685) onward, Akiha Gongen came to be widely known as a deity for fire prevention, and religious associations known as Akiha-kō were established nationwide.&lt;ref name="jiten"/&gt; In An'ei 7 (1778), it even received an imperial mandate from the late Emperor Gō.
== Akiha-kō ==
For commoners in the Edo period, the pilgrimage to Tōshū Akihayama represented a significant financial burden. Thus, a mutual aid organization known as Akiha-kō was established, in which members pooled funds and, in rotation, selected a representative to undertake the pilgrimage to Tōshū Akihayama to pray for fire prevention and safety, and then return home. Moreover, for those unable to make the journey, local communities enshrined Akiha Gongen. At its peak, the number of Akiha-kō groups nationwide was said to exceed 30,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.town.morimachi.shizuoka.jp/sigh/choshi/choshi-26.html Shizuoka Prefecture Morimachi – Illustrated History of Morimachi, Chapter 26: Akiha Faith and Morimachi]&lt;/ref&gt;
== Separation of Shinto and Buddhism / Haibutsu Kishaku ==
In Keiō 4 (1868), the government’s policy of separating Shinto and Buddhism (神仏分離・廃仏毀釈) affected Akiha Gongen as well. At Tōshū Akihayama, debates persisted over whether Akiha Gongen should be considered a Shinto deity or a Buddhist figure. However, in Meiji 5, the Ministry of Religion (教部省), which oversaw shrine and temple administration, stated:
"If the 'Akiha Jiki' mentions the enshrined figures as Seikan-nyo (attributed to Gyōki), Akiha Gongen (the guardian deity of the mountain), and Ōkuninushi (or as some say, the deity of Shikina Kuni Shrine), it must be made clear that the deities of the mountain and the spirit of Sanshakubō are inherently distinct; and since Shikina Kuni Shrine is not located within this district but rather in Imaji-dai Village, the claim that they are the same is not tenable. Furthermore, as the enshrined deity is not of Buddhist origin, it is appropriate to designate it as such." 
Thus, Akiha Gongen was officially determined to be distinct from Sanshakubō, and on December 27 of Keiō 3, it was decreed that it be renamed "Akiha Shrine" (秋葉神社).&lt;ref&gt;辻善之助・村上専精・鷲尾順敬編『新編 明治維新神仏分離史料』第六巻 東海編, 名著出版, 1983, pp.228–230&lt;/ref&gt;
Regarding the name of the enshrined deity, the Ministry of Religion did not adopt the Ōkuninushi theory from "Akiha Jiki" but, drawing on the hereditary traditions of Shugendō, ruled that it was more appropriate to refer to the deity as {{ill|Kagu-tsuchi|lt=Kagu-tsuchi|lt=Kagutsuchi|ja|火之迦具土大神|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kagutsuchi|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}. Following this decision, the majority of small shrines dedicated to Akiha Gongen were clearly marked as Shinto shrines (Akiha Jinja). However, in the "Shaji Torishirabe Ruizan" (compiled in 1870), there is an instance of an Akiha Shrine enshrining Kagutsuchi.&lt;ref name="jiten"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akihasan.or.jp/category01/index04.html Akiha Shrine Official Website]&lt;/ref&gt;
Subsequently, because the head temple, Daidōzan Akiha-dera, was abolished in Meiji 6 (1873) due to the loss of its monastic status, under the guidance of authorities in Hamamatsu Prefecture, Sanshakubō was relocated to Kasuisai.
== Temples That Enshrine Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen ==
Temples that continue to enshrine Akiha Sanshakubō Daikongen include:
* Akiha-dera in Akihayama, located in {{ill|Hamamatsu|en|Hamamatsu|qid=Q185125|lt=Hamamatsu City|1=Hamamatsu}}, {{ill|Tenryū-ku|en|Tenryū-ku|qid=Q1131460|lt=Tenryū-ku|1=Tenryū-ku}}, Shizuoka Prefecture.
* Kasuisai (Akiha Sōhonden) in {{ill|Fukuroi, Shizuoka|en|Fukuroi, Shizuoka|qid=Q821337|lt=Fukuroi City|1=Fukuroi, Shizuoka}}, Shizuoka Prefecture.
* Akiha Honbō in Shimizu-ku, {{ill|Shizuoka (city)|en|Shizuoka (city)|qid=Q174691|lt=Shizuoka City|1=Shizuoka (city)}}, Shizuoka Prefecture.
* Jōan-ji (Akiha Sōhonbyō) in Tochio, {{ill|Nagaoka, Niigata|en|Nagaoka, Niigata|qid=Q540312|lt=Nagaoka City|1=Nagaoka, Niigata}}, Niigata Prefecture (located in Tochio).
* Akiha Shrine in Takuro-chō, {{ill|Tokushima (city)|en|Tokushima (city)|qid=Q207309|lt=Tokushima City|1=Tokushima (city)}}, Tokushima Prefecture.
== References ==
{{reflist|2|qq=}}

== See Also ==
* {{ill|8=ja|9=仏の一覧|List of Buddhalike Deities|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/8=ja|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 日本の仏尊|1=Japanese Buddhist pantheon|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q6158131}}
* {{ill|Great Tengu|ja|大天狗|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Great Tengu|1=Daitengu|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q10934709}}
* {{ill|Iwanawa Gongen|ja|飯縄権現|1=Izuna Gongen|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Iwanawa Gongen|13=User:Immanuelle/Izuna Gongen|qq=}}
* {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akiha Shrine, Motomiya Honmiya Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}}
* {{ill|Akihabara|en|Akihabara|qid=Q418096|lt=Akihabara|1=Akihabara}}
== External Links ==
{{Commonscat|Akiha Gongen|qq=}}
* [http://www.akihasanhongu.jp/ Akihayama Honmiya Akiha Shrine]
* [http://www.kasuisai.or.jp/ Kasuisai (Akiha Sōhonden)]
* [http://www.akihasan.or.jp/ Akihayama Honbō Minehonin]
* [https://www.joanji.jp/ Japan Daiichi Sōhonbyō, Jōan-ji]
* [https://www.city.nagaoka.niigata.jp/kankou/rekishi/jinjya/akibahaiden.html Akiha Shrine (Akiha Sanshakubō Haiden) in Nagaoka City]
{{Buddhism2|qq=}}
{{Shinto Horizontal|qq=}}

{{Akiha Faith|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|秋葉権現|version=104531681|comment=Imported full ja history}}


[[ja:秋葉権現]]

[[zh:%E7%A7%8B%E8%91%89%E6%AC%8A%E7%8F%BE]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{Commons category|Akiha Gongen}}
[[zh:秋葉權現]]
&lt;!--zhwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{Commons category|Akiha Gongen}}
[[zh:秋葉權現]]
{{wikidata link|Q2680724}}
[[Category:Shugendō]]
[[Category:Shugendō deities]]
[[Category:Tengu]]
[[Category:Mountain faith]]
[[Category:Gongen]]
[[Category:History of Hamamatsu]]
[[Category:Fire deities]]
[[Category:Shinbutsu shūgō]]
[[Category:Akiha faith]]
[[Category:Avalokiteśvara]]</text>
      <sha1>s09s9qmwbhecjkg326bn3w5bx5sb13c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
