<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ama Clan Genealogy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17444</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592204</id>
      <parentid>3560087</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:28:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592204</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="20914" sha1="3ax8avcx3mdeva6u7nnm37227xaqexn" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:海部氏系図]]



{{otheruses|Genealogy of the Amabe clan|a district in Yan'an, China|Baota District|qq=}}
[[File:Amabe Clan genealogy.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Genealogy of the Amabe Clan (Main Genealogy)]]
The '''Genealogy of the Amabe Clan''' (海部氏系図, Amabe-shi Keizu) is a genealogy passed down by the [[Amabe clan]] (海部氏, Amabe-shi), the shrine family (社家, Shake) of [[Kono Shrine]] (籠神社, {{ill|Kono Shrine|en|Kono Shrine|qid=Q705126|lt=Kono Shrine|1=Kono Shrine}}), located in {{ill|Miyazu|en|Miyazu|qid=Q111018930|lt=Miyazu|1=Miyazu}}, {{ill|Kyoto Prefecture|en|Kyoto Prefecture|qid=Q120730|lt=Kyoto Prefecture|1=Kyoto Prefecture}}. It consists of two volumes: the '''Genealogy of the Shrine Priests of Kono Shrine''' (籠名神社祝部氏係図, Main Genealogy) and the '''Annotated Genealogy of the Shrine Priests of Kono Shrine, Amabe Clan of Tanba Province''' (籠名神宮祝部丹波国造海部直等氏之本記, Annotated Genealogy).
Both genealogies are valuable documents for studying the evolution of ancient clan and ritual systems. They were designated as {{ill|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|en|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|qid=Q1188622|lt=Important Cultural Property (Japan)|1=Important Cultural Property (Japan)}} in {{ill|1975|en|1975|qid=Q2479|lt=1975|1=1975}} and as {{ill|National Treasure (Japan)|en|National Treasure (Japan)|qid=Q1139795|lt=National Treasure (Japan)|1=National Treasure (Japan)}} in {{ill|1976|en|1976|qid=Q2480|lt=1976|1=1976}} &lt;ref group="note"&gt;The "Annotated Genealogy" was designated as an "accompanying item" (附).&lt;/ref&gt;.
== Main Genealogy ==
The "Main Genealogy" is among the oldest genealogies in Japan, second only to the {{ill|Enchin Genealogy|ja|円珍俗姓系図|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Enchin Genealogy|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, part of the {{ill|Chisho Daishi-related Documents|ja|智証大師関係文書典籍|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Chisho Daishi-related Documents|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, also known as the "Genealogy of the Waki Clan" (和気氏系図). &lt;ref group="note"&gt;The "Genealogy of the Waki Clan" was completed by the early Shōwa period (9th century).&lt;/ref&gt; As a vertical genealogy, it is considered a rare relic that best preserves the ancient form of genealogies.
The genealogy is a scroll (巻子, Makimono) made of five sheets of mulberry paper (楮紙, Kōzo-shi) joined together, measuring 25.7 cm wide and 228.5 cm long. The title at the center reads "Tanba Province, Yosa District, Kono Shrine, Descendants of the Amabe Clan," followed by a single line of light ink under which the names of deities and people are written. Each name is accompanied by a red square seal marked "Tanba Province." This indicates that the genealogy was submitted to and approved by the Tanba Provincial Office.
The genealogy is dated between June 8, 871 CE (when the Kono Shrine was promoted to junior fourth Rank) and December 14, 877 CE (when it was promoted to junior fourth Rank, upper). &lt;ref group="note"&gt;Kono Shrine was promoted to junior fourth Rank on June 8, 871, and to junior fourth Rank, upper, on December 14, 877, according to the {{ill|Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|en|Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|qid=Q1052981|lt=Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|1=Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed to have been compiled by the 33rd head of the family, Amabe-no-Atai Inao (海部直稲雄). &lt;ref group="note"&gt;The "Annotated Genealogy" attributes the compilation to the 32nd head, Tadao, but notes indicate he served as a shrine priest (祝, Hōri) until 864, which creates a chronological inconsistency.&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Content ===
The genealogy consists of three parts:
* From the progenitor [[Hikohoakari no Mikoto]] to the 19th head, Takeshibune no Sukune (建振熊宿祢), covering the period before family names (kabane) were used. This section is sparse, with large gaps.
* From the 20th head, Tobi (都比), to the 24th head, Kunini (勲尼), during the period when the clan held the title "Amabe-no-Atai" and managed the maritime communities (海人族, Ama) in {{ill|Tanba Province|en|Tanba Province|qid=Q954511|lt=Tanba Province|1=Tanba Province}}.
* From the 25th head, Gobekimichi (伍佰道), to the 32nd head, Tadao, during the "shrine priest era," with the title "Amabe-no-Atai" and service at the Kono Shrine. The genealogy records each head's years of service.
== Annotated Genealogy ==
The "Annotated Genealogy" is a more detailed version of the "Main Genealogy," annotated with additional notes. The existing copy is an early {{ill|Edo period|en|Edo period|qid=Q184963|lt=Edo period|1=Edo period}} manuscript, with an afterword by the scribe, Amabe Katsu Chiyo (海部勝千代). The original text, dated to the {{ill|Ninna|en|Ninna|qid=Q1346317|lt=Ninna era|1=Ninna}} (885–889 CE), is known as the "Genealogy of the Amabe Clan of Tanba Province."
The manuscript was written on reused paper containing illustrations of weather predictions and omens from the late {{ill|Azuchi–Momoyama period|en|Azuchi–Momoyama period|qid=Q319531|lt=Azuchi–Momoyama period|1=Azuchi–Momoyama period}}, which adds historical value. The annotations trace the origins of the Amabe clan, provide details missing from the "Main Genealogy," and include unique legends not found in other records such as the {{ill|Kiki|ja|記紀|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kiki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|1=Kiki (Shinto)|qid=Q842308}} or the {{ill|Kojiki|ja|旧事本紀|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kojiki|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 先代旧事本紀}}.
=== Content ===
The "Annotated Genealogy" traces the lineage from the progenitor to the 34th head, providing additional details about each person's deeds and noting collateral lines and their descendants.
== Historical Evaluation ==
The genealogy has been studied by historians such as [[Masashi Murata]], [[Toshihide Akamatsu]], and [[Nobuyoshi Yamamoto]]. Despite minimal skepticism or criticism, historian [[Ryō Ōta]] raised a concern about the absence of Amabe no Oshitatatsu (海直忍立), who is mentioned in other historical records.
== Notes ==
=== Explanatory Notes ===
{{Reflist|group=note|qq=}}
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== References ==
* {{Cite book|author=Amabe Mitsuhiko|title=The Sacred Treasures of Motoise: The National Treasure Genealogy of the Amabe Clan|publisher=Motoise Kono Shrine|year=1996|qq=}}
* {{Cite book|author=Tanaka Suguru|title=Revised Amabe Genealogy|publisher=National Shrine Archives|year=1986|qq=}}
* {{Cite journal|author=Suzuki Masanobu|title=A Foundational Study of the Amabe Clan Genealogy|journal=Kyoto Historical Society Bulletin|year=2015|qq=}}
== External Links ==
* [http://www.motoise.jp/main/houmotu/keizu1.html Official Site of Kono Shrine: National Treasure Genealogy of the Amabe Clan]
{{Japanese-history-stub|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|海部氏系図|version=103286188|comment=Imported full ja history}}


&lt;!--Ama Clan Genealogy--&gt;

[[Category:Pages with duplicated content]]
==Merged second translation==
[[File:Amabe Clan genealogy.jpg|thumb|right|250px|{{ill|Ama Clan Genealogy|ja|海部氏系図（本系図）巻頭|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Amabe Clan Genealogy|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}]]
'''{{ill|Ama Clan Genealogy|ja|海部氏系図|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Amabe Clan Genealogy|qq=}}''' (Amabe Shikeizu) is the genealogy passed down within the {{ill|Kono Shrine|en|Kono Shrine|qid=Q705126|lt=Kago Shrine|1=Kono Shrine}} family ({{ill|Shake (social class)|en|Shake (social class)|qid=Q11588367|lt=Shrine family|1=Shake (social class)}}) of the {{ill|Amabe clan|en|Amabe clan|qid=Q65272445|lt=Amabe Clan|1=Amabe clan}}, and consists of two parts: Volume 1 of the ''{{ill|Kagonashinja Shukube-shikeizu|ja|籠名神社祝部氏係図|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kagonashinja Shukube-shikeizu|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}'' (hereafter called the “Main Genealogy”) and Volume 1 of the ''{{ill|Kagonashingu Shukube Tanba Kunizukuri Amabe Naotō-shi no Honki|ja|籠名神宮祝部丹波国造海部直等氏之本記|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kagonashingu Shukube Tanba Kunizukuri Amabe Naotō-shi no Honki|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}'' (hereafter called the “Annotated Genealogy”).
Both documents are regarded as invaluable texts for studying the evolution of ancient clan systems and religious rites; the Main Genealogy was designated as a {{ill|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|en|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|qid=Q1188622|lt=Important Cultural Property|1=Important Cultural Property (Japan)}} in June of Showa 50 (1975) and, in the following month (Showa 51, 1976), the Annotated Genealogy was designated as a {{ill|National Treasure (Japan)|en|National Treasure (Japan)|qid=Q1139795|lt=National Treasure|1=National Treasure (Japan)}}.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;However, the “Annotated Genealogy” is designated as an “附（つけたり）”.&lt;/ref&gt;
== Main Genealogy (Hon Keizu) ==
The “Main Genealogy” is one of the oldest extant genealogies in Japan and is second only to the National Treasure ''{{ill|Enchin Zokusei Keizu|ja|円珍俗姓系図|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Enchin Zokusei Keizu|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}'' (also known as the “{{ill|Wakakei Shikeizu|ja|和気氏系図|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Wakakei Shikeizu|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}”)—which is one of the documents in the series of the {{ill|Chishō Daishi Kankei Monjotenseki|ja|智証大師関係文書典籍|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Chishō Daishi Kankei Monjotenseki|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}—and, by following a vertical (tate-keizu) format, is considered a rare relic that best preserves the ancient form of genealogical records.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;The “Wakakei Shikeizu” is believed to have been established in the early part of the Shōwa (承和) period (early 9th century).&lt;/ref&gt;
Its format is that of a scroll ({{ill|makushi|ja|巻子本|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/makushi|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 巻物|1=Scroll|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q720106}}) made by joining five sheets of paper ({{ill|Japanese tissue|en|Japanese tissue|qid=Q3445052|lt=kaminogami|1=Japanese tissue}}) vertically; it measures 25.7 cm in width and 228.5 cm in length. The central inscription reads: 
"丹後国与謝郡従四位下籠名神従元于今所斎奉祝部奉仕海部直等之氏"  
Below this, a line drawn in light ink ({{ill|tan-sumi|ja|淡墨|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/tan-sumi|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}) is placed, upon which the names of deities and individuals are recorded. Over this, a vermilion seal bearing the inscription “丹後国印” is affixed (28 seals in total), indicating that the document was submitted to, and approved by, the {{ill|Tango Province|en|Tango Province|qid=Q1054331|lt=Tango Province|1=Tango Province}} authorities.
Regarding its date of composition, the inscription “従四位下籠名神” indicates that it was compiled during the period when {{ill|Kono Shrine|en|Kono Shrine|qid=Q705126|lt=Kago Shrine|1=Kono Shrine}} held the Rank of “従四位下.” This period is bounded above by the 13th year of {{ill|Zhenguan|en|Zhenguan|qid=Q3577278|lt=Jōgan|1=Zhenguan}} (June 8, 871, old calendar) and below by the 1st year of {{ill|Gangyō|en|Gangyō|qid=Q747451|lt=Genkei|1=Gangyō}} (December 14, 877, old calendar).&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Kago Shrine was elevated to “従四位下” on June 8, 871 and further to “従四位上” on December 14, 877 (according to the ''{{ill|Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|en|Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|qid=Q1052981|lt=Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku|1=Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku}}'').&lt;/ref&gt; The notes in the Annotated Genealogy also indicate that it was compiled during the Jōgan period (859–877).&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;In the 19th year of Jōgan (4/16, old calendar), the era name was changed to Genkei.&lt;/ref&gt; The author is believed to be the then-current head (the 33rd generation according to the Annotated Genealogy) known as '''Amabe Naioe'''.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Although the Annotated Genealogy attributes it to the 32nd generation, the note for Naioe states that he served for 16 years as “Shuku,” until the 6th year of Jōgan (864), which creates a discrepancy.&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Content ===
The genealogy records only the direct male descendants from the legendary ancestor {{ill|Hikoakitsumeri no Mikoto|ja|彦火明命|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hikoakitsumeri no Mikoto|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 天火明命|1=Amenohoakari|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q10940411}} through to the 32nd generation member known as '''Tayu'''.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;An exception is found in the 27th generation, where three brothers (Senjima, Senashi, and Senari) are recorded.&lt;/ref&gt; In terms of content, it is divided into three parts:&lt;ref name="秘宝"&gt;See “The Treasures of Moto Ise and the National Treasure Amabe Clan Genealogy”.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first part covers the early period—from the ancestor to the 19th generation member '''Kenfuri Kumayasukune''', a phase that does not include a surname (kabane) and in which only three individuals (deities) are recorded, due to gaps covering the 2nd and 3rd generations and the 5th through the 18th generations.
* The second part spans from the 20th generation, known as '''Toshibi''', through the 24th generation, known as '''Kun-ni''', during which the members bore the surname “Amabe Naochi” and are believed to have led the Amabe group (an assemblage of the maritime peoples) as representatives (【ill|Tomo-zō|ja|伴造】) of {{ill|Tanba Province|en|Tanba Province|qid=Q954511|lt=Tanba Province|1=Tanba Province}} (which at the time also included Tango Province).
* The third part covers from the 25th generation, '''Gobai-dō''', through the Jōgan period up to the 32nd generation member '''Tayu'''. In this period, members bear the surname “Amabe Naochi” and include the character “祝” (shuku) appended to their names, recording the number of years they served as officiants (shuku) at Kago Shrine.
== Annotated Genealogy (Kan-chū Keizu) ==
The “Annotated Genealogy” is an annotated version of the Main Genealogy. Although it also follows a vertical (tate-keizu) format, the extant copy is an early Edo period manuscript&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Its colophon is by a scribe named '''Kaihei Katsuchiyo'''.&lt;/ref&gt; According to tradition, the original was compiled during the Ninna period (885–889) as ''Tanba Kunizukuri Kaihei Naotō-shi no Honki''. Its verso features divination charts—presumably dating from the Momoyama period—that depict divination based on weather conditions and cloud shapes. These charts were originally written on the reverse side of now-discarded divination charts and are also regarded as valuable ancient documents.&lt;ref name="秘宝"/&gt; Incidentally, the annotations describe the following compilation history (recorded as “一本云”):
* During the reign of {{ill|Empress Suiko|en|Empress Suiko|qid=Q298057|lt=Empress Suiko|1=Empress Suiko}}, Kaihei Chokishi Yasunune, who served as the governor (国造) of Tanba, among others, composed the "Kuni Honki."
* Three generations later, in {{ill|Yōrō|en|Yōrō|qid=Q1373061|lt=Yōro|1=Yōrō}} 5 (721), Kaihei Chokisen (the 27th generation) and his brothers—Senjima, Senashi, and Senari—compiled the "Kago-sha Shukube-shikeizu" (which is known as the Main Genealogy) (some sources give the date as August of Yōro 6 (722)).
* During the Ninna period, because the Main Genealogy did not include mythological events or the names of the ancestors, the 33rd generation member, Inae, supplemented the earlier record to compile the "Kago-sha Shukube-shikeizu" (the present Main Genealogy).
* In the Ninna period, because the Main Genealogy did not record mythological details or ancestral names and did not fully conform to a complete record, the 33rd generation member, Inae, supplemented the traditional oral history and composed the ''Tanba Kunizukuri Kaihei Naotō-shi no Honki''.
=== Content ===
The genealogy records from the legendary ancestor to the 34th generation, with detailed supplementary annotations regarding each deity and individual’s deeds. It even includes sections on collateral branches (such as the siblings and their descendants) that are not found in ancient records like the {{ill|Kojiki|en|Kojiki|qid=Q813031|lt=Kojiki|1=Kojiki}}, thus preserving unique traditions that are not recorded elsewhere.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Up to the 14th generation, the names in this genealogy coincide with those in the “Wari-shi Keizu” found in the {{ill|Kojiki|ja|旧事本紀|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kojiki|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 先代旧事本紀}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In this manner, passages that were omitted in the Main Genealogy have been supplemented.&lt;ref name="秘宝"/&gt; 
== Textual Criticism ==
Investigations into the original document have been carried out by historians such as {{ill|Murata Masashi|ja|村田正志|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Murata Masashi|1=Masashi Murata|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11523464}}, {{ill|Akamatsu Toshihide|ja|赤松俊秀|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Akamatsu Toshihide|1=Akamatsu Toshihide|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q6582053}}, and {{ill|Yamamoto Nobuyoshi|ja|山本信吉|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yamamoto Nobuyoshi|1=Nobuyoshi Yamamoto|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11468847}}. However, there has been very little critical debate regarding the authenticity of this genealogy; historian {{ill|Ota Ryo|ja|太田亮|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ota Ryo|1=Akira Ōta|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q13099367}} only briefly mentioned that “the absence of Kaihei Naochi Tatsu in the Tajima Shōzei-chō is rather suspicious.”
== Footnotes ==
=== Note ===
{{Reflist|group=Note|qq=}}
=== References ===
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== References ==
* “{{ill|Kaibe Clan Genealogy|ja|海部氏系圖|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kaibe Clan Genealogy|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}},” from ''Kaibe-shi Keizu, {{ill|Hachiman Gudōkun|ja|八幡愚童訓|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hachiman Gudōkun|1=Hachiman Gudōkun|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q4162454}}, {{ill|Shinsen Kame Sōki|ja|新撰龜相記|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinsen Kame Sōki|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, {{ill|Takahashi Ujibumi|en|Takahashi Ujibumi|qid=Q1108567|lt=Takahashi-shi Bun|1=Takahashi Ujibumi}}, and {{ill|Tensho|ja|天書|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Tensho|1=Tensho|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11442689}}– a section of the {{ill|Shintō Taikei|ja|神道大系|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shintō Taikei|1=Shintō Taikei|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11590923}} (Classics, Volume 13), compiled by the Shintō Taikei Editorial Committee, 1992.
* {{ill|Murata Masashi|ja|村田正志|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Murata Masashi|1=Masashi Murata|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11523464}} (ed.), with Kaihei Mitsuhiko as compiler, ''Moto Ise no Hihō to Kokuhō Kaibe-shi Keizu Zōho-ban'' (Expanded Edition of the National Treasure Kaibe Clan Genealogy from Moto Ise), published by the Moto Ise Kago Jinja Office, 1996 (first edition 1988).
* {{ill|Tanaka Taku|ja|田中卓|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Tanaka Taku|1=Takashi Tanaka|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11575370}}, “Kōtei Kaibe-shi Keizu no Kōtei” (“Textual Critical Edition of the Kaibe Clan Genealogy”), in ''Tanaka Taku Chosakushū 2'', published by Kokusho Kankōkai, 1986, ISBN 4-336-01611-9.
* ''Asahi Hyakka Nihon no Kokuhō'', Volume 8 (Kinki 6), Asahi Shimbunsha, 1999, ISBN 978-4-02-380012-0.
* {{ill|Suzuki Masanobu|ja|鈴木正信|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Suzuki Masanobu|1=Masanobu Suzuki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q20040831}}, “Fundamental Research on the Kaibe Clan Genealogy”, in ''Kyōtanago-shi Kyōdō-sai'', 2015.
== External Links ==
* [http://www.motoise.jp/main/houmotu/keizu1.html Official site of {{ill|Kono Shrine|en|Kono Shrine|qid=Q705126|lt=Kago Shrine|1=Kono Shrine}} – “National Treasure Kaibe Clan Genealogy”] {{ja icon|qq=}}
{{Japanese-history-stub|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|海部氏系図|version=103286188|comment=Imported full ja history}}

}}

{{draft categories|

&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q11559330}}
[[Category:Tango Province]]
[[Category:National Treasures of Kyoto Prefecture]]
[[Category:宮津市の歴史]]
[[Category:宮津市の重要文化財]]
[[Category:History books of the Heian Period]]
[[Category:日本の国宝 (書跡・典籍・古文書)]]
[[Category:Japanese mythology]]
[[Category:Shinto texts]]
[[Category:Family trees]]
[[Category:Pages with 50+ untranslated japanese characters]]
[[Category:Pages with 100+ untranslated japanese characters]]</text>
      <sha1>3ax8avcx3mdeva6u7nnm37227xaqexn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
