<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese pagoda</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3595580</id>
      <parentid>3572732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:19:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3595580</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="28505" sha1="p69udldg4a75zkw4ag3qaokgzdpbbab" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[de:Tō]][[en:Japanese pagoda]][[es:Pagoda japonesa]][[fr:Tō]][[it:Pagoda giapponese]][[nl:Tō]][[sl:Japonska pagoda]][[th:เจดีย์ญี่ปุ่น]][[vi:Chùa Nhật Bản]]
{{Short description|Significant component of Japanese Buddhist temple compounds}}
{{Redirect|Tō|the swords|Japanese sword|and|Katana}}
&lt;div class="thumb tright"&gt;
&lt;div class="thumbinner"&gt;
{| style="border-collapse:collapse" cellpadding="0"
|style="border:1px solid black;"|[[File:Shitennoji - pagoda.jpg|alt=Wooden pagoda|x149px]]
|style="border:1px solid black;"|[[File:Fujitoji 06.JPG|alt=Stone pagoda|x150px]]
|style="border:1px solid black;"|[[File:Eisonto-mae.jpg|alt=A ''gorintō''|x150px]]
|}
&lt;div class="thumbcaption"&gt;Multi-storied pagodas in wood and stone, and a ''gorintō''&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
Pagodas in Japan are called {{nihongo|'''tō'''|塔|lit. pagoda}}, sometimes {{nihongo|'''buttō'''|仏塔|1=Stupa|lit. Buddhist pagoda}} or {{nihongo|'''tōba'''|塔婆|lit. pagoda}}, and derive historically from the {{ill|Chinese pagoda|en|Chinese pagoda|qid=Q5100853|lt=Chinese pagoda|1=Chinese pagoda}}, itself an interpretation of the Indian ''[[stupa]]''.&lt;ref name="IK "/&gt;  Like the ''stupa'', pagodas were originally used as [[:en:Reliquaries|Reliquaries]], but in many cases ended up losing this function.&lt;ref name="jaanustou"/&gt; Pagodas are quintessentially Buddhist and an important component of {{ill|Buddhist temples in Japan|en|Buddhist temples in Japan|qid=Q3141900|lt=Japanese Buddhist temple|1=Buddhist temples in Japan}} compounds but, because until the [[Shinbutsu bunri|Kami and Buddhas Separation Act]] of 1868, a {{ill|Shinto shrine|en|Shinto shrine|qid=Q845945|lt=Shinto shrine|1=Shinto shrine}} was normally [[Shinbutsu-shūgō|also a Buddhist temple and vice versa]], they are not rare at shrines either. The famous [[Itsukushima Shrine]], for example, has one.&lt;ref name="hamashima group"&gt;{{cite book|last=Hamashima|first=Masashi|title=Jisha Kenchiku no Kanshō Kiso Chishiki|year=1999|publisher=Shibundō|location=Tokyo|pages=88|language=ja}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Meiji Restoration]] the word ''tō'', once used exclusively in a religious context, came to mean also "{{ill|Tower|en|Tower|qid=Q12518|lt=Tower|1=Stupas by number}}" in the western sense, as for example in {{nihongo|{{ill|Eiffel Tower|en|Eiffel Tower|qid=Q243|lt=Eiffel Tower|1=Eiffel Tower}}|エッフェル塔|Efferu-tō}}.

Of the Japanese pagoda's many forms, some are built in wood and are collectively known as {{nihongo|''mokutō''|木塔|lit. wood pagoda}}, but most are carved out of stone ({{nihongo|''sekitō''|石塔|lit. stone pagoda}}. Wood pagodas are large buildings with either two stories (like the {{nihongo|''[[tahōtō]]''|多宝塔|lit. [[:ja:多宝如来|Tahō]] pagoda}}, see photo below) or an odd number of stories. Extant wood pagodas with more than two storeys have almost always either three stories (and are therefore called {{nihongo|''sanjū-no-tō''|三重塔|1=Three-storied pagoda|2=ja|3=三重塔|4=zh|5=三重塔|1=Three-storied pagodas|lit. three-storeyed pagoda}}) or five (and are called {{nihongo|''gojū-no-tō''|五重塔|lit. five-storeyed pagoda}}. Stone pagodas are nearly always small, usually well below 3 metres, and as a rule offer no usable space. If they have more than one storey, pagodas are called {{nihongo|''tasōtō''|多層塔|lit. multi-storied pagoda}} or {{nihongo|''tajūtō''|多重塔|lit. multi-storied pagoda}}.

A pagoda's size is measured in ''{{ill|Ken (unit)|en|Ken (unit)|qid=Q3195007|lt=ken|1=Ken (unit)}}'', where a ''ken'' is the interval between two pillars of a traditional-style building. A ''tahōtō'' for example can be either 5x5 ken or 3x3 ''ken''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Nihon Kenchiku-shi |editor= Fujita Masaya, Koga Shūsaku |publisher=Shōwa-dō |date=April 10, 1990 |edition=September 30, 2008 |isbn=4-8122-9805-9 |language=ja |page=79}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word is usually translated in English as "bay" and is better understood as an indication of proportions than as a unit of measurement.

==History==
[[File:Hokiji03ds1536.jpg|Japan's oldest three-storeyed pagoda at [[Hokki-ji]], {{ill|Ikaruga, Nara|en|Ikaruga, Nara|qid=Q379233|lt=Ikaruga|1=Ikaruga, Nara}}, {{ill|Nara Prefecture|en|Nara Prefecture|qid=Q131287|lt=Nara Pref.|1=Nara Prefecture}} It was built in 706.|thumb|160 px]]The ''stupa'' was originally a simple mound containing the {{ill|The Buddha|en|The Buddha|qid=Q9441|lt=The Buddha|1=The Buddha}}'s ashes which in time became more elaborate, while its finial grew proportionally larger.&lt;ref name="jaanustou"&gt;Jaanus, ''Tou''&lt;/ref&gt; After reaching China, the stupa met the Chinese watchtower and evolved into the pagoda, a tower with an odd number of storeys.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;Odd numbers are strongly favoured by Chinese {{ill|Numerology|en|Numerology|qid=Q140732|lt=Numerology|1=Numerology}} and Buddhism. They are supposed to represent {{ill|Yin and yang|en|Yin and yang|qid=Q62744|lt=yang|1=Yin and yang}}, that is, the male and positive principle, and are therefore considered lucky.&lt;/ref&gt; Its use then spread to Korea and, from there, to Japan. Following its arrival in Japan together with {{ill|Buddhism|en|Buddhism|qid=Q748|lt=Buddhism|1=Buddhism}} in the 6th century, the pagoda became one of the focal points of the early Japanese ''[[:en:Garan|Garan]]''.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;Temple compound, ideally composed of seven buildings.&lt;/ref&gt; In Japan it evolved in shape, size and function, finally losing its original role as a reliquary.&lt;ref name="nk"&gt;{{Harvnb|Fujita|Koga|2008|pp=79–81}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also became extremely common, while on the Asian continent it is rare.&lt;ref name="scheidpa"&gt;Scheid, Japanische Pagoden&lt;/ref&gt;

With the birth of new sects in later centuries, the pagoda lost importance and was consequently relegated to the margins of the ''garan''. Temples of the [[Jōdo-shū|Jōdo]] sects rarely have a pagoda.&lt;ref name="jaanustou"/&gt; During the {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}} the {{ill|Zen|en|Zen|qid=Q7953|lt=Zen|1=Zen}} sect arrived in Japan and their temples do not normally include a pagoda.

Pagodas originally were reliquaries and did not contain sacred images, but in Japan many, for example [[Hōryū-ji]]'s five-storied pagoda, enshrine statues of various deities.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; To allow the opening of a room at the ground floor and therefore create some usable space, the pagoda's central shaft, which originally reached the ground, was shortened to the upper stories, where it rested on supporting beams.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; In that room are enshrined statues of the temple's main objects of worship. Inside [[Shingon]] pagodas there can be paintings of deities called {{nihongo|Shingon Hasso|真言八祖}}; on the ceiling and on the central shaft there can be decorations and paintings.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;

===Design and structure evolution===
The edge of a pagoda's {{ill|Eaves|en|Eaves|qid=Q163972|lt=Eaves|1=Eaves}} forms a straight line, with each following edge being shorter than the other. The more difference in length (a parameter called {{nihongo|''teigen''|逓減|gradual diminution}} in Japanese) between stories, the more solid and secure the pagoda seems to be. Both ''teigen'' and the {{ill|Finial|en|Finial|qid=Q1406758|lt=Finial|1=Finial}} are greater in older pagodas, giving them a sense of solidity.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; Vice versa, recent pagodas tend to be steeper and have shorter finials, creating svelter silhouettes.

From the structural point of view, old pagodas had a {{nihongo|stone base|心礎|shinso}} over which stood the {{nihongo|main pillar|心柱|shinbashira}}. Around it would be erected the first storey's supporting pillars, then the beams supporting the eaves and so on. The other stories would be built over the completed one, and on top of the main pillar would at last be inserted the finial.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; In later eras, all of the supporting structures would be erected at once, and later to them were fixed parts of more cosmetic function.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;

Early pagodas had a central pillar that penetrated deep into the ground. With the evolution of architectural techniques, it was first put to rest on a base stone at ground level, then it was shortened and put to rest on beams at the second storey to allow the opening of a room.&lt;ref name="jaanustou"/&gt;&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;

Their role within the temple declined gradually while they were being functionally replaced by {{ill|Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)|en|Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)|qid=Q17051413|lt=main halls|1=Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)}} (''kondō''). Originally the centerpiece of the Shingon and Tendai ''[[:en:Garan|Garan]]'', they were moved later to its edges and finally abandoned, in particular by the Zen sects, the last to appear in Japan.

===Loss of importance of the pagoda within the garan===
[[Image:飛鳥寺復元図.jpg|thumb|left|A reconstruction of {{ill|Asuka-dera|en|Asuka-dera|qid=Q779755|lt=Asuka-dera|1=Asuka-dera}}'s original layout with a pagoda at its center]]

Because of the relics they contained, wooden pagodas used to be the centerpiece of the ''[[shichidō garan|garan]]'', the seven edifices considered indispensable for a temple.&lt;ref name="tamura"&gt;*{{cite book   |last=Tamura   |first=Yoshiro   |title=Japanese Buddhism - A Cultural History   |publisher=Kosei Publishing Company   |location=Tokyo   |year=2000   |edition=First   |pages=40–41 pages   |isbn=4-333-01684-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They gradually lost importance and were replaced by the ''{{ill|Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)|en|Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)|qid=Q17051413|lt=kondō|1=Main Hall (Japanese Buddhism)}}'' (golden hall), because of the magic powers believed to lie within the images the building housed. This loss of status was so complete that Zen schools, which arrived late in Japan from China, normally do not have any pagoda in their ''garan''. The layout of four early temples clearly illustrates this trend: they are in chronological order {{ill|Asuka-dera|en|Asuka-dera|qid=Q779755|lt=Asuka-dera|1=Asuka-dera}}, [[Shitennō-ji]], [[Hōryū-ji]], and [[Yakushi-ji]].&lt;ref name="tamura"/&gt; In the first, the pagoda was at the very center of the ''garan'' surrounded by three small ''kondō'' (see the reconstruction of the temple's original layout). In the second, a single ''kondō'' is at the center of the temple and the pagoda lies in front of it. At Hōryū-ji, they are one next to the other. Yakushi-ji has a single, large ''kondō'' at the center with two pagodas on the sides. The same evolution can be observed in Buddhist temples in China.

==Stone pagodas==
[[File:16-tier-buttou.jpg|thumb|150 px|A rare 16-storey stone pagoda at {{ill|Chōshō-ji|en|Chōshō-ji|qid=Q2972149|lt=Chōshō-ji|1=Chōshō-ji}} in {{ill|Kamakura|en|Kamakura|qid=Q200267|lt=Kamakura|1=Kamakura}}]]
Stone pagodas (''sekitō'') are usually made of materials like {{ill|Apatite|en|Apatite|qid=Q178397|lt=Apatite|1=Apatite}} or {{ill|Granite|en|Granite|qid=Q41177|lt=Granite|1=Granite}}, are much smaller than wooden ones and are finely carved.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; Often they bear {{ill|Sanskrit|en|Sanskrit|qid=Q11059|lt=Sanskrit|1=Sanskrit}} inscriptions, Buddhist figurines and Japanese lunar calendar dates ''[[:en:Nengō|Nengō]]''. Like wooden ones, they are mostly classifiable on the basis of the number of stories as ''tasōtō'' or ''hōtō'', but there are however some styles hardly ever seen in wood, namely the ''gorintō'', the ''muhōtō'', the ''hōkyōintō'' and the ''kasatōba''.&lt;ref name="jaanusseki"&gt;JAANUS, ''Sekitou''&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Tasōtō'' or ''tajūtō''===
With a few very rare exceptions, ''tasōtō'' (also called ''tajūtō'', 多層塔) have an odd number of stories, normally comprised between three and thirteen.&lt;ref&gt;JAANUS, ''Tasoutou''&lt;/ref&gt; They are usually less than three meters tall, but they can occasionally be much taller. The tallest still extant is a 13-storey pagoda at {{ill|Hannya-ji|en|Hannya-ji|qid=Q1576651|lt=Hannya-ji|1=Hannya-ji}} in {{ill|Nara (city)|en|Nara (city)|qid=Q169134|lt=Nara|1=Nara (city)}}, which is 14.12 m. They are often dedicated to Buddha and offer no usable room, but some have a small space inside which holds a sacred image.&lt;ref name="jaanusseki"/&gt; In the oldest extant specimen, while the edge of each storey are parallel to the ground, each successive storey is smaller than the next, resulting in a strongly slanted curve. More modern ''tasōtō'' tend to have a less pronounced curve.
*{{Commons category-inline|Tasōtō}}

===''Hōtō''===
[[File:Houtou - Ankokuron-ji.jpg|150px|left|thumb|A ''hōtō'' at {{ill|Ankokuron-ji|en|Ankokuron-ji|qid=Q2850357|lt=Ankokuron-ji|1=Ankokuron-ji}}]]
A {{nihongo|''hōtō''|宝塔|1=Treasure Pagoda|2=de|3=Schatzpagode|4=ja|5=宝塔|lit. jewel stupa}} is a pagoda consisting of four parts: a low foundation stone, a cylindrical body with a rounded top, a four-sided roof and a {{ill|Finial|en|Finial|qid=Q1406758|lt=Finial|1=Finial}}.&lt;ref name="jaanushoutou"/&gt; Unlike the similar ''tahōtō'' (see section below) it has no enclosed pent roof (''{{ill|Mokoshi|en|Mokoshi|qid=Q3319398|lt=Mokoshi|1=Mokoshi}}'') around its circular core.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; Like the  ''tahōtō'' it takes its name from Buddhist deity [[:ja:多宝如来|Tahō Nyorai]].  The ''hōtō'' was born during the early {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian period|1=Heian period}}, when the {{ill|Tendai|en|Tendai|qid=Q855964|lt=Tendai|1=Tendai}} and [[Shingon]] sects first arrived in Japan. Indeed, because it does not exist on the Asian continent, it is believed to have been invented in Japan.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;

There used to exist full-size ''hōtō'', but almost only miniature ones survive, normally made of stone and/or metal.&lt;ref name="jaanushoutou"&gt;JAANUS, ''Houtou''&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Commons category-inline|Hōtō}}

===''Gorintō''===
''{{main|Gorintō}}''

[[File:Mimizuka-M1773 corrected.jpg|thumb|150 px|A ''gorintō'']]The {{nihongo|''gorintō''|五輪塔|1=Gorintō|1=Gorintō|lit. five ring tower}} is a pagoda found almost only in Japan and believed to have been first adopted by the [[Shingon]] and {{ill|Tendai|en|Tendai|qid=Q855964|lt=Tendai|1=Tendai}} sects during the mid {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian period|1=Heian period}}.&lt;ref name="jaanusgo"&gt;JAANUS - ''Gorintou''&lt;/ref&gt;  It is used as a tomb marker or as a cenotaph, and is therefore a common sight in Buddhist temples and cemeteries. It is also called {{nihongo|''gorinsotōba''|五輪卒塔婆}} ("five-ringed stupa") or {{nihongo|''goringedatsu''|五輪解脱}}, where the term ''sotoba'' is a transliteration of the Sanskrit word [[stupa]].&lt;ref name="IK"/&gt;

In all its variations, the ''gorintō'' is made of five blocks (although that number can sometimes be difficult to detect), each having one of the five shapes which symbolize of the [[:en:Five elements (Japanese philosophy)|Five Elements]] believed to be the basic building blocks of reality: earth (cube), water (sphere), fire (pyramid), air (crescent), and ether, energy, or void (lotus).&lt;ref name="jaanusgo"/&gt; The last two rings (air and ether) are visually and conceptually united into a single subgroup.
*{{Commons category-inline|Gorintōs|gorintō}}

===''Hōkyōintō''===
{{main|Hōkyōintō}}
[[File:Jikoji hokyointo.JPG|thumb|left|150 px|A ''hōkyōintō'']]The {{nihongo|''hōkyōintō''|宝篋印塔|1=Hōkyōintō|2=ja|3=宝篋印塔|4=fr|5=Hōkyōintō|6=nl|7=Hōkyōintō|1=Hōkyōintō|1=Hōkyōintō}} is a large stone pagoda so called because it originally contained the {{nihongo|Hōkyōin|宝篋印}} {{nihongo|{{ill|Dharani|en|Dharani|qid=Q1207590|lt=Dharani|1=Dharani}}|陀羅尼}} {{ill|Sutra|en|Sutra|qid=Q209680|lt=Sutra|1=Sutra}}.&lt;ref name="IK"&gt;Iwanami Kōjien Japanese dictionary&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally used as a cenotaph for the King of [[:en:Wuyue (Ten Kingdoms)|Wuyue]] - {{ill|Qian Liu|en|Qian Liu|qid=Q1074727|lt=Qian Liu|1=Qian Liu}} in China.&lt;ref name="IK"/&gt;

The ''hōkyōintō'' tradition in Japan is believed to have begun during the {{ill|Asuka period|en|Asuka period|qid=Q210688|lt=Asuka period|1=Asuka period}} (550–710 CE).&lt;ref name="YMM"/&gt; They used to be made of wood and started to be made in stone only during the Kamakura period.&lt;ref name="YMM"/&gt; It is also during this period that they started to be used as tombstones and cenotaphs.&lt;ref name="YMM"/&gt;  The ''hōkyōintō'' started to be made in its present form during the {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}}.&lt;ref name="IK"/&gt; Like a ''gorintō'', it is divided in five main sections representing the five elements of Japanese cosmology.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The sūtra it sometimes hides contain all the pious deeds of a [[:en:Tathagata|Tathagata]] Buddha, and the faithful believe that, by praying in front of the ''hōkyōintō'', their sins will be canceled, during their lives they will be protected from disasters and after death they will go to heaven.&lt;ref name="YMM"&gt;Yatsushiro Municipal Museum&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Commons category-inline|Hōkyōintō}}

===''Muhōtō'' or ''rantō''===
[[File:Engakuji Muhōtō.jpg|thumb|170 px|A ''muhōtō'']]
The {{nihongo|''muhōtō''|無縫塔|lit. no stitch tower}} or {{nihongo|''rantō''|卵塔|lit. egg tower}} is a pagoda which usually marks the gravesite of a Buddhist priest. It was originally used by just the Zen schools, but it was later adopted by the others too.&lt;ref name="jaanusmu"&gt;JAANUS - ''Muhoutou''&lt;/ref&gt;  Its characteristic egg-shaped upper portion is supposed to be a [[:en:Phallic symbol|Phallic symbol]].

*{{Commons category-inline|Muhōtō}}

===''Kasatōba''===
A {{nihongo|''kasatōba''|笠塔婆|umbrella stupa}} (see photo in the gallery below) is simply a square stone post placed over a square base and covered by a pyramidal roof. Over the roof stand a bowl-shaped stone and a lotus-shaped stone. The shaft can be carved with Sanskrit words or low-relief images of Buddhist gods. Within the shaft there can be stone wheels which allow the faithful to turn the stupa around while praying as with a {{ill|Prayer wheel|en|Prayer wheel|qid=Q80876|lt=Prayer wheel|1=Prayer wheel}}.&lt;ref name="jaanuskasatouba"&gt;JAANUS - Kasatouba&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Commons category-inline|Kasatōba}}

===''Sōrintō''===
The {{nihongo|''sōrintō''|相輪橖}} is a type of small pagoda consisting just of a pole and a ''{{ill|Sōrin|en|Sōrin|qid=Q834370|lt=Sōrin|1=Sōrin}}''.

==Wooden pagodas==

===''Tasōtō''===
[[File:Yakushiji Nara11s5bs4200.jpg|thumb|left|150 px|Yakushi-ji's Eastern Pagoda]]Wooden ''tasōtō'' are pagodas with an odd number of stories. Some may appear to have an even number because of the presence between stories of purely decorative enclosed pent roofs called ''{{ill|Mokoshi|en|Mokoshi|qid=Q3319398|lt=Mokoshi|1=Mokoshi}}''&lt;ref group=note&gt;Besides being decorative in themselves,they are also used also to hide structural components which would otherwise mar the pagoda's feel.&lt;/ref&gt; A famous example is [[Yakushi-ji]]'s eastern pagoda (see photo to the left), which seems to have six stories but has in fact only three. Another is the ''tahōtō'' (see below), which has a single storey, plus a ''mokoshi'' under its roof, and seems therefore to have two stories.&lt;ref group=note&gt;On the subject, see also the articles ''{{ill|Hisashi (architecture)|en|Hisashi (architecture)|qid=Q7884608|lt=Hisashi|1=Hisashi (architecture)}}'', {{ill|Mokoshi|en|Mokoshi|qid=Q3319398|lt=Mokoshi|1=Mokoshi}} and {{ill|Omoya|en|Omoya|qid=Q3326980|lt=Moya|1=Omoya}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There existed specimen with seven or nine stories, but all extant ones have either three (and are therefore called {{nihongo|''sanjū-no-tō''|三重塔|1=Three-storied pagoda|2=ja|3=三重塔|4=zh|5=三重塔|1=Three-storied pagodas|lit. three-storied pagoda}}) or five (and are called {{nihongo|''gojū-no-tō''|五重塔|lit. five-storied pagoda}}.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;（Tanzan Jinja in Sakurai, {{ill|Nara (city)|en|Nara (city)|qid=Q169134|lt=Nara|1=Nara (city)}}, has a pagoda having thirteen, which however for structural reasons is classified separately, and is not considered a ''tasōtō''.)&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The oldest three-storied pagoda stands at Nara's [[Hokki-ji]] and was built between 685 and 706.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The oldest extant five-storied pagoda belongs to [[Hōryū-ji]] and was built some time during the {{ill|Asuka period|en|Asuka period|qid=Q210688|lt=Asuka period|1=Asuka period}} (538–710).  The tallest wooden ''tasōtō'' belongs to [[Tō-ji]], Kyoto. It has five stories and is 54 m tall.
*{{Commons category-inline|tasōtō}}

=== ''Hōtō'' ===
[[File:Yakuo-ji, Yugi Tower 05.jpg|thumb|150 px|A ''hōtō'' at Yakuō-ji, Tokushima prefecture]]A wooden ''hōtō'' is a rare type of pagoda consisting of four parts: a low foundation stone, a cylindrical body with a rounded top, a pyramidal roof and a {{ill|Finial|en|Finial|qid=Q1406758|lt=Finial|1=Finial}}.&lt;ref name="jaanushoutou"/&gt; Unlike the similar ''tahōtō'' (see section below) it has no square enclosed pent roof (''{{ill|Mokoshi|en|Mokoshi|qid=Q3319398|lt=Mokoshi|1=Mokoshi}}'') around its cylindrical core.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; Like the  ''tahōtō'' it takes its name from Buddhist deity [[:ja:多宝如来|Tahō Nyorai]].  The ''hōtō'' was born during the early {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian period|1=Heian period}}, when the {{ill|Tendai|en|Tendai|qid=Q855964|lt=Tendai|1=Tendai}} and [[Shingon]] Buddhist sects first arrived in Japan.

There used to be many full-size ''hōtō'', but almost only miniature ones survive, normally made of stone and/or metal. A good example of full-size ''hōtō'' can be seen at {{ill|Ikegami Honmon-ji|en|Ikegami Honmon-ji|qid=Q1537312|lt=Ikegami Honmon-ji|1=Ikegami Honmon-ji}} in {{ill|Nishi-magome Station|en|Nishi-magome Station|qid=Q1038919|lt=Nishi-magome|1=Nishi-magome Station}}, {{ill|Tokyo|en|Tokyo|qid=Q1490|lt=Tokyo|1=Tokyo}}. The pagoda is 17.4 meter tall and 5.7 meter wide.&lt;ref name="jaanushoutou"/&gt;

*{{Commons category-inline|Hōtō}}

===''Tahōtō''===
{{main|Tahōtō}}
[[File:Negoroji03s3200.jpg|thumb|150 px|left|Negoro-ji's ''daitō'']]The ''tahōtō'' is a type of wooden pagoda unique for having an even number of stories (two), the first square with a rounded core, the second circular. This style of ''tō'' was created surrounding the cylindrical base of a ''hōtō'' (see above) with a square, roofed corridor called ''{{ill|Mokoshi|en|Mokoshi|qid=Q3319398|lt=Mokoshi|1=Mokoshi}}''.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;For reasons of space, however, the wall separating the ''mokoshi'' from the core of the pagoda is present only in large ''tahōtō'' called ''daitō'' (see the next section).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The core of the pagoda has just one storey with its ceiling below the circular second storey, which is inaccessible. Like the ''tasōtō'' and the ''{{ill|Rōmon|en|Rōmon|qid=Q3458957|lt=Rōmon|1=Rōmon}}'', in spite of its appearance it therefore offers usable space only at the ground floor.&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt;

Because its kind does not exist either in Korea or in China, it is believed to have been invented in Japan during the {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian period|1=Heian period}} (794–1185). The ''tahōtō'' was important enough to be considered one of the seven indispensable buildings (the so-called ''[[shichidō garan]]'') of a [[Shingon]] temple.&lt;ref name="jaanusdaitou"&gt;JAANUS, Daitou&lt;/ref&gt; {{ill|Kūkai|en|Kūkai|qid=Q222227|lt=Kūkai|1=Kūkai}} himself is responsible for the construction of the ''tahōto'' at {{ill|Mount Kōya|en|Mount Kōya|qid=Q535065|lt=Mount Kōya|1=Mount Kōya}}'s {{ill|Kongōbu-ji|en|Kongōbu-ji|qid=Q1203429|lt=Kongōbu-ji|1=Kongōbu-ji}}.

====''Daitō''====
[[File:Negoroji-daitou-flooplan.svg|thumb|180 px|The floorplan of Negoro-ji's ''daitō'']]Usually the base of a ''tahōtō'' is 3-''{{ill|Ken (unit)|en|Ken (unit)|qid=Q3195007|lt=ken|1=Ken (unit)}}'' across with four main, supporting pillars called {{nihongo|''shitenbashira''|四天柱}} at the corners (see drawing).&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The room the ''shitenbashira'' form houses a sanctuary where the main objects of worship (the ''[[gohonzon]]'') are enshrined.

Larger, 5x5 ''ken'' ''tahōtō'' however exist and are called {{nihongo|''daitō''|大塔|lit. large pagoda}} because of their dimensions. This is the only type of ''tahōtō'' to retain the original structure with a wall separating the corridor (''mokoshi'') from the core of the structure. This type of pagoda used to be common but, of all ''daitō'' ever built, only three are still extant. One is at [[:en:Wakayama prefecture|Wakayama prefecture]]'s [[Negoro-ji]], another at {{ill|Kongōbu-ji|en|Kongōbu-ji|qid=Q1203429|lt=Kongōbu-ji|1=Kongōbu-ji}}, again in Wakayama, and the last at Kirihata-dera, [[:en:Tokushima prefecture|Tokushima prefecture]].&lt;ref name="jaanusdaitou"/&gt; The ''daitō'' at Kongōbu-ji was founded by {{ill|Shingon Buddhism|en|Shingon Buddhism|qid=Q550182|lt=Shingon sect|1=Shingon Buddhism}}'s  {{ill|Kūkai|en|Kūkai|qid=Q222227|lt=Kūkai|1=Kūkai}}. The specimen found at Negoro-ji (see photo above) is 30.85 meters tall and a {{ill|National Treasure (Japan)|en|National Treasure (Japan)|qid=Q1139795|lt=National Treasure|1=National Treasure (Japan)}}.

*{{Commons category-inline|Daitō}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Tahōtō}}

===''Sotōba''===
Often offertory strips of wood with five subdivisions and covered with elaborate inscriptions called {{nihongo|''sotōba''|卒塔婆}} can be found at tombs in Japanese cemeteries (see photo in the gallery below).&lt;ref name="nk"/&gt; The inscriptions contain {{ill|Sutra|en|Sutra|qid=Q209680|lt=Sutra|1=Sutra}} and the posthumous name of the dead person. Their name derives from the Sanskrit [[:en:Stūpa|Stūpa]], and they can be also considered pagodas.
*{{Commons category-inline|Sotōba}}

==Gallery of pagodas in Japan==
&lt;gallery perrow="4" widths="170px" heights="130px"&gt;

File:Hokokubyou 17.jpg|A ''gorintō''
File:Mizumadera hokyointo.jpg|A ''hōkyōintō''
File:Ashikaga Mochiujis Houtou.jpg|A ''hōtō''
File:Ankokuronji-Garden.jpg|A stone ''tasōtō''
File:Hannyaji Stone Kasatoba.jpg|Two ''kasatōba'' at Hannya-ji, Nara
File:Ichijoji Kasai13bs4272.jpg|{{ill|Ichijō-ji|en|Ichijō-ji|qid=Q3147650|lt=Ichijō-ji|1=Ichijō-ji}}'s ''sanjū-no-tō'' (three storied pagoda). It was built in 1171.
File:Murou-ji 4.jpg|[[Murō-ji]]'s ''gojū-no-tō'' (five storied pagoda). It was built in 800.
File:20100723 Miyajima Itsukushima 5140.jpg|A pagoda at a Shinto shrine, Itsukushima Shrine
File:Sotoba.jpg|A ''sotōba''. Clearly visible is the division in five sections
File:Hitsujisaki_jinja_Sourintou.JPG|A ''sorintō''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*{{ill|Shinbashira|en|Shinbashira|qid=Q11583259|lt=Shinbashira|1=Shinbashira}}, the suspended wooden column inside

==Notes==
&lt;references group="note"/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons Category|Pagodas in Japan}}
* Iwanami {{nihongo|{{ill|Kōjien|en|Kōjien|qid=Q1192611|lt=Kōjien|1=Kōjien}}|広辞苑}} Japanese dictionary, 6th Edition (2008), DVD version
*{{cite web
|title=JAANUS
|url=http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/
|publisher=[[Japanese Architecture and Art Net Users System]]
|access-date=19 August 2010
}}
*{{cite book
 | title=Nihon Kenchiku-shi
 | editor=Fujita Masaya, Koga Shūsaku
 | publisher=Shōwa-dō
 | date=April 10, 1990
 | edition=September 30, 2008
 | isbn=4-8122-9805-9
 | language=ja
 |ref=CITEREFFujitaKoga2008
 }}
*{{cite web|last=Scheid|first=Bernhard|title=Japanische Pagoden|url=http://www.univie.ac.at/rel_jap/bauten/bilder_pagoden.htm|publisher=University of Vienna|access-date=19 August 2010|language=de}}
* [http://www.city.yatsushiro.kumamoto.jp/museum/event/per_ex1/pdf/hokyointo.pdf Shinkō no Katachi - Hōkyōintō], Yatsushiro Municipal Museum, accessed on September 18, 2008 (in Japanese)

{{Japanese architectural elements}}
{{Buddhist temples in Japan}}



[[en:Japanese pagoda]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[de:Tō]]
[[es:Pagoda japonesa]]
[[fr:Tō]]
[[it:Pagoda giapponese]]
[[nl:Tō]]
[[sl:Japonska pagoda]]
[[th:เจดีย์ญี่ปุ่น]]
[[vi:Chùa Nhật Bản]]
{{wikidata link|Q2465311}}
[[Category:Japanese architectural history]]
[[Category:Japanese Buddhist architecture]]
[[Category:Pagodas in Japan| ]]
[[Category:Shinto shrines]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]</text>
      <sha1>p69udldg4a75zkw4ag3qaokgzdpbbab</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
