<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jingū Guards</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13007</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3595596</id>
      <parentid>3572745</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:19:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3595596</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8118" sha1="8hy5r8tgapk7ww25xiu6zua7zov7kj3" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:神宮衛士]]



[[File:Eji Mihari Jo.jpg|thumb|伊勢神宮内宮にある、衛士見張所。]]
'''Jingū Eji''' (じんぐうえじ、じんぐうえし) refers to the title once bestowed upon the government officials who served as security guards at {{ill|Ise Shrine|en|Ise Shrine|qid=Q687168|lt=Ise Jingū|1=Ise Grand Shrine}}. Today, the name is retained by the staff of the religious corporation “Jingū.”

== Origin and Overview ==
At the time of the enshrinement of the deity at the shrine, it is said that the subordinates (the "Eighty-Friend Group") of {{ill|Yamatohime-no-mikoto|en|Yamatohime-no-mikoto|qid=Q4388732|lt=Yamatohime-no-mikoto|1=Yamatohime-no-mikoto}} who accompanied {{ill|Mononobe Toshichine no Mikoto|ja|物部十千根命|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mononobe Toshichine no Mikoto|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} were assigned to security duties. Later, inspectors ({{ill|Kenbiishi|ja|検非違使|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kenbiishi|1=Office of Police and Justice|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q497217}}) were appointed as retainers of the Daijinguji to investigate lawbreakers within the territory. However, those who directly assumed the role of palace guardians were the {{ill|Neogi|ja|禰宜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Neogi|1=Negi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11594490}} and the {{ill|Ōuchibito|ja|大内人|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ōuchibito|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, with these [[:en:Kannushi|Shinto priests]] commanding the estate officials and standing guard day and night. Thereafter, the security of the shrine’s domain was transferred to the warrior class, and even within that class, {{ill|Yamada bugyō|en|Yamada bugyō|qid=Q4275043|lt=Yamada Bugyō|1=Yamada bugyō}} made the protection of both the {{ill|Kōtai Jingū|lt=Kōtai Jingū|lt=Inner Shrine|ja|皇大神宮|lt=Kōtai Jingū|lt=Inner Shrine|lt_ja=内宮|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Inner Shrine|comment=enwiki is a redirect}} and the {{ill|Kōtai Jingū|lt=Kōtai Jingū|lt=Outer Shrine|ja|外宮|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Outer Shrine|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 豊受大神宮}} his primary duty. During the special security arrangements for the Shikinen Sengu in the Edo period, the neighboring {{ill|Toba Domain|en|Toba Domain|qid=Q1396816|lt=Toba Domain|1=Toba Domain}} assumed the duty, with 330 samurai of Toba Domain assigned to security during the September ceremony of {{ill|Kaei|en|Kaei|qid=Q1146125|lt=Kaei|1=Kaei}} 2.

== Chronology of the Official Period ==
On January 13, Meiji 27, an Imperial Ordinance titled “Regarding the Jingū Eji Chief and Ejis” (Imperial Ordinance No. 5, January 13, Meiji 27) was promulgated. At that time, one Eji Chief and 12 Ejis were established, all of whom were accorded the status of {{ill|Hanninkan|ja|判任官|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hanninkan|1=hanninkan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11396615}}.

On August 12, Meiji 31, a new Imperial Ordinance titled “Regarding the Jingū Eji Chief and Ejis” (Imperial Ordinance No. 189, August 12, Meiji 31) was issued, thereby repealing the Meiji 27 ordinance. At that time, one Eji Chief, two Eji Vice-Chiefs, and 30 Ejis were appointed, all receiving the status of {{ill|Hanninkan|ja|判任官|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hanninkan|1=hanninkan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11396615}}.

On April 1, Meiji 33, the number of Ejis was increased to 40.&lt;ref&gt;Imperial Ordinance No. 91, March 30, Meiji 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 20, Meiji 45, it was decided to discontinue regulating the number of Ejis by Imperial Ordinance, and instead, the Minister of Home Affairs was given the authority to determine the number. Additionally, the Eji Chief was accorded the status of a {{ill|Sōninkan|ja|奏任官|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Sōninkan|1=sōninkan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11445526}}.&lt;ref&gt;Imperial Ordinance No. 90, April 20, Meiji 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Uniform Regulations during the Official Period ==
On December 16, Taishō 10, an Imperial Ordinance titled “Regarding the Uniform Regulations for the Jingū Eji Chief, Eji Vice-Chiefs, and Ejis” (Imperial Ordinance No. 476, December 16, Taishō 10) was promulgated, thereby stipulating the uniforms for the Eji Chief and below.

According to this regulation, the uniforms for the Eji Chief and below were classified as:
# Formal attire (a frock-coat style with a stand-up collar and with shoulder insignia attached)
# Ceremonial attire (a frock-coat style with a stand-up collar and with shoulder insignia)
# Everyday attire (a frock-coat style with a stand-up collar and with shoulder insignia)

== As Employees of the Religious Corporation “Jingū” ==
After the war, with their numbers reduced by half and the official status of government officials relinquished, the positions of Eji Chief, Eji Vice-Chiefs, and Ejis were established under Article 31 of the “Jingū Regulations,” a regulation under the Religious Corporations Act governing the religious corporation “Jingū.”

According to Article 39 of the Jingū Regulations, “the Eji Chief, under orders from his superior, shall direct and supervise the Eji Vice-Chiefs and Ejis,” the Eji Vice-Chiefs are to assist the Eji Chief in the execution of security duties, and the Ejis are to engage in security and forest protection under the orders of their superiors.

Currently, approximately 60 Ejis serve as staff in the security division of the Jingū Shichō, the administrative body of the shrine, safeguarding the shrine grounds day and night.

They also undertake the duties of the Self-Defense Fire Brigade within the shrine premises, and a fire engine is stationed there. (However, members of the “Jingū Fire Brigade”—the shrine’s own self-defense fire team—are not all Ejis, as they include not only shrine employees but also local residents selected from among volunteers.)

== Current Uniform Regulations ==
Presently, the Eji Chief, Eji Vice-Chiefs, and Ejis all wear the uniforms prescribed by the Jingū Shichō. Their winter uniform is a suit-style outfit in black with a double-breasted design featuring six buttons (three fastened) and common-fabric shoulder insignia; the summer uniform is a suit-style outfit in gray with a single-breasted design featuring four buttons and common-fabric shoulder insignia; the peak summer uniform consists of a light gray long-sleeved shirt with a gray shoulder insignia paired with gray trousers; the raincoat is a dark navy double-breasted trench coat with three buttons; and the cold-weather overcoat is a black double-breasted garment with eight buttons. The Rank insignia are worn on the left chest, and the necktie is either black or dark navy.

The cap bears the {{ill|Chrysanthemum Crest|ja|菊花紋章|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Chrysanthemum Crest|1=Kikumon (chrysanthemum crests)|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11082563}} as its hat badge, and for ceremonial events, a white decorative cord is attached to the uniform.
== Related Articles ==
* {{ill|Ise Shrine|en|Ise Shrine|qid=Q687168|lt=Ise no Jingū|1=Ise Grand Shrine}}
* {{ill|Eishi|ja|衛視|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Eishi|1=eishi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11626335}}
* {{ill|Security guard|en|Security guard|qid=Q856887|lt=Security Guard|1=Security guard}}
* {{ill|Gatekeeper|ja|守衛|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Gatekeeper|1=guard|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q680928}}
* {{ill|Eji|ja|衛士|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Eji|1=eji|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11626291}}
* {{ill|Shinjin|ja|神人|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinjin|1=Jinin|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11588676}}
{{Japanese-history-stub}}
{{shinto-stub}}

{{translated page|ja|神宮衛士|version=94755568|comment=Imported full ja history}}


&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[ja:神宮衛士]]
{{wikidata link|Q11589497}}
[[Category:Ise Shrine]]
[[Category:Public safety]]
[[Category:Security]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]</text>
      <sha1>8hy5r8tgapk7ww25xiu6zua7zov7kj3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
