<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jinmyōchō Kōshō Dodai</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3600606</id>
      <parentid>3595607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-05T04:46:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Sn crud]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23993722414|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3600606</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7985" sha1="2zju52u145ivzupz70l7f49het2tm97" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:神名帳考証土代]]



{{Contains special characters}}
[[File:Ban Nobutomo Zenshu honbun cropped Ban Nobutomo Zenshu Vol 1 Frame 8.jpg|thumb|300px|The main text of ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō'' included in volume 1 of the ''Ban Nobutomo Zenshū''&lt;ref&gt;edited by {{ill|Kenkichi Ichijima|ja|市島謙吉|1=Kenkichi Ichishima|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11480125}}, ''Ban Nobutomo Zenshū'' Vol. 1, {{ill|Kokusho Kankōkai|ja|国書刊行会 (1905–1922)|lt=Kokusho Kankōkai|lt_ja=國書刊行會}}, 1907, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Jinmyōchō Kōshō Dodai''' (jinmyōchō kōshō dodai) is a work by {{ill|Ban Nobutomo|ja|伴信友|1=Ban Nobutomo|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q4346747}} that critically examines the shrines (shiki-nai-sha) listed in the {{ill|Engishiki Jinmyōchō|ja|延喜式神名帳}} (hereafter the ''Jinmyōchō''). Completed in {{ill|Bunka era|ja|文化 (元号)|lt=Bunka|lt_ja=文化|1=Bunka|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q1373146}} 10 (1813), it comprises 69 volumes. It is also simply called '''Jinmyōchō Kōshō''', but since a work of the same name by {{ill|Deguchi Nobunaga|ja|出口延経|1=Deguchi Nobutsune|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q108780926}} exists, the term “Dodai” is appended to distinguish it. Incidentally, “Dodai” means “draft.”

== Overview ==

Research on Shikinaisha has been conducted in numerous works from {{ill|Bunki era|ja|文亀|1=Bunki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q1324885}} 3 (1503) with {{ill|Kanetomo Yoshida|ja|吉田兼倶|1=Yoshida Kanetomo|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q723266}}’s ''Engi-shiki Jinmyōchō Tōchū'' onward through Ban’s time, and it can be said that premodern studies of shrines and shrine history were almost entirely focused on Shikinaisha. This book similarly provides critical examination of the names, enshrined deities, founding, divine rank, history, development, location, and related shrines of Shikinaisha (and some {{ill|Kokushi Genzaisha|ja|国史見在社|1=Shakaku|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q10444029}}). In conducting his analysis, Ban cites the original texts of the sources he uses and appends his own observations under labels such as “Shinyū an” and “Shinyū un,” demonstrating a rigorous approach grounded in bibliology and textual criticism. Even among earlier scholarly achievements, its breadth and fidelity have made it one of the most important works in its genre&lt;ref name="西牟田"/&gt;. Incidentally, volumes 1 and 2 of the later six-volume ''Jinja Shikō'' correspond to the opening volumes of this work{{Efn2|''Jinja Shikō'' was completed in {{ill|Tenpō era|ja|天保|1=Tenpō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q1369045}} 12 (1841).}}.

== Compilation ==

According to the colophon entitled “Kōgō no koto,” Ban collated and edited the text of the Jinmyōchō against 24 manuscripts, adding his critical notes, and finalized his draft on the intercalary 11th month, 21st day of {{ill|Bunka era|ja|文化 (元号)|lt=Bunka|lt_ja=文化|1=Bunka|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q1373146}} 10. However, the colophon of one of the surviving eight-volume autograph copies indicates that when Ban journeyed to the capital from {{ill|Wakasa Province|ja|若狭国|1=Wakasa Province|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q1053713}} in Bunka 1, he borrowed the ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō Kenroku'' from {{ill|Momoki Ueda|ja|上田百樹|lt=Momoki Ueda|lt_ja=上田百木}} {{Efn2|This “Kenroku” is said to have been supplemented by Kiyosai Kisaya, Masami Watarai, Hisao Arakida, Momoki Ueda, and others. See “Jinmyōchō Kōshō” for details on the Kenroku.}} and, dividing the work with {{ill|Yoshiji Okita|ja|興田吉従}}, transcribed it, completing the transcription on April 15 of Bunka 4, three years later. Thereafter, by using this Kenroku as a reference, he embarked on the collation of the Jinmyōchō text itself and spent a further seven years bringing the work to completion&lt;ref name="西牟田"/&gt;.

== Authorial Approach ==

The autograph colophon states:  
&gt; “Of the collated texts, there are passages reflecting syncretic ideas such as Confucianism and Buddhism that do not accord with ancient meanings; those that do not align with my understanding have, for the most part, been omitted and discarded.”

This indicates Ban’s stance of excluding foreign religious and philosophical influences and adhering to ahistorical traditions. Although he initially titled his draft ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō''{{Efn2|The manuscript title slip of the eight-volume autograph reads ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō''.}}, the work developed substantially in content, and he positioned it as “a draft to properly demonstrate the correct critical examination of the Jinmyōchō.” Consequently, he undertook comprehensive research methods—collecting geographic and shrine records of regions across Japan, consulting earlier critical texts, considering theories of local scholars, and examining popular beliefs—thus pioneering what might be called a new scholarly field of textual criticism. He also clearly cited his sources and preserved quoted passages in their original form, demonstrating a strong respect for primary materials&lt;ref name="西牟田"/&gt;. Furthermore, even after completing the draft, he continued to incorporate new insights as they arose, striving for greater perfection, and concluding his colophon with words of expectation for collaboration from like-minded scholars:  
&gt; “May co-researchers throughout the provinces arise and refine and complete this work,”  
reflecting his academic integrity&lt;ref name="西牟田"/&gt;.

== Additional Notes ==

Approximately thirty different manuscript copies of this work are known, though some indicate 22 and others 23 collated copies of the Jinmyōchō. This discrepancy may be understood as the result of additions during the long research period, but because two main lineages can be identified—differing in how they present the collated copies and in insertion order—it is also possible that two versions of the work originally existed: one titled ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō'' and another titled ''Jinmyōchō Kōshō Dodai''&lt;ref name="西牟田"/&gt;.

== Footnotes ==
{{脚注ヘルプ}}
=== Notes ===
{{Notelist2}}
=== Sources ===
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* Iwamoto Tokuichi, “Commentary on Jinmyōchō Kō,” in ''Annotations to the Engi-shiki Shrine Register'' (Shintō Taikei Classical Commentary Series 7), Shintō Taikei Editorial Committee, 1986.  
* Toki Masanori, “Jinmyōchō Kōshō,” in ''Dictionary of Shintō History'', {{ill|Yoshikawa Kōbunkan|ja|吉川弘文館|1=Yoshikawa Kōbunkan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q4346755}}, 2004. ISBN 4-642-01340-7.  
* Nishimuta Takao, “Ban Nobutomo’s Research on the Engi-shiki Shrine Register,” in ''Studies on the Engi-shiki Shrine Register'', {{ill|Kokusho Kankōkai|ja|国書刊行会|1=Kokusho Kankōkai|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11420946}}, 1996. ISBN 4-336-03808-2.  
* ''Dictionary of Shintō'' (abridged reprint), {{ill|Rinsen Shoten|ja|臨川書店|1=Rinsen Shoten|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11612454}}, 1969. ISBN 4-653-01347-0 (original ed. Heibonsha, 1939).

== External Links ==
* [https://dl.ndl.go.jp/info:ndljp/pid/991312 Ban Nobutomo Zenshū Vol. 1 — National Diet Library Digital Collections] — Introduction page for volume 1 of ''Ban Nobutomo Zenshū'' on the National Diet Library website.

{{List of Shikinaisha}}

[[ja:神名帳考証土代]]
{{commonscat|Jinmyōchō Kōshō Dodai}}
{{translated page|ja|神名帳考証土代|version=91381996|comment=Imported full ja history}}
{{wikidata link|Q11588823}}
[[Category:1810s books]]
[[Category:Kokugaku]]
[[Category:Shikinaisha|Jinmyōchō Kōshō Dodai]][[Category:Shinto texts]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]</text>
      <sha1>2zju52u145ivzupz70l7f49het2tm97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
