<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Daruma doll</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5073</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3593336</id>
      <parentid>3591999</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:41:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3593336</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="25685" sha1="nq9ah7v4ks4rxk6azeko5qlpqlm68w2" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ar:داروما]][[az:Daruma (kukla)]][[ca:Daruma]][[cs:Daruma]][[da:Daruma]][[de:Daruma]][[en:Daruma doll]][[eo:Daruma]][[es:Daruma]][[fa:عروسک داروما]][[fr:Daruma]][[he:בובת דארומה]][[hu:Daruma]][[hy:Դարումա (տիկնիկ)]][[iba:Anak patung Daruma]][[id:Daruma]][[is:Daruma]][[it:Daruma]][[ja:だるま]][[ko:다루마]][[lt:Daruma]][[ml:ദാരുമ പാവകൾ]][[nl:Darumapop]][[pl:Daruma (lalka)]][[pt:Daruma]][[ru:Дарума (кукла)]][[simple:Daruma doll]][[sv:Daruma]][[th:ดารูมะ]][[tr:Daruma]][[uk:Лялька Дарума]][[uz:Daruma qoʻgʻirchogʻi]][[vi:Búp bê Daruma]][[zh:達摩 (玩偶)]]


{{short description|Traditional Japanese doll|qq=}}
{{original research|date=June 2013|qq=}}
[[Image:Daruma doll, cut out, 03.jpg|upright=1.35|thumb|Daruma doll]]
A {{nihongo|'''Daruma doll'''|達磨|daruma|lead=yes|qq=}} is a hollow, round, [[:en:Japanese traditional dolls|Japanese traditional doll]] modeled after {{ill|Bodhidharma|en|Bodhidharma|qid=Q187172|lt=Bodhidharma|1=Bodhidharma}}, the founder of the {{ill|Zen|en|Zen|qid=Q7953|lt=Zen|1=Zen}} tradition of {{ill|Buddhism|en|Buddhism|qid=Q748|lt=Buddhism|1=Buddhism}}. These dolls, though typically red and depicting the Indian monk, Bodhidharma, vary greatly in color and design depending on region and artist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=What is daruma doll?: How to use, History, FAQs |url=https://www.daruma.jp/about.html |access-date=2024-12-dd |website=www.daruma.jp|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though considered a toy by some, Daruma has a design that is rich in symbolism and is regarded more as a {{ill|Talisman|en|Talisman|qid=Q44506|lt=Talisman|1=Talisman}} of good luck to the Japanese. Daruma dolls are seen as a symbol of perseverance and good luck, making them a popular gift of encouragement.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The doll has also been commercialized by many Buddhist temples to use alongside the setting of goals.
==Use== 
{{Expand section|date=February 2018|qq=}}
When purchased, the figure's eyes are both blank white. The owner selects a goal or wish and paints in the left eye of the figure's two eyes with Chinese or Japanese ink. Once the goal is achieved, the right eye is filled in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://welovedaruma.com/about-daruma/|title=About Daruma - We Love Daruma|website=www.welovedaruma.com|access-date=24 October 2023|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Bodhidharma==
{{Main|Bodhidharma|qq=}}
[[Image:BodhidharmaYoshitoshi1887.jpg|thumb|{{ill|Bodhidharma|en|Bodhidharma|qid=Q187172|lt=Bodhidharma|1=Bodhidharma}}, {{ill|Woodblock printing|en|Woodblock printing|qid=Q1261053|lt=woodblock|1=Woodblock printing}} print by {{ill|Tsukioka Yoshitoshi|en|Tsukioka Yoshitoshi|qid=Q467337|lt=Yoshitoshi|1=Tsukioka Yoshitoshi}}, 1887]]
Bodhidharma was a {{ill|Buddhism|en|Buddhism|qid=Q748|lt=Buddhist|1=Buddhism}} {{ill|Bhikkhu|en|Bhikkhu|qid=Q854997|lt=monk|1=Bhikkhu}} who lived during the 5th/6th century CE. He is traditionally credited as the transmitter of [[:en:Ch'an|Ch'an]] ({{ill|Zen|en|Zen|qid=Q7953|lt=Zen|1=Zen}}) to {{ill|China|en|China|qid=Q148|lt=China|1=China}}. Little contemporary biographical information on Bodhidharma is available, and subsequent accounts have become layered with legend.&lt;ref name="McRae 2003"&gt;{{Harvcolnb|McRae|2003|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to one tradition, Bodhidharma gained a reputation for, among other things, his practice of wall-gazing. Legend claims that he sat facing a wall in {{ill|Meditation|en|Meditation|qid=Q108458|lt=Meditation|1=Meditation}} for a period of nine years without moving, which caused his legs and arms to fall off from {{ill|Atrophy|en|Atrophy|qid=Q194520|lt=Atrophy|1=Atrophy}}.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idChapin1946|Chapin, Helen B. "Three Early Portraits of Bodhidharma".]] p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; Another popular legend is that after falling asleep during his nine-year meditation he became angry with himself and cut off his eyelids to avoid ever falling asleep again.
According to the principal Chinese sources, Bodhidharma came from the {{ill|Western Regions|en|Western Regions|qid=Q1190423|lt=Western Regions|1=Western Regions}}, which refers to Central Asia but may also include the {{ill|Indian subcontinent|en|Indian subcontinent|qid=Q60140|lt=Indian subcontinent|1=Indian subcontinent}}, and was either a "Persian Central Asian" or a "South Indian ... the third son of a great Indian king."&lt;ref&gt;Emmanuel Francis (20dd), [https://journals.equinoxpub.com/index.php/ROSA/article/view/15172 ''The Genealogy of the Pallavas: From Brahmins to Kings''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180603021936/https://journals.equinoxpub.com/index.php/ROSA/article/view/15172 |date=2018-06-03 |qq=}}, Religions of South Asia, Vol. 5, No. 1/5.2 (20dd)&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jorgensen|2000|p=159|qq=}} Throughout {{ill|Buddhist art|en|Buddhist art|qid=Q1001041|lt=Buddhist art|1=Buddhist art}}, Bodhidharma is depicted as an ill-tempered, bearded, wide-eyed {{ill|Hua–Yi distinction|en|Hua–Yi distinction|qid=Q3030751|lt=non-Chinese person|1=Hua–Yi distinction}}. He is referred as "The Blue-Eyed Barbarian" ({{lang-zh|c=碧眼胡|p=Bìyǎnhú|qq=}}) in Chan texts, although note that while the translation "barbarian" is derogatory, in Chinese it is simply descriptive of non-Chinese origin.
==History and commercialization==
[[File:Maneki-Neko and Okiagari-Koboshi Daruma Edo Period.jpg|left|thumb|A wooden mold for a papier-mâché [[Maneki-neko]] and Okiagari-Koboshi Daruma figure from the Edo Period, 18th century. {{ill|Brooklyn Museum|en|Brooklyn Museum|qid=Q632682|lt=Brooklyn Museum|1=Brooklyn Museum}}.]]
The current popular symbolism associated with Daruma as a good luck charm in part originated at [[Shorinzan Daruma Temple]], in the city of {{ill|Takasaki|en|Takasaki|qid=Q336438|lt=Takasaki|1=Takasaki}} ({{ill|Gunma Prefecture|en|Gunma Prefecture|qid=Q129499|lt=Gunma Prefecture|1=Gunma Prefecture}}, north of Tokyo). Josef Kyburz, author of ''"Omocha": Things to Play (Or Not to Play) with'', explained that the founder of Daruma-Dera would draw New Year’s charms depicting Bodhidharma. The parishioners would keep these charms to "bring happiness and prosperity and ward off accidents and misfortune".&lt;ref name="autogenerated15"&gt;[[#Reference-idKyburz1994|"Omocha": Things to Play (Or Not to Play) with]] p.15&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hirokage_-_Comic_Incidents_at_Famous_Places_in_Edo_(Edo_meisho_dôke_zukushi),_No._22,_dog_stealing_a_workman's_meal_from_a_snow_Daruma.jpg|right|thumb|No. 22, Snow in Front of the Official Storehouses by [[:en:Hirokage|Hirokage]]]]
It is believed that the Daruma figurine then originated from this region when the ninth priest, Togaku, found a solution to handle the constant requests of the parishioners for new charms. The charms were always given with an effectiveness of one year, so the people required new ones every year. He solved this by entrusting them with the making of their own Daruma charms near the beginning of the {{ill|Meiwa|en|Meiwa|qid=Q1146161|lt=Meiwa|1=Meiwa}} period (1764–72). The temple made wooden block molds for the people to use. The peasants then used these molds to make three-dimensional papier-mâché charms.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idKyburz1994|"Omocha": Things to Play (Or Not to Play) with]] p.14&lt;/ref&gt;
Kyburz notes that though it is unknown when the Daruma figurine combined with the {{ill|Roly-poly toy|en|Roly-poly toy|qid=Q779519|lt=tumbler doll|1=Roly-poly toy}}; the two were well recognized as synonymous by the mid-19th century. The doll quickly grew in popularity, becoming a mascot of the region. This was due greatly in part to fact that the majority of the families were silk farmers, a crop which requires a great deal of luck for success.&lt;ref name="autogenerated15"/&gt;
There is an annual {{nihongo|Daruma Doll Festival|達磨市|daruma-ichi|qq=}} held by the city of Takasaki in celebration of being the proclaimed birthplace of the Daruma doll. The celebration is held at the Shorinzan, the name of Takasaki's "Daruma-Dera". According to the Takasaki city website, "Over 400,000 people from all over the Kanto Plain come to buy new good-luck dolls for the year. Takasaki produces 80% of Japan's Daruma dolls."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.city.takasaki.gunma.jp/English/TakasakiEvents.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070619043922/http://www.city.takasaki.gunma.jp/English/TakasakiEvents.html|title=The City of Takasaki|archive-date=19 June 2007|website=city.takasaki.gunma.jp|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The festival also features a 24-hour reading of {{ill|Sutra|en|Sutra|qid=Q209680|lt=sutras|1=Sutra}} by the Shorinzan monks for world peace.
==Physical features and symbolism==
[[Image:Daruma dolls.jpg|thumb|Daruma dolls at Shōrinzan Daruma-ji, [[:en:Takasaki, Gunma|Takasaki]], {{ill|Japan|en|Japan|qid=Q17|lt=Japan|1=Japan}}]]
Daruma’s design, particularly the shape, color, eyes and facial hair, each have its own history and symbolic meaning.
===Shape===
Darumas are still usually made of papier-mâché, have a round shape, are hollow and weighted at the bottom so that they will always return to an upright position when tilted over. In Japanese, a {{ill|Roly-poly toy|en|Roly-poly toy|qid=Q779519|lt=Roly-poly toy|1=Roly-poly toy}} is called ''okiagari'', meaning to get up (''oki'') and arise (''agari''). This characteristic has come to symbolize the ability to have success, overcome adversity, and recover from misfortune.&lt;ref name="autogenerated15"/&gt; In Japanese popular culture on cards, banners and books, Daruma is often illustrated alongside the phrase "Nanakorobi Yaoki" ({{lang|ja|七転び八起き|qq=}}), translated to mean "seven times down, eight times up". While some traditional Daruma dolls have flat bases, the Sankaku or Triangle Daruma ({{lang|ja|三角だるま|qq=}}) is constructed from a rolled cardboard cone attached to a rounded clay base so that it always stands straight when tilted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Triangle Daruma Wishes Are Peaceful|url=https://www.nikkei.com/article/DGXKZO26261560Z20C18A1BC8000|website=Nihon Keizai Shimbun|date=30 January 2018 |publisher=Nikkei.com|accessdate=12 May 2022|language=Japanese|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Triangle Darumas.jpg|thumb|left|Triangle Darumas made by Tokushiro Imai (1895-1995), who developed their design in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Expressing the strength of will in a funny expression|url= http://rongo.sakura.ne.jp/yamagutininngyou/yamagutininngyou.htm|website= Paper Drawing Blog|publisher= rongo.sakura.ne.jp |accessdate=12 May 2022|language=Japanese|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;|175px]]
The tumbler doll style is similar to an earlier toy called the [[:en:Okiagari Koboshi|Okiagari Koboshi]], a little self-righting monk which was popular in the [[:en:Kinki|Kinki]] region during the mid-17th century. The original okiagari toy, however, is said to have been introduced from [[:en:Ming China|Ming China]] around 1368–1644.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idKyburz1994|"Omocha": Things to Play (Or Not to Play) with]] p.23&lt;/ref&gt;
===Color===
[[File:Neonpink-daruma-ibaraki-japan-sept22-2015.jpg|thumb|Non-traditional neon pink Daruma dolls in [[:en:Ibaraki prefecture|Ibaraki]].]]
Though it is not certain, the origins of Daruma's traditional red coloring probably came from the color of priest's robes. Reliable sources in English are hard to find, but one Japan-based website cites this red as being the "color of the robe of a high-Ranking priest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amie.or.jp/daruma/Mini%20Daruma.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091230182620/http://www.amie.or.jp/daruma/Mini%20Daruma.html|title=MINI Daruma and a Tiny Encyclopedia about Daruma ミニミニ辞典—知識散歩|archive-date=30 December 2009|website=amie.or.jp|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The author then concludes that "since Daruma was the founder of the Zen Sect, he must have worn a red robe." The art historian James T. Ulak has documented a history of depictions of the Bodhidharma wearing lavish red robes, prior to representations of him as a doll, in an article entitled "Japanese Works in The Art Institute of Chicago."&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idUlak1993|Japanese Works in The Art Institute of Chicago: Five Recent Acquisitions]] p.178&lt;/ref&gt;
By virtue of his red robes, Daruma has come to play a role in recovering from sickness. During the late {{ill|Edo period|en|Edo period|qid=Q184963|lt=Edo period|1=Edo period}} (1603-1868), red was believed to have a strong association to {{ill|Smallpox|en|Smallpox|qid=Q12214|lt=Smallpox|1=Smallpox}}. Hartmut O. Rotermond, author of ''Demonic Affliction or Contagious Disease?'', describes that in Edo and surrounding cities, there were many outbreaks of measles and smallpox. In present-day Japan, there are many red shrines dedicated to a God of Smallpox, which had a particular liking for red. These shrines were built in response to those outbreaks.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idRotermund2001|Rotermund, Hartmut O. "Demonic Affliction or Contagious Disease? Changing Perceptions of Smallpox in the Late Edo Period."]] p.1&lt;/ref&gt; Believing that the God of smallpox, if pleased, would spare the afflicted child, the Japanese would often stretch out ropes around the house strung with red paper strips, have the child wear a red robe, and make a small altar for the God to put talisman-like Daruma figurines on.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idRotermund2001|Rotermund, Hartmut O. "Demonic Affliction or Contagious Disease? Changing Perceptions of Smallpox in the Late Edo Period"]]. p.374&lt;/ref&gt; These precautions were also used to warn others that sickness was in the house, and to encourage cleanliness around the sick. The red of Daruma, however, was used to pacify the God, while the image of okiagari was to encourage the patient to recover as quickly as they fell ill.&lt;ref name="autogenerated15"/&gt; Daruma are also sold as a set of five colors – blue, yellow, red, white and black – called ''Goshiki Daruma''. These days, daruma can also be found in colors other than red, including gold, which is meant to bring luck in financial matters.
===Eyes===
[[Image:Daruma doll.jpg|thumb|200px|A daruma doll with one eye filled in for wishing]]
The eyes of Daruma are often blank when sold. Monte A. Greer, author of ''Daruma Eyes'', described the "oversized symmetrical round blank white eyes" as a means to keep track of goals or big tasks and motivate them to work to the finish. The recipient of the doll fills in one eye upon setting the goal, then the other upon fulfilling it. In this way, every time they see the one-eyed Daruma, they recall the goal. One explanation how this custom started says that in order to motivate Daruma-san to grant your wish, you promise to give him full sight once the goal is accomplished. This practice might also have something to do with the "enlightenment", the ideal attainment of Buddhism. This custom has led to a phrase in Japanese translated as "Both Eyes Open". Referring to "opening" the second eye, it expresses the realization of a goal.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;[[#Reference-idGreer2002|Greer, Monte A. "Daruma Eyes: The Sixth Century Founder of Zen Buddhism and Kung Fu Had the Earliest Recorded Graves]] p.1&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, the Daruma was purchased as a household item, and only the head of the household would paint in the eyes.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idPunsmann1962|Punsmann, Henry. "Daruma, a Symbol of Luck"]]. p.5&lt;/ref&gt;
One example of this is politicians during election time. Political parties have often been shown at their headquarters with large Daruma dolls and amulets purchased from local temples as a prayer for victory. This practice was highlighted in a 1967 article in ''{{ill|Time (magazine)|en|Time (magazine)|qid=Q43297|lt=Time|1=Time (magazine)}}'' magazine: "Last week, in the Tokyo headquarters of Japan's ruling {{ill|Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|en|Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|qid=Q232595|lt=Liberal Democratic Party|1=Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)}}, Premier {{ill|Eisaku Satō|en|Eisaku Satō|qid=Q179871|lt=Eisaku Satō|1=Eisaku Satō}} dipped a sumi brush into an ink stone and with swift strokes daubed in the dark right eye of his Daruma. 'The eyes,' he remarked when he had finished, 'are as big as my own.'"&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idTime1967|"Japan: The Right Eye of Daruma". ''Time'']]. p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;
The Matsukawa Daruma ({{lang|ja|松川だるま|qq=}}) is produced with the eyes already painted, with the purpose of watching over a family's household.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sendai papier-mâché|url=https://tetotetote-sendai.jp/en/hariko|website=Te to Te to Te|publisher=tetotetote|accessdate=7 June 2022|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These intricate figures are more slender than traditional Daruma and typically feature blue coloring and a base molded (or simply painted) in the form of the {{ill|Takarabune|en|Takarabune|qid=Q48723823|lt=ship|1=Takarabune}} that transports the [[Seven Lucky Gods]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Why is Matsukawa Daruma blue?|url=https://www.nhk.or.jp/sendai-blog/update/459285.html|website=NHK|publisher=nhk.or.jp|accessdate=7 June 2022|language=japanese|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===Facial hair===
Daruma's facial hair is a symbolic representation of the animals well known in Asian culture to embody longevity: the crane and the tortoise. The eyebrows are in the shape of a crane, while the cheek hair resembles the shell of the tortoise. A Japanese-based website states that originally, there was a snake or dragon depicted across the moustache and cheeks, but was changed to tortoise to emphasize the desire for longevity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amie.or.jp/daruma/Tsurukame.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100dd3182313/http://www.amie.or.jp/daruma/Tsurukame.html|title=Tsurukame – Crane, Tortoise and Daruma for Good Luck 鶴亀とだるま—縁起物散歩|archive-date=13 January 2010|website=amie.or.jp|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, Daruma was designed to match the Japanese proverb "The crane lives 1000 years, the tortoise 10,000 years".
==Daruma burning==
[[Image:Dairyuji-Gifu D01.JPG|thumb|right|Burning of the Daruma]]
At the end of the year, all the Daruma are brought back to the temple they were purchased from for a traditional burning ceremony.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt; This ceremony, called the {{Nihongo||だるま供養|daruma kuyō|qq=}}, is held once a year, usually right after New Year's Day. The most renowned of these events are held at the [[Adachi, Tokyo#Nishiarai Daishi|Nishi-Arai Daishi Temple]] (Tokyo), and the {{ill|Dairyū-ji (Gifu)|en|Dairyū-ji (Gifu)|qid=Q3012156|lt=Dairyū-ji|1=Dairyū-ji (Gifu)}} Temple (Gifu). At these events, people bring the Daruma figures they had used that year to the temple. After expressing gratitude to them, they turn them over to the temple and buy new ones for the next year. All of the old Daruma figures are burnt together in the temple. After a solemn display of the monks' entry, reading of the sutras and blowing of horns, the tens of thousands of figurines are then set aflame.
==Feminine representations==
Daruma dolls also come in the form of {{Nihongo|''Princess Daruma''|姫だるま |hime daruma|qq=}} and {{Nihongo|''Lady Daruma''|女だるま |onna daruma|qq=}}. This contrasts greatly with traditional representations of Bodhidharma, who, accredited as the father of many martial arts, has traditionally been depicted as very masculine with rough facial hair.&lt;ref name="mcfarland170"&gt;[[#Reference-idMcFarland1986|McFarland, H. Neill. "Feminine Motifs in Bodhidharma Symbology in Japan"]] p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt; H. Neill McFarland, Professor of Theology, discusses the feminine representations of Bodhidharma in his article ''Feminine Motifs in Bodhidharma Symbology in Japan''. The answer to this anomaly lies in the social changes at the time, developing in the Edo Period. The class distinctions placed the merchants at the bottom, who in turn developed their own culture focusing on humor and poking fun at what those of higher class held sacred. This is evident in the depiction of Bodhidharma as a prostitute since prostitutes displayed the same "okiagari" resilience. Famous pieces of art depicting Bodhidharma were also redrawn with a woman in his place.&lt;ref name="mcfarland170"/&gt;
With the inception of the Daruma doll, the Onna Daruma doll quickly followed. Though the aforementioned examples of feminine motifs of Bodhidharma were satirical, the doll forms maintain the same wholesome image of a bringer of good luck.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reference-idMcFarland1986|McFarland, H. Neill. "Feminine Motifs in Bodhidharma Symbology in Japan"]] p. 172&lt;/ref&gt;
==Children's games==
[[Image:Darumaotoshi.JPG|thumb|upright|Daruma Otoshi. The Daruma character, hammer and rainbow-colored pieces.]]
Many children's games make mention of Daruma. In Japanese, snowmen are called "Yukidaruma" ({{langx|ja|雪だるま|qq=}}), literally ''snow daruma''. Possibly because the shape is related to Daruma, they usually only have two sections instead of three.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Netsuke in the form of a boy rolling a yuki daruma, or snowman|url=https://collections.ashmolean.org/collection/browse-9148/object/24894|access-date=15 February 2021|website=collections.ashmolean.org|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Statues (game)#Other names|Darumasan ga Koronda]] is an equivalent to the American [[Statues (game)#Variations|Red Light/Green Light]] game. {{nihongo|''Daruma Otoshi''|だるま落とし|qq=}} is a traditional game played with a daruma doll in five pieces, usually in the colors of the rainbow, from top to bottom: head – a man's face, blue, green, yellow, red. The game is played by using a small hammer to hit each of the colored pieces, from bottom to the top, without letting the pieces fall during the game.
==See also==
* {{ill|Japanese craft|en|Japanese craft|qid=Q6158727|lt=Japanese craft|1=Japanese craft}}
* {{ill|Japanese dolls|en|Japanese dolls|qid=Q1317521|lt=Japanese dolls|1=Japanese dolls}}
* [[:en:Matryoshka|Matryoshka]], a Russian doll said to be inspired by the Daruma doll
* [[:en:Religions of Japan|Religions of Japan]]
{{Clear|qq=}}
==References==
{{reflist|30em|qq=}}
==Sources==
{{refbegin|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idChapin1946|reference=Chapin, Helen B. "Three Early Portraits of Bodhidharma." Archives of the Chinese Art Society of America, Vol. 1 (1945/1946), 66–98|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idKyburz1994|reference=Kyburz Josef A., " "Omocha": Things to Play (Or Not to Play) with" Asian Folklore Studies, Vol.53, No. 1 (1994), 1–28|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idFaure1986|reference= Faure, Bernard. "Bodhidharma as Textual and Religious Paradigm." History of Religions, Vol. 25, No. 3 (Feb., 1986), 187–198|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idGettis2003|reference=Gettis , Alan. Seven Times Down, Eight Times Up: Landing on Your Feet in an Upside-down World. Trafford Publishing, 2003|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idGreer2002|reference=Greer, Monte A. "Daruma Eyes: The Sixth Century Founder of Zen Buddhism and Kung Fu Had the Earliest Recorded Graves' Ophthalmopathy." Thyroid. May 2002, 12(5): 389–391|qq=}}
* {{Citation |last=Jorgensen |first=John |year=2000 |chapter=Bodhidharma |editor-last=Johnston |editor-first =William M. |title=Encyclopedia of Monasticism: A-L |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|qq=}}
* {{Citation | last =McRae | first =John | year =2003 | title =Seeing Through Zen. Encounter, Transformation, and Genealogy in Chinese Chan Buddhism | publisher =The University Press Group Ltd | isbn =978-0-520-23798-8|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idRotermund2001|reference=Rotermund, Hartmut O. "Demonic Affliction or Contagious Disease? Changing Perceptions of Smallpox in the Late Edo Period." Japanese Journal of Religious Studies 2001 28/3–4|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idUlak1993|reference=Ulak, James T. "Japanese Works in The Art Institute of Chicago: Five Recent Acquisitions" Art Institute of Chicago Museum Studies, Vol. 19, No. 2(1993), 174–185, 154–157, 205–207|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idPunsmann1962|reference=Punsmann, Henry. "Daruma, a Symbol of Luck" Folklore Studies, Vol. 21 (1962), 241–244|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idTime1967|reference="[https://web.archive.org/web/20080220194152/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,840819,00.html Japan: The Right Eye of Daruma]". ''Time''. Friday, Feb. 10, 1967|qq=}}
* {{wikicite|id=idMcFarland1986|reference=McFarland, H. Neill. "Feminine Motifs in Bodhidharma Symbology in Japan" Asian Folklore Studies, Vol. 45, No. 2 (1986), pp. 167–191 |qq=}}
{{refend|qq=}}
==Further reading==
* McFarland, H. Neill (1987). ''Daruma: The Founder of Zen in Japanese Art and Popular Culture''. Tokyo and New York: Kodansha International Ltd.
==External links==
* {{commonscat-inline|Daruma|qq=}}
{{jmyth navbox long|qq=}}
{{Authority control|qq=}}



[[en:Daruma doll]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[ar:داروما]]
[[az:Daruma (kukla)]]
[[ca:Daruma]]
{{Commons category|Daruma dolls}}
[[cs:Daruma]]
[[da:Daruma]]
[[de:Daruma]]
[[eo:Daruma]]
[[es:Daruma]]
[[fa:عروسک داروما]]
[[fr:Daruma]]
[[he:בובת דארומה]]
[[hu:Daruma]]
[[hy:Դարումա (տիկնիկ)]]
[[iba:Anak patung Daruma]]
[[id:Daruma]]
[[is:Daruma]]
[[it:Daruma]]
[[ja:だるま]]
[[ko:다루마]]
[[lt:Daruma]]
[[ml:ദാരുമ പാവകൾ]]
[[nl:Darumapop]]
[[pl:Daruma (lalka)]]
[[pt:Daruma]]
[[ru:Дарума (кукла)]]
[[simple:Daruma doll]]
[[sv:Daruma]]
[[th:ดารูมะ]]
[[tr:Daruma]]
[[uk:Лялька Дарума]]
[[uz:Daruma qoʻgʻirchogʻi]]
[[vi:Búp bê Daruma]]
[[zh:達摩 (玩偶)]]
{{wikidata link|Q276107}}
[[Category:Buddhist folklore]]
[[Category:Figurines]]
[[Category:Japanese dolls]]
[[Category:Japanese folk art]]
[[Category:Japanese folklore]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]
[[Category:Zazen]]
[[Category:Zen art and culture]]</text>
      <sha1>nq9ah7v4ks4rxk6azeko5qlpqlm68w2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
