<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Demotion to subject status</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21223</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3593380</id>
      <parentid>3568849</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:42:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3593380</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="20237" sha1="p8lis36uefj4sud2lhi39gy0hp904nc" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[fa:شینسکی کوکا]][[ja:臣籍降下]][[ko:신적강하]][[zh-min-nan:Sîn-che̍k kàng-hā]][[zh:臣籍降下]]



'''Shinseki kōka''' (臣籍降下) – literally “descent to the civil register” – refers to a member of the {{ill|Imperial House of Japan|de|Japanische Kaiserfamilie|ja|皇族|zh|日本皇族|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Imperial House of Japan|1=Imperial Family of Japan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11581068}} who resigns imperial status, receives a family name, and is entered in the population register as a subject.  The procedure is also called '''Shisei kōka''' (賜姓降下, “descent with a bestowed surname”); such (former) imperials are colloquially known as '''Shisei kōzoku''' (“surname-bestowed royalty”).  When an imperial princess loses royal status by marrying a commoner, the term is '''Shinseki kōka (kōka-kon)’''' (臣籍降嫁, “descent by marriage”).

Since the abolition of legal status classes under the present {{ill|Constitution of Japan|en|Constitution of Japan|qid=Q237082|lt=Constitution of Japan|1=Constitution of Japan}}, the expression “descent” is considered inappropriate; instead '''Kōseki ridatsu''' (皇籍離脱, “departure from the imperial register”) is used.  This article also treats '''Kōseki fukki''' (皇籍復帰, “return to imperial status”), when a person who once descended – or that person’s descendants – re-enters the imperial house.

== Current provisions for losing imperial status ==
{{blockquote|style={{皇室典範/blockquote@style|qq=}}
; {{ill|Imperial Household Law|en|Imperial Household Law|qid=Q1324733|lt=Imperial House Law|1=Imperial Household Law}} art. 11
: 1. A female {{ill|Imperial princess|de|Prinzessin (Japan)|ja|内親王|zh|内亲王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Imperial princess|1=Imperial princess|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q8015665}}, {{ill|Prince (Japanese title)|de|Ō (Adelstitel)|ja|王 (皇族)|zh|王 (皇族)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Prince (Japanese title)|1=ō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q16142365}}, or {{ill|Princess (Japanese title)|de|Nyoo|ja|女王 (皇族)|zh|女王 (皇族)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Princess (Japanese title)|1=Joō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q10942783}} aged 15 or older may, of her own will, leave imperial status by decision of the {{ill|Imperial Household Council|en|Imperial Household Council|qid=Q338120|lt=Imperial Household Council|1=Imperial Household Council}}.
: 2. A male {{ill|Prince (Japan)|de|Prinz (Japan)|ja|親王|zh|亲王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Prince (Japan)|1=Shinnō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q903422}} (except the Crown Prince and Crown Grandson), princess, prince, or princess may, for unavoidable special reasons, leave imperial status by decision of the council.
; art. 12
: A female imperial family member loses imperial status upon marriage to anyone other than the Emperor or another imperial.
; art. 13
: When a prince’s wife exits the register, their direct descendants and spouses exit simultaneously, unless the council decides otherwise.
; art. 14
: A commoner woman who became a princess by marriage may, upon widowhood, exit the register of her own will (para. 1) or, for special reasons, by council decision (para. 2).  She automatically leaves upon divorce (para. 3).  Paragraphs 1 and 3 apply mutatis mutandis to a woman who married into another imperial branch.
}}

=== Matters requiring Imperial Household Council deliberation (excerpt) ===
* Voluntary departure of princesses, princes, or princesses aged 15+ (art. 11-1).
* Involuntary departure of princes (except the crown line) and other imperials (art. 11-2).
* Exception to retain imperial status for a prince’s descendants upon his departure (art. 13 proviso).
* Involuntary departure of a widowed commoner princess (art. 14-2).

{{Infobox Imperial system Japan
|name       = Shinseki kōka
|japanese   = 臣籍降下
|caption    = Scroll of Prince Mochihito’s civil descent (1180)
}}

'''Shinseki kōka''' (臣籍降下, lit. “descent to the civil register”) refers to a member of the {{ill|Imperial House of Japan|en|Imperial House of Japan|qid=Q909452|lt=Imperial House of Japan|1=Imperial House of Japan}} who relinquishes imperial status, receives a surname, and enters the 
common census as a subject. The procedure is also called '''Shisei kōka''' (賜姓降下, “descent with a bestowed surname”); such former imperials are colloquially termed '''Shisei kōzoku'''. When an imperial princess loses her status by marrying a commoner, the act is '''Shinseki kōka-kon''' (臣籍降嫁, “descent by marriage”).

Since the social-class system was abolished under the 1947 Constitution, the expression “kōka” is deemed inappropriate; modern documents use '''Kōseki ridatsu''' (皇籍離脱, “withdrawal from the imperial register”).  This article also treats '''Kōseki fukki''' (皇籍復帰, “restoration”), the rare return of a descended line to imperial status.

== Current law ==
{{blockquote|style={{皇室典範/blockquote@style|qq=}}
; {{ill|Imperial Household Law|en|Imperial Household Law|qid=Q1324733|lt=Imperial House Law|1=Imperial Household Law}} art. 11-14 – abridged translation
* Females and collateral princes aged 15 + may leave the register by their own wish with approval of the {{ill|Imperial Household Council|en|Imperial Household Council|qid=Q338120|lt=Imperial Household Council|1=Imperial Household Council}}.
* They may also be removed for unavoidable special reasons.
* A princess automatically departs when she marries outside the imperial family.
* Departure of a prince extends to his consort and direct descendants unless the council decides otherwise.
* A commoner widow of a prince may choose to leave; she must do so upon divorce.
}}

=== Council items related to descent ===
* Voluntary exit of princesses/princes aged 15 +.
* Involuntary exit of collateral princes/princesses.
* Retention of imperial status for a departing prince’s children (special case).
* Involuntary exit of a commoner princess-widow.

== Historical development ==
{{seealso|身位|qq=}}
=== Antiquity ===
Under the {{ill|Ritsuryō|en|Ritsuryō|qid=Q742460|lt=Ritsuryō system|1=Ritsuryō}} imperial kin (''kōshin'') were defined by degree of agnatic descent from successive emperors.  Descendants within four generations were styled "Prince (ō)" or "Princess (joō)"; fifth-generation princes retained the title but fell outside the imperial kin and were granted Junior Fifth Rank, while from the sixth generation the royal title was not granted (modified by an edict of Keiun 3 = 706).  Thus males of sufficiently distant blood entered the civil register in due course.

By the early {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian period|1=Heian period}} the dynasty produced so many children that four-generation princes proliferated, most with negligible claim to succession.  Some abused their stipends, straining the treasury.  Accordingly emperors began transferring collateral princes to civilian status ahead of schedule.  Emperor {{ill|Emperor Kanmu|en|Emperor Kanmu|qid=Q314846|lt=Kanmu|1=Emperor Kanmu}} alone bestowed surnames on over one hundred relatives, including three first-generation princes whose mothers were of low Rank.  Subsequent sovereigns from {{ill|Emperor Saga|en|Emperor Saga|qid=Q316654|lt=Saga|1=Emperor Saga}} onward followed suit.

Imperial princes were restricted to few offices, so some themselves petitioned for descent.  For one or two generations their new houses retained high court Rank, but by the third many declined, settled in the provinces, and evolved into warrior or landed families.

Former princes usually received a new '''uji''' (clan name) and '''kabane''' (hereditary title) – a custom later called '''kōshin shisei''' (“bestowal of surname upon an imperial”).  Some descended by adoption into a noble house (the so-called {{ill|Kōbetsu sekke|de|Kōbetsu-sekke|ja|皇別摂家|zh|皇别摄家|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kōbetsu sekke|1=Kōbetsu sekke|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11581001}}).

While their personal names generally remained unchanged save for dropping the title ō/joō, a few adopted new names (e.g. Prince Katsuragi → Tachibana Moroe; Prince Mochihito → Minamoto no Yorimasa).

; Bestowed surnames
From antiquity various uji were granted; by the Heian period almost always either the {{ill|Minamoto clan|en|Minamoto clan|qid=Q599881|lt=Minamoto clan|1=Minamoto clan}} or the {{ill|Taira clan|en|Taira clan|qid=Q1079102|lt=Taira clan|1=Taira clan}}.
* '''Minamoto''' began in 814 (Kōnin 5) when Emperor Saga conferred it on three of his sons, imitating the Yuan He story in China’s ''Book of Wei''.
* '''Taira''' began in 825 (Tenchō 2) when Emperor Junna granted it to the children of Prince Katsurahara, fifth son of Emperor Kanmu; the name honours the new capital Heian-kyō.

Originally imperial descendants bore the kabane ''kimi'' 公. After the {{ill|Eight kabane|de|Yatsuka no kabane|ja|八色の姓|zh|八色姓|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Eight kabane|1=Eight Kabane system|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11391729}} reform they generally received ''Mahito'', sometimes ''Asomi'' or ''Sukune''. Once the Gen-Pei convention crystallised, the kabane standardised as ''Asomi''.

=== Middle Ages to early modern era ===
The titles {{ill|Shinnō|de|Shinnō|ja|親王|zh|亲王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinnō|qq=}} and {{ill|Naishinnō|de|Naishinnō|ja|内親王|zh|内亲王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Naishinnō|1=Imperial princess|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q8015665}}, once automatic, became subject to {{ill|Shinnō senge|de|Shinnō senge|ja|親王宣下|zh|亲王宣下|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinnō senge|1=Shinnō senge|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11630454}}, wherein the emperor selectively proclaimed eligible heirs; princes not so proclaimed descended to civil status. Thus the decision to remain imperial preceded title-granting.

After the era of cloistered rule the court hierarchy ossified. Creation of new nobles by imperial descent threatened this order, so collateral princes were typically tonsured in childhood as {{ill|Hōshinnō|de|Hōshinnō|ja|法親王|zh|法亲王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hōshinnō|1=hosshinnō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11555351}}, leaving no offspring. Only four ''hereditary prince houses'' – Fushimi, Katsura, Arisugawa, Kan’in – retained succession; surname-bestowed princes virtually disappeared. From the Kamakura period onward the only new ''dōjōke'' founded by imperial descent and surviving to Meiji was the {{ill|Hirohata family|de|Hirohata-ke|ja|広幡家|zh|广幡家|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hirohata family|1=Hirohata family|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11485396}}.

=== Old Imperial House Law (1889) ===
{{seealso|永世皇族制|qq=}}
During the Meiji Restoration many sons of {{ill|Prince Fushimi Kuniie|en|Prince Fushimi Kuniie|qid=Q7243989|lt=Prince Fushimi Kuniie|1=Prince Fushimi Kuniie}} returned to lay life and adopted new palace names.  An internal draft of 1882 proposed descent by genealogical degree (prince only in the first generation, royal title to the fourth, descent to nobility at the ninth).  Yet the 1889 {{ill|Imperial House Law of 1889|de|Kaiserliches Hausgesetz (Japan)|ja|皇室典範 (1889年)|zh|皇室典范 (1889年)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Imperial House Law of 1889|1=Imperial Household Law|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11581033}} adopted an '''“eternal imperial”''' system: princes up to the fourth generation, royals from the fifth “in perpetuity,” with no further descent.  Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal {{ill|Sanjō Sanetomi|en|Sanjō Sanetomi|qid=Q516646|lt=Sanjō Sanetomi|1=Sanjō Sanetomi}} opposed this on fiscal grounds, but drafter {{ill|Inoue Kowashi|en|Inoue Kowashi|qid=Q711131|lt=Inoue Kowashi|1=Inoue Kowashi}} insisted descent lacked historical basis, and the plan was approved.

At the time Emperor Meiji had only one surviving, sickly son (Prince Yoshihito, later Emperor Taishō), so collateral male lines were deemed necessary.  Because Edo-period princes outside the four houses entered monastic life, close male kin were scarce; the Arisugawa line alone lay within eight generations.  Distant Fushimi branches (15th generation) were therefore retained.

The law also stipulated that an imperial woman marrying anyone other than the emperor or another imperial must lose status (art. 12), overturning earlier custom.  Partners, however, were limited to imperials, nobles, or peers, and leeway remained to retain the Rank of princess or queen.

==== Table 1. Direct male descendants of Prince Kuniie reaching majority by 1907 ====
{{small|(Palace succession, new palace foundation, or no descent indicated)|qq=}}
{|class="wikitable" style="font-size:80%"
! Name !! Relation to Kuniie !! Majority !! Outcome
|-
| {{ill|Prince Yamashina Akira|en|Prince Yamashina Akira|qid=Q5499202|lt=Prince Akira|1=Prince Yamashina Akira}} || son || 22 Oct 1836 || laicised → founded '''Yamashina no miya'''
|-
| {{ill|Prince Kaga (Yoshinari)|de|Shōgo-in-no-miya Yoshinari|ja|聖護院宮嘉言親王|lt=Prince Yoshinari|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Prince Kaga (Yoshinari)|1=Shōgoin-no-miya Yoshikoto-shinnō|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11611124}} || son || 28 Feb 1841 || laicised → founded '''Shōgo-in no miya''' (later merged as Kitashirakawa)
|-
| {{ill|Prince Kuni Asahiko|en|Prince Kuni Asahiko|qid=Q5370435|lt=Prince Asahiko|1=Prince Kuni Asahiko}} || son || 27 Mar 1844 || laicised → founded '''Kuni no miya'''
|-
| {{ill|Prince Komatsu Akihito|en|Prince Komatsu Akihito|qid=Q712627|lt=Prince Akihito|1=Prince Komatsu Akihito}} || son || 11 Feb 1866 || laicised → founded '''Komatsu no miya'''
|-
| {{ill|Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa|en|Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa|qid=Q3197569|lt=Prince Norihisa|1=Prince Kitashirakawa Yoshihisa}} || son || 1 Apr 1867 || laicised → succeeded '''Kitashirakawa no miya'''
|-
| … 
|}

=== 1907 Supplement ===
In 1907, with Crown Prince Yoshihito safely adult and four sons born, the {{ill|Supplement to the Imperial House Law|de|Ergänzung zum Kaiserlichen Hausgesetz|ja|皇室典範増補|zh|皇室典範增补|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Supplement to the Imperial House Law|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} opened a path for fifth-generation princes to descend without founding new palaces and barred return once descended (arts. 1 &amp; 6).  The first case was Prince Teruhisa of Komatsu in 1910.

Abridged table (1908-1920 majorities) …

=== 1920 Descent Guidelines ===
To curb further expansion, Interior Minister Hatano Kei choku tasked the Imperial Institutions Commission with rules. The ''Shinnō kōka shikō junso'' (1920) provided that collateral princes other than the main heir of each palace – and, in principle, any royal in the ninth generation from the throne – should descend unless they petitioned to remain. Because all Fushimi lines already exceeded nine generations, Prince Kuniie was treated as “fourth generation” for counting.

The first to descend under the rules was Prince Yamashina Yoshimaro (July 1920).  Subsequent eligible princes followed the same procedure, formally by voluntary petition.  No exceptional retention was granted.

=== 1947 – The descent of eleven palaces ===
After Japan’s defeat in World War II the Allied occupation questioned public funding of collateral lines "highly unlikely ever to reign."  Following negotiations between the Imperial Household and GHQ, a decision was taken to retain only the Emperor’s three brotherly palaces (Chichibu, Takamatsu, Mikasa).  On 14 Oct 1947, by council vote, eleven Fushimi-derived palaces (51 persons) left the imperial house.  Emperor Shōwa expressed hope for continued close relations, and guidelines granted them quasi-imperial treatment (e.g. precedence at garden parties).  They are commonly called the '''{{ill|Ōke|en|Ōke|qid=Q864190|lt=Former imperial family|1=Ōke}}''', and their potential return has been debated in post-Heisei succession discussions.

=== Modern period ===
Since 1947 every withdrawal has involved an imperial woman marrying a commoner.

== Return to Imperial Status (皇籍復帰)==

In principle, a prince or princess who has once been **stripped of imperial Rank and entered the civilian registers (臣籍降下)** may not re-enter the Imperial Family.  
In practice, however, there were quite a few exceptions—typically to secure a broader pool of heirs to the throne—where former imperial members were readmitted.  
Occasionally, a child born **after** a parent’s demotion was also granted imperial status at the very moment that parent was restored.

Some scholars add that, once the system of **formal “Prince/Princess Proclamation” (親王宣下・内親王宣下)** replaced the older ritsuryō rule by which every imperial offspring automatically became a prince or princess, an emperor could revise a child’s standing at will. This doctrinal shift—nicknamed *“the separation of status from the body”*—opened the door to viewing restoration to imperial Rank as no less legitimate than demotion.【仁藤 2021】

== Footnotes ==
{{脚注ヘルプ|qq=}}

=== Annotations ===
{{Notelist|30em|qq=}}

=== References ===
{{Reflist|18em|qq=}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{Cite journal |language=ja |author=Katsuoka, Kanji |authorlink=Katsuoka Kanji |script-title=ja:菊栄親睦会の基礎的研究 |trans-title=Fundamental Study of the Kiku-e Friendship Association |journal=Nihon Kokushi-gaku (Journal of Japanese National History) |volume=17 |publisher=Japan National History Society |date=2021-08-01 |pages=74–127 |isbn=978-4-89992-077-9 |ref={{SfnRef|Katsuoka|qq=}} |qq=}}

== See also ==
{{Wiktionary|Shinsekikōka|qq=}}
{{Wikisource|Decree Relieving Prince Hiroaki et al. of Imperial Status|qq=}}
{{Wikisource|Decree Relieving Princess Toshiko et al. of Imperial Status|qq=}}
{{Wikisource|Decree Relieving Princess Chikako et al. of Imperial Status|qq=}}
* {{ill|Ōke|en|Ōke|qid=Q864190|lt=Former imperial family of Japan|1=Ōke}}
* {{ill|Imperial regent houses|de|Kaiserliche Regentengeschlechter|ja|皇別摂家|zh|皇别摄家|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Imperial regent houses|1=Kōbetsu sekke|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11581001}}
* {{ill|Return of former imperial family to the Imperial House debate|de|Debatte über die Rückkehr ehemaliger Prinzenhäuser|ja|皇籍離脱者の皇籍復帰問題|zh|皇籍离脱者的皇籍复归问题|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Return of former imperial family to the Imperial House debate|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Commoners in Japan|de|Bürgerliche (Japan)|ja|庶民|zh|庶民|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Commoners in Japan|1=Commoners in Japan|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11063536}}

== External links ==
* [https://www.kunaicho.go.jp/about/kosei/motokozoku.html Departures from Imperial Status upon Marriage – Imperial Household Agency]
* {{コトバンク|臣籍降下|qq=}}
* {{コトバンク|賜姓降下|qq=}}
* {{コトバンク|皇籍離脱|qq=}}
* {{コトバンク|臣籍降嫁|qq=}}

{{天皇項目|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|臣籍降下|version=104663439|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:臣籍降下]]
[[de:Shinsekikōka]]

&lt;!-- table truncated for brevity --&gt;

&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[fa:شینسکی کوکا]]
[[ko:신적강하]]
[[zh:臣籍降下]]
[[zh-min-nan:Sîn-che̍k kàng-hā]]
{{wikidata link|Q8193495}}
[[Category:Family registers]]
[[Category:Heian period]]
[[Category:Imperial Princes Granted Surnames]]
[[Category:Japanese monarchy]]
[[Category:Kuge]]
[[Category:Samurai]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]
[[Category:Pages with 50+ untranslated japanese characters]]</text>
      <sha1>p8lis36uefj4sud2lhi39gy0hp904nc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
