<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>109075</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3236627</id>
      <timestamp>2026-02-26T03:03:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: migrate talk page structure; import discussion seed (ja:靖国神社問題, en:Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine); add local discussion section + dated import note</comment>
      <origin>3236627</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="31195" sha1="dx8jt5o8bjjkf7q4683rl676vagbpu4" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/96400050 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:靖国神社問題 | revid=96400050 --&gt;
{{削除依頼ログ
|talk=false
|result1=存続|page1=靖国神社問題|date1=2005年11月4日
}}


{{talkheader}}
{{論争的}}
{{出典検索|靖国神社}}
{{archive box|auto=yes}}

==天皇陛下の靖国参拝について==

{{提案}} 以下の記述を記事に入れる事を提案します。

[[富田メモ]]云々があるかと思いますが、時系列に並べると以下の通りになります。

{{Quotation|*1975年11月20日　内閣委員会で天皇陛下の靖国神社参拝を、社会党の[[秦豊]]氏、野田哲氏、[[矢田部理]]氏が問題視する。
*1975年11月21日　昭和天皇、最後の靖国神社参拝
*1978年10月17日　所謂A級戦犯の合祀が行われる
*1979年4月19日　[[朝日新聞]]が所謂A級戦犯を靖国神社に合祀したことを記事にする。
*1982年　　　　社会党の[[田邊誠]]氏が、[[中国共産党中央委員会]]に対して[[南京大虐殺紀念館]]を建設する様に、再三要請
*1985年　　　　この年以降、中国が靖国神社参拝を問題視する様になる。}}

問題視された主な内容は、以下の答弁から始まりました。

{{Quotation|社会党の野田哲氏「いま植木長官はそういうふうに言われますけれども、八月十五日に三木総理が靖国神社へ参拝した。これはいま吉國長官も'''私的行為だということで強弁'''されておりますけれども、いかに私的行為だと言っても、あの当時のやはり国民の受けとめ方というか、靖国神社の国家護持を推進しようとする団体は、あの三木総理がいかに私人だと言ったって、総理が靖国神社へ参拝してくれたということをもって靖国神社国家護持の運動は一歩前進をするというふうに'''団体の機関紙'''などで評価をしておるんですよ、評価を。恐らく明日の'''天皇の靖国神社参拝'''についても、そういう形で取り扱う団体が絶対にないとは保証できないでしょう。これは保証できない。だとするならば、あなた方がどういうふうに理解をされようとも、明らかにこれは'''政治的に利用された'''ということになるではないですか。そういう懸念は一切持っていないんですか、政府の方では。どうですか長官。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の145番目の答弁より引用)　}}

それに対し、富田メモで有名な宮内庁の富田長官が、

{{Quotation|宮内庁の富田朝彦氏「先ほど来私も申し上げておりますように、多くの戦没された方々への陛下の気持ちをあらわされたいというその御意思に基づく私的な行為でございます。そういうことに関連しての諸問題につきましては、ただいま総務長官がお述べになられましたように、そういう'''政治の渦中に巻き込まれる'''ということは'''絶対ないという配慮'''のもとにまいりたいと、かように考えております。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の170番目の答弁より引用)　}}　

と締めくくり、それ以降、天皇陛下が靖国神社に参拝されることは無くなりました。--[[利用者:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月3日 (月) 06:04 (UTC)

以上の記述です。如何でしょうか？--[[利用者:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 01:38 (UTC)

最後の一文の「天皇参拝」とは「親拝」のことであり、例大祭等に天皇からの勅使参向（これも天皇の参拝に当たる）が続いている点など、皇室との関係がその後も保たれている点の事実関係は補足しておいた方がよいと思います。--[[利用者:Kogane|Kogane]]（[[利用者‐会話:Kogane|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 08:33 (UTC)
: 旧勅祭社ですから形式的とも言えます（平安神宮でも「勅使参向」はありますから）。これを「天皇の参拝」と同視する行為とまでいえるのかどうか。但し、事実としての記述は「勅祭社」の意義、歴史などの点を踏まえ、評価についても過大でなく事実を淡々と書くことには賛成です。--[[利用者:T34-76|T34-76]]（[[利用者‐会話:T34-76|会話]]） 2014年3月21日 (金) 09:39 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== プロパガンダカテゴリ ==

Category:中華人民共和国のプロパガンダとCategory:韓国のプロパガンダにカテゴライズされていますが、記事の現状を見ると二国政府から発信された情報についての記述は記事全体からみてごく少量でしかなく、日本国内での論争や訴訟に関する記述が大半です。この二国のカテゴライズはしない方がいいかと思います。[[:Category:韓国のプロパガンダ]]内にある記事は韓国国内の事物か韓国政府の傘下にある事物です。 --[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B|2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B]] 2020年10月23日 (金) 03:57 (UTC)
:{{済}}--[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6|2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6]] 2022年4月21日 (木) 12:39 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1335386070 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine | revid=1335386070 --&gt;
{{controversial}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|
{{WikiProject Japan|importance=mid|tokyo=yes|attention=yes|shinto=yes}}
}}

==Rewrite==
I rewrote the article on Yasukuni and it was rated a "B" (hoping to make it a GA still), but now it is time to tackle this article and its problems. I've been doing research and have lots of citations and timeline details. I will also "neutralize the discussion" as it has become very passionate, which should not be used here. This is a factual discussion of the sides of a dispute based on religious beliefs and public vs. private matters which the Japanese are very keen to separate. We here in the Americas may not see the need to understand the separation, but any religious matter is a personal and/or private one in Japan. Also families go to the shrine to visit their dead comrades and relatives, so much more care should be taken in making factual statements about this controversy. Finally, it would make sense that countries outside of Japan may be overstepping their place when commenting about internal religious matters of another country. Eg: China and Tibet, China regularly tells all other countries to mind their own business as it is an internal matter. I will begin some work right away this weekend. Please feel free to give me some feedback. [[Takashi Ueki]] 16 May 2009

So, I finally split the two articles. Right now, I'm focusing all of my efforts on cleaning, referencing, editing and organizing the controversy section in [[Yasukuni Shrine]]. No easy task. Harder still, would be trying to clean up this article. There is a LOT of information here (sourced and unsourced) that will take a lot of time to organize correctly. If anyone is up to the task, go for it. As for me, it is far too much for me to handle at the moment. I want to get the Yasukuni Shrine article up to possible [[GA]] status first, if possible.
[[User:Torsodog|Torsodog]] ([[User talk:Torsodog|talk]]) 08:17, 13 April 2008 (UTC)

:The first section really, really needs to be revised. The fact of the matter is, the individuals buried at Yasukuni were convicted as war criminals, period. This entry is not the proper forum for discussing the controversies surrounding the trials themselves.  The views of a dissenting Indian Justice, as an example, are completely irrelevant to this entry. &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class="autosigned"&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.141.155.6|74.141.155.6]] ([[User talk:74.141.155.6#top|talk]]) 21:04, 30 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Bunrei and kanjō==
It says in the text, "The Shinto processes of bunrei and kanjō exist specifically to remove a kami from its shrine and re-enshrine it elsewhere." This is not quite correct. It is almost true and would be if "remove" were changed to "move" since "bunrei" (lit 'dividing the spirit') leaves the kami at the originating shrine, while kanjo welcomes it to a new place/shrine. Kami are infinitely divisible without becoming any weaker, like signs. That there are Yasukuni Shrines all over Japan is achieved through this bunrei and kanjō, but the kami are not removed from the main shrine in Tokyo. The sentence gives the impression that it the process of "removing" a kami is very straightforward when it is rather very atypical (I know nothing about the Tokugawa period exceptions).--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:15, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

The below is from the [[kanjō]] article. 
"The process of propagation, described by the priests as akin to the lighting of a candle from another already lit, leaves the original kami intact in its original place and therefore doesn't alter any of its properties."--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:32, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

So I added ", but typically leaves the kami at the originating shrine intact and unchanged" to the article citing the kanjō article reference used to backup the above (imho very uncontroversial) claim.--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:40, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this line really need to be here? ==

"issue is somewhat different than that of visits by the German Chancellor to the Holocaust Memorial, which are explicitly made in the context of a state visit."

Isn't this comparing apples to oranges? The Chancellors are paying tribute to the victims of the Nazi regime, while the Japanese Prime Ministers (Fukuda excepted) are implicitly paying tribute to Hideki Tojo and the other so-called "martyrs of Showa". What the Prime Ministers are doing is more analogous to a hypothetical visit to the [[Kehlsteinhaus]] to pay respects to Hitler, and even that's not a 1-to-1 comparison.[[User:Pat Payne|Pat Payne]] ([[User talk:Pat Payne|talk]]) 19:10, 10 July 2008 (UTC)

:From what I recall, Mr Koizumi was criticised in Japan for signing the guest book of the shrine as prime minister. There was no concern with him appearing as a private individual in the following years.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.180.63.216|87.180.63.216]] ([[User talk:87.180.63.216|talk]]) 10:01, 16 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==A modification needs to be made toward the debate in Japan section==
The debate in Japan section starts out by pointing out the Shintoist perspecive view of the shrine, but that view should be moved to the end of the Debate in Japan section since the Debate in Japan section should be about the perspective view of the Japanese in general.  Only a minority in Japan deny the existance of war crimes.

Alright.  After no response i'm changing the Japanese section.  I'll also add a section mentions the Shinto perspective of the Yasukuni Shrine since the information at the start of the "debate in Japan" secton is more suitable for that.

After trying to add a Shinto perspective of the Shrine section nothing happins.  Strange...  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Graylandertagger|Graylandertagger]] ([[User talk:Graylandertagger|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Graylandertagger|contribs]]) 22:05, 18 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== "Furthermore it is believed that all negative or evil acts committed are absolved when enshrinement occurs." ==

This is the first I've ever heard of anything remotely like this in Shinto.  Shinto doesn't even really have things like "negative" or "evil", much less anything like "absolution".  There are bad guys and bad people, but there's nothing like "sin" in any branch of the religion as far as I know.  Furthermore, googling the terms "shinto enshrinement absolution" only returns this wikipedia page (and several other pages with incident hits where it talks about enshrinement in one place and absolution in another).

Unless there's a *good* citation, it needs to be removed.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/131.112.115.101|131.112.115.101]] ([[User talk:131.112.115.101|talk]]) 05:03, 25 September 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Taiwanese aborigine protest against Yasukuni ==

The aborigines were led by Taiwanese legislator [[May Chin]]

http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/detail.asp?ID=63832&amp;GRP=B

http://english.sina.com/taiwan_hk/1/2005/0914/45924.html

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 07:32, 23 February 2014 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this article belong in the Anti-Japanese Sentiment Category? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:07, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

Two editors, [[user:LoveJapanChika]] and [[user:NipponSun7]], have persistently attempted to add this page to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment.  When pressed for a reason, nipponsun claimed that "criticism of Japanese visiting a location in their home country" is justification for such.  As the article deals with a political controversy that has very little to do with claims of racism against Japanese, this claim seems to be a non-sequitur at best.  However, if there are more clear reasons as to why the category is appropriate, I would be interested in hearing them.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 04:57, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* We understand your bias Zmflavius. Your admissions of political controversy are justification for our edits. You do not own this article, and you are going to be facing constant and increasing editing pressure on this subject from pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias. Be honest and call a spade a spade: the critical contents of this article clearly represent anti-Japanese sentiment. Or are the controversies pro-Japanese? Please elaborate. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 18:41, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

::"pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias." I beg your pardon?  Are you perhaps aware of [WP:NPOV]]?  Let me quote it for you now:
:::"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic."
:::I myself am not editing from a position of bias, not least because this is exactly the wrong attitude to approach wikipedia with.  You will pardon me if I find that I am unimpressed by your threat of "constant and increasing editing pressure from pro-Japanese editors."  Having said all this, the controversies I think are best summed up by the first sentence of the lead, that is to say, "Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine are a major international issues surrounding the Yasukuni Shrine, which is a Japanese Shinto shrine."  The controversies reflect criticism of the actions of prominent Japanese politicians in visiting a controversial and politically-charged location.  The gap between criticism and actual bigoted sentiment is fairly great.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 22:48, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* Your quote of NPOV is exactly our argument. The entire article is not neutral. It should be removed from Wikipedia. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 05:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
::That is nonsense and not how NPOV works.  The article is writing about a very well-documented controversy which exists about Yasukuni Shrine.  That is more than sufficient grounds for being on wikipedia.  In any case, what ''is'' POV is supporting the removal or addition of material on such spurious grounds.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== NPOV dispute: Does this article belong in Wikipedia? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:05, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic." [[WP:NPOV]]
:Yes? [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;We'll continue to discuss it at length Zm. What most people don't understand is that China and Japan are one household. When we disagree in public, as all families do, it doesn't change the fact that we are stuck with each other permanently. The past is unchangeable. But we '''can''' choose to make a kinder, gentler future together. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 08:14, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::What does this have to do with the article?  Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a political platform. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 09:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;Zmflavius, you are once again making our POV-push argument for us. This article is a political polemic and should be removed or at least acknowledged to belong to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment. The simple addition of the appropriate category label would satisfy us. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 22:08, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::"I do not like what it has to say," which is the sum total of your objections to the article, is not a sufficient basis to suppress an article or label it as "anti-Japanese sentiment" (a category which, incidentally, is about documenting articles for which the subject falls into said category, not which you believe are such yourselves.).  As I have said above, I do not think either your claims about the purported bigotry present in this article or its subject stand up to scrutiny.
::On a somewhat related note, you seem to also have a misunderstanding as to what the purpose of the article is, especially in the context of the purpose of wikipedia.  The purpose of the article is to document (very well documented) controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine, which more than meet wikipedia's notability guidelines.  This is a subset of wikipedia's role in documenting information.  The role of the article is not to be a political polemic, nor is it the role of wikipedia to write either polemics or counter-polemics.  If you feel that this article as it currently exists is a political polemic, and can point to areas in the article which indicate as much, I would be interested in hearing how you would improve those sections of the article or the article as a whole.  Your proposals of either deletion or watering down the content of the article as a whole, however, do not appear to be adding any value to the article so far as I can see. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 23:40, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;In any case it is now an official NPOV dispute. Have a nice day. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 00:29, 17 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=701284391 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081121075607/http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm to http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 17:22, 23 January 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707784149 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20080618005612/http://www.iht.com:80/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php to http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:48, 1 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:6|one external link|6 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=752250629 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.korea.net/News/News/LangView.asp?serial_no=20070329019&amp;lang_no=1&amp;part=110&amp;SearchDay=
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://lccn.loc.gov/2007553672
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://asia.news.yahoo.com/060804/kyodo/d8j9m1ko0.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090501064407/http://www.nikkei.co.jp:80/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html to http://www.nikkei.co.jp/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227003151/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227012900/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227013006/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp:80/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:59, 30 November 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=771519497 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.tetsusenkai.net/official/yasukuni/english/japanese2.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 00:14, 22 March 2017 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=795197762 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:40, 12 August 2017 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dx8jt5o8bjjkf7q4683rl676vagbpu4</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3416096</id>
      <parentid>3236627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T02:02:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "利用者:" to "User:"</comment>
      <origin>3416096</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="31175" sha1="irnrnfpbgdv1jj62bmaylrneg2y5ki1" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/96400050 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:靖国神社問題 | revid=96400050 --&gt;
{{削除依頼ログ
|talk=false
|result1=存続|page1=靖国神社問題|date1=2005年11月4日
}}


{{talkheader}}
{{論争的}}
{{出典検索|靖国神社}}
{{archive box|auto=yes}}

==天皇陛下の靖国参拝について==

{{提案}} 以下の記述を記事に入れる事を提案します。

[[富田メモ]]云々があるかと思いますが、時系列に並べると以下の通りになります。

{{Quotation|*1975年11月20日　内閣委員会で天皇陛下の靖国神社参拝を、社会党の[[秦豊]]氏、野田哲氏、[[矢田部理]]氏が問題視する。
*1975年11月21日　昭和天皇、最後の靖国神社参拝
*1978年10月17日　所謂A級戦犯の合祀が行われる
*1979年4月19日　[[朝日新聞]]が所謂A級戦犯を靖国神社に合祀したことを記事にする。
*1982年　　　　社会党の[[田邊誠]]氏が、[[中国共産党中央委員会]]に対して[[南京大虐殺紀念館]]を建設する様に、再三要請
*1985年　　　　この年以降、中国が靖国神社参拝を問題視する様になる。}}

問題視された主な内容は、以下の答弁から始まりました。

{{Quotation|社会党の野田哲氏「いま植木長官はそういうふうに言われますけれども、八月十五日に三木総理が靖国神社へ参拝した。これはいま吉國長官も'''私的行為だということで強弁'''されておりますけれども、いかに私的行為だと言っても、あの当時のやはり国民の受けとめ方というか、靖国神社の国家護持を推進しようとする団体は、あの三木総理がいかに私人だと言ったって、総理が靖国神社へ参拝してくれたということをもって靖国神社国家護持の運動は一歩前進をするというふうに'''団体の機関紙'''などで評価をしておるんですよ、評価を。恐らく明日の'''天皇の靖国神社参拝'''についても、そういう形で取り扱う団体が絶対にないとは保証できないでしょう。これは保証できない。だとするならば、あなた方がどういうふうに理解をされようとも、明らかにこれは'''政治的に利用された'''ということになるではないですか。そういう懸念は一切持っていないんですか、政府の方では。どうですか長官。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の145番目の答弁より引用)　}}

それに対し、富田メモで有名な宮内庁の富田長官が、

{{Quotation|宮内庁の富田朝彦氏「先ほど来私も申し上げておりますように、多くの戦没された方々への陛下の気持ちをあらわされたいというその御意思に基づく私的な行為でございます。そういうことに関連しての諸問題につきましては、ただいま総務長官がお述べになられましたように、そういう'''政治の渦中に巻き込まれる'''ということは'''絶対ないという配慮'''のもとにまいりたいと、かように考えております。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の170番目の答弁より引用)　}}　

と締めくくり、それ以降、天皇陛下が靖国神社に参拝されることは無くなりました。--[[User:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月3日 (月) 06:04 (UTC)

以上の記述です。如何でしょうか？--[[User:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 01:38 (UTC)

最後の一文の「天皇参拝」とは「親拝」のことであり、例大祭等に天皇からの勅使参向（これも天皇の参拝に当たる）が続いている点など、皇室との関係がその後も保たれている点の事実関係は補足しておいた方がよいと思います。--[[User:Kogane|Kogane]]（[[利用者‐会話:Kogane|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 08:33 (UTC)
: 旧勅祭社ですから形式的とも言えます（平安神宮でも「勅使参向」はありますから）。これを「天皇の参拝」と同視する行為とまでいえるのかどうか。但し、事実としての記述は「勅祭社」の意義、歴史などの点を踏まえ、評価についても過大でなく事実を淡々と書くことには賛成です。--[[User:T34-76|T34-76]]（[[利用者‐会話:T34-76|会話]]） 2014年3月21日 (金) 09:39 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== プロパガンダカテゴリ ==

Category:中華人民共和国のプロパガンダとCategory:韓国のプロパガンダにカテゴライズされていますが、記事の現状を見ると二国政府から発信された情報についての記述は記事全体からみてごく少量でしかなく、日本国内での論争や訴訟に関する記述が大半です。この二国のカテゴライズはしない方がいいかと思います。[[:Category:韓国のプロパガンダ]]内にある記事は韓国国内の事物か韓国政府の傘下にある事物です。 --[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B|2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B]] 2020年10月23日 (金) 03:57 (UTC)
:{{済}}--[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6|2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6]] 2022年4月21日 (木) 12:39 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1335386070 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine | revid=1335386070 --&gt;
{{controversial}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|
{{WikiProject Japan|importance=mid|tokyo=yes|attention=yes|shinto=yes}}
}}

==Rewrite==
I rewrote the article on Yasukuni and it was rated a "B" (hoping to make it a GA still), but now it is time to tackle this article and its problems. I've been doing research and have lots of citations and timeline details. I will also "neutralize the discussion" as it has become very passionate, which should not be used here. This is a factual discussion of the sides of a dispute based on religious beliefs and public vs. private matters which the Japanese are very keen to separate. We here in the Americas may not see the need to understand the separation, but any religious matter is a personal and/or private one in Japan. Also families go to the shrine to visit their dead comrades and relatives, so much more care should be taken in making factual statements about this controversy. Finally, it would make sense that countries outside of Japan may be overstepping their place when commenting about internal religious matters of another country. Eg: China and Tibet, China regularly tells all other countries to mind their own business as it is an internal matter. I will begin some work right away this weekend. Please feel free to give me some feedback. [[Takashi Ueki]] 16 May 2009

So, I finally split the two articles. Right now, I'm focusing all of my efforts on cleaning, referencing, editing and organizing the controversy section in [[Yasukuni Shrine]]. No easy task. Harder still, would be trying to clean up this article. There is a LOT of information here (sourced and unsourced) that will take a lot of time to organize correctly. If anyone is up to the task, go for it. As for me, it is far too much for me to handle at the moment. I want to get the Yasukuni Shrine article up to possible [[GA]] status first, if possible.
[[User:Torsodog|Torsodog]] ([[User talk:Torsodog|talk]]) 08:17, 13 April 2008 (UTC)

:The first section really, really needs to be revised. The fact of the matter is, the individuals buried at Yasukuni were convicted as war criminals, period. This entry is not the proper forum for discussing the controversies surrounding the trials themselves.  The views of a dissenting Indian Justice, as an example, are completely irrelevant to this entry. &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class="autosigned"&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.141.155.6|74.141.155.6]] ([[User talk:74.141.155.6#top|talk]]) 21:04, 30 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Bunrei and kanjō==
It says in the text, "The Shinto processes of bunrei and kanjō exist specifically to remove a kami from its shrine and re-enshrine it elsewhere." This is not quite correct. It is almost true and would be if "remove" were changed to "move" since "bunrei" (lit 'dividing the spirit') leaves the kami at the originating shrine, while kanjo welcomes it to a new place/shrine. Kami are infinitely divisible without becoming any weaker, like signs. That there are Yasukuni Shrines all over Japan is achieved through this bunrei and kanjō, but the kami are not removed from the main shrine in Tokyo. The sentence gives the impression that it the process of "removing" a kami is very straightforward when it is rather very atypical (I know nothing about the Tokugawa period exceptions).--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:15, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

The below is from the [[kanjō]] article. 
"The process of propagation, described by the priests as akin to the lighting of a candle from another already lit, leaves the original kami intact in its original place and therefore doesn't alter any of its properties."--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:32, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

So I added ", but typically leaves the kami at the originating shrine intact and unchanged" to the article citing the kanjō article reference used to backup the above (imho very uncontroversial) claim.--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:40, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this line really need to be here? ==

"issue is somewhat different than that of visits by the German Chancellor to the Holocaust Memorial, which are explicitly made in the context of a state visit."

Isn't this comparing apples to oranges? The Chancellors are paying tribute to the victims of the Nazi regime, while the Japanese Prime Ministers (Fukuda excepted) are implicitly paying tribute to Hideki Tojo and the other so-called "martyrs of Showa". What the Prime Ministers are doing is more analogous to a hypothetical visit to the [[Kehlsteinhaus]] to pay respects to Hitler, and even that's not a 1-to-1 comparison.[[User:Pat Payne|Pat Payne]] ([[User talk:Pat Payne|talk]]) 19:10, 10 July 2008 (UTC)

:From what I recall, Mr Koizumi was criticised in Japan for signing the guest book of the shrine as prime minister. There was no concern with him appearing as a private individual in the following years.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.180.63.216|87.180.63.216]] ([[User talk:87.180.63.216|talk]]) 10:01, 16 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==A modification needs to be made toward the debate in Japan section==
The debate in Japan section starts out by pointing out the Shintoist perspecive view of the shrine, but that view should be moved to the end of the Debate in Japan section since the Debate in Japan section should be about the perspective view of the Japanese in general.  Only a minority in Japan deny the existance of war crimes.

Alright.  After no response i'm changing the Japanese section.  I'll also add a section mentions the Shinto perspective of the Yasukuni Shrine since the information at the start of the "debate in Japan" secton is more suitable for that.

After trying to add a Shinto perspective of the Shrine section nothing happins.  Strange...  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Graylandertagger|Graylandertagger]] ([[User talk:Graylandertagger|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Graylandertagger|contribs]]) 22:05, 18 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== "Furthermore it is believed that all negative or evil acts committed are absolved when enshrinement occurs." ==

This is the first I've ever heard of anything remotely like this in Shinto.  Shinto doesn't even really have things like "negative" or "evil", much less anything like "absolution".  There are bad guys and bad people, but there's nothing like "sin" in any branch of the religion as far as I know.  Furthermore, googling the terms "shinto enshrinement absolution" only returns this wikipedia page (and several other pages with incident hits where it talks about enshrinement in one place and absolution in another).

Unless there's a *good* citation, it needs to be removed.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/131.112.115.101|131.112.115.101]] ([[User talk:131.112.115.101|talk]]) 05:03, 25 September 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Taiwanese aborigine protest against Yasukuni ==

The aborigines were led by Taiwanese legislator [[May Chin]]

http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/detail.asp?ID=63832&amp;GRP=B

http://english.sina.com/taiwan_hk/1/2005/0914/45924.html

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 07:32, 23 February 2014 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this article belong in the Anti-Japanese Sentiment Category? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:07, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

Two editors, [[user:LoveJapanChika]] and [[user:NipponSun7]], have persistently attempted to add this page to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment.  When pressed for a reason, nipponsun claimed that "criticism of Japanese visiting a location in their home country" is justification for such.  As the article deals with a political controversy that has very little to do with claims of racism against Japanese, this claim seems to be a non-sequitur at best.  However, if there are more clear reasons as to why the category is appropriate, I would be interested in hearing them.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 04:57, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* We understand your bias Zmflavius. Your admissions of political controversy are justification for our edits. You do not own this article, and you are going to be facing constant and increasing editing pressure on this subject from pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias. Be honest and call a spade a spade: the critical contents of this article clearly represent anti-Japanese sentiment. Or are the controversies pro-Japanese? Please elaborate. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 18:41, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

::"pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias." I beg your pardon?  Are you perhaps aware of [WP:NPOV]]?  Let me quote it for you now:
:::"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic."
:::I myself am not editing from a position of bias, not least because this is exactly the wrong attitude to approach wikipedia with.  You will pardon me if I find that I am unimpressed by your threat of "constant and increasing editing pressure from pro-Japanese editors."  Having said all this, the controversies I think are best summed up by the first sentence of the lead, that is to say, "Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine are a major international issues surrounding the Yasukuni Shrine, which is a Japanese Shinto shrine."  The controversies reflect criticism of the actions of prominent Japanese politicians in visiting a controversial and politically-charged location.  The gap between criticism and actual bigoted sentiment is fairly great.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 22:48, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* Your quote of NPOV is exactly our argument. The entire article is not neutral. It should be removed from Wikipedia. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 05:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
::That is nonsense and not how NPOV works.  The article is writing about a very well-documented controversy which exists about Yasukuni Shrine.  That is more than sufficient grounds for being on wikipedia.  In any case, what ''is'' POV is supporting the removal or addition of material on such spurious grounds.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== NPOV dispute: Does this article belong in Wikipedia? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:05, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic." [[WP:NPOV]]
:Yes? [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;We'll continue to discuss it at length Zm. What most people don't understand is that China and Japan are one household. When we disagree in public, as all families do, it doesn't change the fact that we are stuck with each other permanently. The past is unchangeable. But we '''can''' choose to make a kinder, gentler future together. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 08:14, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::What does this have to do with the article?  Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a political platform. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 09:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;Zmflavius, you are once again making our POV-push argument for us. This article is a political polemic and should be removed or at least acknowledged to belong to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment. The simple addition of the appropriate category label would satisfy us. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 22:08, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::"I do not like what it has to say," which is the sum total of your objections to the article, is not a sufficient basis to suppress an article or label it as "anti-Japanese sentiment" (a category which, incidentally, is about documenting articles for which the subject falls into said category, not which you believe are such yourselves.).  As I have said above, I do not think either your claims about the purported bigotry present in this article or its subject stand up to scrutiny.
::On a somewhat related note, you seem to also have a misunderstanding as to what the purpose of the article is, especially in the context of the purpose of wikipedia.  The purpose of the article is to document (very well documented) controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine, which more than meet wikipedia's notability guidelines.  This is a subset of wikipedia's role in documenting information.  The role of the article is not to be a political polemic, nor is it the role of wikipedia to write either polemics or counter-polemics.  If you feel that this article as it currently exists is a political polemic, and can point to areas in the article which indicate as much, I would be interested in hearing how you would improve those sections of the article or the article as a whole.  Your proposals of either deletion or watering down the content of the article as a whole, however, do not appear to be adding any value to the article so far as I can see. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 23:40, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;In any case it is now an official NPOV dispute. Have a nice day. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 00:29, 17 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=701284391 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081121075607/http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm to http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 17:22, 23 January 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707784149 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20080618005612/http://www.iht.com:80/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php to http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:48, 1 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:6|one external link|6 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=752250629 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.korea.net/News/News/LangView.asp?serial_no=20070329019&amp;lang_no=1&amp;part=110&amp;SearchDay=
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://lccn.loc.gov/2007553672
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://asia.news.yahoo.com/060804/kyodo/d8j9m1ko0.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090501064407/http://www.nikkei.co.jp:80/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html to http://www.nikkei.co.jp/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227003151/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227012900/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227013006/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp:80/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:59, 30 November 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=771519497 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.tetsusenkai.net/official/yasukuni/english/japanese2.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 00:14, 22 March 2017 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=795197762 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:40, 12 August 2017 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>irnrnfpbgdv1jj62bmaylrneg2y5ki1</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3618125</id>
      <parentid>3416096</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-22T15:22:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Project:History cleanup|Offloading history due to miraheze stability concerns]] previous contributors were [[User:en&gt;Tyris776]], [[User:Immanuelle]], [[User:EmmaBot]], see [https://emmaleonhart.github.io/shintowiki-scripts/wikihistory.html?page=Controversies_surrounding_Yasukuni_Shrine here] for full history [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24756154998|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3618125</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="31554" sha1="96idt87vcnoc5vuhsogbtf318ul53hd" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- History offloaded: due to miraheze stability concerns, the edit history of this page has been offloaded to the XML archive. See https://emmaleonhart.github.io/shintowiki-scripts/wikihistory.html?page=Controversies_surrounding_Yasukuni_Shrine for full history. Last refreshed: [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24756154998|commit triggered pipeline]] --&gt;
{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/96400050 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:靖国神社問題 | revid=96400050 --&gt;
{{削除依頼ログ
|talk=false
|result1=存続|page1=靖国神社問題|date1=2005年11月4日
}}


{{talkheader}}
{{論争的}}
{{出典検索|靖国神社}}
{{archive box|auto=yes}}

==天皇陛下の靖国参拝について==

{{提案}} 以下の記述を記事に入れる事を提案します。

[[富田メモ]]云々があるかと思いますが、時系列に並べると以下の通りになります。

{{Quotation|*1975年11月20日　内閣委員会で天皇陛下の靖国神社参拝を、社会党の[[秦豊]]氏、野田哲氏、[[矢田部理]]氏が問題視する。
*1975年11月21日　昭和天皇、最後の靖国神社参拝
*1978年10月17日　所謂A級戦犯の合祀が行われる
*1979年4月19日　[[朝日新聞]]が所謂A級戦犯を靖国神社に合祀したことを記事にする。
*1982年　　　　社会党の[[田邊誠]]氏が、[[中国共産党中央委員会]]に対して[[南京大虐殺紀念館]]を建設する様に、再三要請
*1985年　　　　この年以降、中国が靖国神社参拝を問題視する様になる。}}

問題視された主な内容は、以下の答弁から始まりました。

{{Quotation|社会党の野田哲氏「いま植木長官はそういうふうに言われますけれども、八月十五日に三木総理が靖国神社へ参拝した。これはいま吉國長官も'''私的行為だということで強弁'''されておりますけれども、いかに私的行為だと言っても、あの当時のやはり国民の受けとめ方というか、靖国神社の国家護持を推進しようとする団体は、あの三木総理がいかに私人だと言ったって、総理が靖国神社へ参拝してくれたということをもって靖国神社国家護持の運動は一歩前進をするというふうに'''団体の機関紙'''などで評価をしておるんですよ、評価を。恐らく明日の'''天皇の靖国神社参拝'''についても、そういう形で取り扱う団体が絶対にないとは保証できないでしょう。これは保証できない。だとするならば、あなた方がどういうふうに理解をされようとも、明らかにこれは'''政治的に利用された'''ということになるではないですか。そういう懸念は一切持っていないんですか、政府の方では。どうですか長官。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の145番目の答弁より引用)　}}

それに対し、富田メモで有名な宮内庁の富田長官が、

{{Quotation|宮内庁の富田朝彦氏「先ほど来私も申し上げておりますように、多くの戦没された方々への陛下の気持ちをあらわされたいというその御意思に基づく私的な行為でございます。そういうことに関連しての諸問題につきましては、ただいま総務長官がお述べになられましたように、そういう'''政治の渦中に巻き込まれる'''ということは'''絶対ないという配慮'''のもとにまいりたいと、かように考えております。」

(第０７６回国会[[内閣委員会]]第４号　昭和50年(1975年)11月20日[[参議院]]の170番目の答弁より引用)　}}　

と締めくくり、それ以降、天皇陛下が靖国神社に参拝されることは無くなりました。--[[User:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月3日 (月) 06:04 (UTC)

以上の記述です。如何でしょうか？--[[User:鈴木直紀|鈴木直紀]]（[[利用者‐会話:鈴木直紀|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 01:38 (UTC)

最後の一文の「天皇参拝」とは「親拝」のことであり、例大祭等に天皇からの勅使参向（これも天皇の参拝に当たる）が続いている点など、皇室との関係がその後も保たれている点の事実関係は補足しておいた方がよいと思います。--[[User:Kogane|Kogane]]（[[利用者‐会話:Kogane|会話]]） 2014年2月4日 (火) 08:33 (UTC)
: 旧勅祭社ですから形式的とも言えます（平安神宮でも「勅使参向」はありますから）。これを「天皇の参拝」と同視する行為とまでいえるのかどうか。但し、事実としての記述は「勅祭社」の意義、歴史などの点を踏まえ、評価についても過大でなく事実を淡々と書くことには賛成です。--[[User:T34-76|T34-76]]（[[利用者‐会話:T34-76|会話]]） 2014年3月21日 (金) 09:39 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== プロパガンダカテゴリ ==

Category:中華人民共和国のプロパガンダとCategory:韓国のプロパガンダにカテゴライズされていますが、記事の現状を見ると二国政府から発信された情報についての記述は記事全体からみてごく少量でしかなく、日本国内での論争や訴訟に関する記述が大半です。この二国のカテゴライズはしない方がいいかと思います。[[:Category:韓国のプロパガンダ]]内にある記事は韓国国内の事物か韓国政府の傘下にある事物です。 --[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B|2001:240:2414:7152:BC93:FD63:5285:74B]] 2020年10月23日 (金) 03:57 (UTC)
:{{済}}--[[特別:投稿記録/2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6|2001:240:240A:A494:9493:C67D:DA84:F3C6]] 2022年4月21日 (木) 12:39 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1335386070 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine | revid=1335386070 --&gt;
{{controversial}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|
{{WikiProject Japan|importance=mid|tokyo=yes|attention=yes|shinto=yes}}
}}

==Rewrite==
I rewrote the article on Yasukuni and it was rated a "B" (hoping to make it a GA still), but now it is time to tackle this article and its problems. I've been doing research and have lots of citations and timeline details. I will also "neutralize the discussion" as it has become very passionate, which should not be used here. This is a factual discussion of the sides of a dispute based on religious beliefs and public vs. private matters which the Japanese are very keen to separate. We here in the Americas may not see the need to understand the separation, but any religious matter is a personal and/or private one in Japan. Also families go to the shrine to visit their dead comrades and relatives, so much more care should be taken in making factual statements about this controversy. Finally, it would make sense that countries outside of Japan may be overstepping their place when commenting about internal religious matters of another country. Eg: China and Tibet, China regularly tells all other countries to mind their own business as it is an internal matter. I will begin some work right away this weekend. Please feel free to give me some feedback. [[Takashi Ueki]] 16 May 2009

So, I finally split the two articles. Right now, I'm focusing all of my efforts on cleaning, referencing, editing and organizing the controversy section in [[Yasukuni Shrine]]. No easy task. Harder still, would be trying to clean up this article. There is a LOT of information here (sourced and unsourced) that will take a lot of time to organize correctly. If anyone is up to the task, go for it. As for me, it is far too much for me to handle at the moment. I want to get the Yasukuni Shrine article up to possible [[GA]] status first, if possible.
[[User:Torsodog|Torsodog]] ([[User talk:Torsodog|talk]]) 08:17, 13 April 2008 (UTC)

:The first section really, really needs to be revised. The fact of the matter is, the individuals buried at Yasukuni were convicted as war criminals, period. This entry is not the proper forum for discussing the controversies surrounding the trials themselves.  The views of a dissenting Indian Justice, as an example, are completely irrelevant to this entry. &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class="autosigned"&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.141.155.6|74.141.155.6]] ([[User talk:74.141.155.6#top|talk]]) 21:04, 30 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Bunrei and kanjō==
It says in the text, "The Shinto processes of bunrei and kanjō exist specifically to remove a kami from its shrine and re-enshrine it elsewhere." This is not quite correct. It is almost true and would be if "remove" were changed to "move" since "bunrei" (lit 'dividing the spirit') leaves the kami at the originating shrine, while kanjo welcomes it to a new place/shrine. Kami are infinitely divisible without becoming any weaker, like signs. That there are Yasukuni Shrines all over Japan is achieved through this bunrei and kanjō, but the kami are not removed from the main shrine in Tokyo. The sentence gives the impression that it the process of "removing" a kami is very straightforward when it is rather very atypical (I know nothing about the Tokugawa period exceptions).--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:15, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

The below is from the [[kanjō]] article. 
"The process of propagation, described by the priests as akin to the lighting of a candle from another already lit, leaves the original kami intact in its original place and therefore doesn't alter any of its properties."--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:32, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

So I added ", but typically leaves the kami at the originating shrine intact and unchanged" to the article citing the kanjō article reference used to backup the above (imho very uncontroversial) claim.--[[User:Timtak|Timtak]] ([[User talk:Timtak|talk]]) 06:40, 9 August 2013 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this line really need to be here? ==

"issue is somewhat different than that of visits by the German Chancellor to the Holocaust Memorial, which are explicitly made in the context of a state visit."

Isn't this comparing apples to oranges? The Chancellors are paying tribute to the victims of the Nazi regime, while the Japanese Prime Ministers (Fukuda excepted) are implicitly paying tribute to Hideki Tojo and the other so-called "martyrs of Showa". What the Prime Ministers are doing is more analogous to a hypothetical visit to the [[Kehlsteinhaus]] to pay respects to Hitler, and even that's not a 1-to-1 comparison.[[User:Pat Payne|Pat Payne]] ([[User talk:Pat Payne|talk]]) 19:10, 10 July 2008 (UTC)

:From what I recall, Mr Koizumi was criticised in Japan for signing the guest book of the shrine as prime minister. There was no concern with him appearing as a private individual in the following years.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.180.63.216|87.180.63.216]] ([[User talk:87.180.63.216|talk]]) 10:01, 16 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==A modification needs to be made toward the debate in Japan section==
The debate in Japan section starts out by pointing out the Shintoist perspecive view of the shrine, but that view should be moved to the end of the Debate in Japan section since the Debate in Japan section should be about the perspective view of the Japanese in general.  Only a minority in Japan deny the existance of war crimes.

Alright.  After no response i'm changing the Japanese section.  I'll also add a section mentions the Shinto perspective of the Yasukuni Shrine since the information at the start of the "debate in Japan" secton is more suitable for that.

After trying to add a Shinto perspective of the Shrine section nothing happins.  Strange...  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Graylandertagger|Graylandertagger]] ([[User talk:Graylandertagger|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Graylandertagger|contribs]]) 22:05, 18 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== "Furthermore it is believed that all negative or evil acts committed are absolved when enshrinement occurs." ==

This is the first I've ever heard of anything remotely like this in Shinto.  Shinto doesn't even really have things like "negative" or "evil", much less anything like "absolution".  There are bad guys and bad people, but there's nothing like "sin" in any branch of the religion as far as I know.  Furthermore, googling the terms "shinto enshrinement absolution" only returns this wikipedia page (and several other pages with incident hits where it talks about enshrinement in one place and absolution in another).

Unless there's a *good* citation, it needs to be removed.  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/131.112.115.101|131.112.115.101]] ([[User talk:131.112.115.101|talk]]) 05:03, 25 September 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Taiwanese aborigine protest against Yasukuni ==

The aborigines were led by Taiwanese legislator [[May Chin]]

http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/detail.asp?ID=63832&amp;GRP=B

http://english.sina.com/taiwan_hk/1/2005/0914/45924.html

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 07:32, 23 February 2014 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Does this article belong in the Anti-Japanese Sentiment Category? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:07, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

Two editors, [[user:LoveJapanChika]] and [[user:NipponSun7]], have persistently attempted to add this page to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment.  When pressed for a reason, nipponsun claimed that "criticism of Japanese visiting a location in their home country" is justification for such.  As the article deals with a political controversy that has very little to do with claims of racism against Japanese, this claim seems to be a non-sequitur at best.  However, if there are more clear reasons as to why the category is appropriate, I would be interested in hearing them.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 04:57, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* We understand your bias Zmflavius. Your admissions of political controversy are justification for our edits. You do not own this article, and you are going to be facing constant and increasing editing pressure on this subject from pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias. Be honest and call a spade a spade: the critical contents of this article clearly represent anti-Japanese sentiment. Or are the controversies pro-Japanese? Please elaborate. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 18:41, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

::"pro-Japanese editors who openly and honestly admit their bias." I beg your pardon?  Are you perhaps aware of [WP:NPOV]]?  Let me quote it for you now:
:::"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic."
:::I myself am not editing from a position of bias, not least because this is exactly the wrong attitude to approach wikipedia with.  You will pardon me if I find that I am unimpressed by your threat of "constant and increasing editing pressure from pro-Japanese editors."  Having said all this, the controversies I think are best summed up by the first sentence of the lead, that is to say, "Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine are a major international issues surrounding the Yasukuni Shrine, which is a Japanese Shinto shrine."  The controversies reflect criticism of the actions of prominent Japanese politicians in visiting a controversial and politically-charged location.  The gap between criticism and actual bigoted sentiment is fairly great.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 22:48, 15 November 2014 (UTC)

* Your quote of NPOV is exactly our argument. The entire article is not neutral. It should be removed from Wikipedia. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 05:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
::That is nonsense and not how NPOV works.  The article is writing about a very well-documented controversy which exists about Yasukuni Shrine.  That is more than sufficient grounds for being on wikipedia.  In any case, what ''is'' POV is supporting the removal or addition of material on such spurious grounds.[[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== NPOV dispute: Does this article belong in Wikipedia? ==
{{discussion top|1=Useless drivel posted by POV-pusher. No reason to keep this open. ···[[User:Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:darkgreen;"&gt;日本穣&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[WP:HIJCS|?]]&lt;/sup&gt; · &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Nihonjoe|&lt;span style="color:blue;"&gt;投稿&lt;/span&gt;]] · [[User talk:Nihonjoe|Talk to Nihonjoe]] · [[WP:JA|&lt;span style="color:maroon;"&gt;Join WP Japan&lt;/span&gt;]]!&lt;/small&gt; 06:05, 2 December 2014 (UTC)}}

"All encyclopedic content on Wikipedia must be written from a neutral point of view (NPOV), which means representing fairly, proportionately, and, as far as possible, without bias, all of the significant views that have been published by reliable sources on a topic." [[WP:NPOV]]
:Yes? [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 05:37, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;We'll continue to discuss it at length Zm. What most people don't understand is that China and Japan are one household. When we disagree in public, as all families do, it doesn't change the fact that we are stuck with each other permanently. The past is unchangeable. But we '''can''' choose to make a kinder, gentler future together. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 08:14, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::What does this have to do with the article?  Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a political platform. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 09:23, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;Zmflavius, you are once again making our POV-push argument for us. This article is a political polemic and should be removed or at least acknowledged to belong to the category Anti-Japanese sentiment. The simple addition of the appropriate category label would satisfy us. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 22:08, 16 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::"I do not like what it has to say," which is the sum total of your objections to the article, is not a sufficient basis to suppress an article or label it as "anti-Japanese sentiment" (a category which, incidentally, is about documenting articles for which the subject falls into said category, not which you believe are such yourselves.).  As I have said above, I do not think either your claims about the purported bigotry present in this article or its subject stand up to scrutiny.
::On a somewhat related note, you seem to also have a misunderstanding as to what the purpose of the article is, especially in the context of the purpose of wikipedia.  The purpose of the article is to document (very well documented) controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine, which more than meet wikipedia's notability guidelines.  This is a subset of wikipedia's role in documenting information.  The role of the article is not to be a political polemic, nor is it the role of wikipedia to write either polemics or counter-polemics.  If you feel that this article as it currently exists is a political polemic, and can point to areas in the article which indicate as much, I would be interested in hearing how you would improve those sections of the article or the article as a whole.  Your proposals of either deletion or watering down the content of the article as a whole, however, do not appear to be adding any value to the article so far as I can see. [[User:Zmflavius|Zmflavius]] ([[User talk:Zmflavius|talk]]) 23:40, 16 November 2014 (UTC)
:*&lt;small&gt;In any case it is now an official NPOV dispute. Have a nice day. [[User:LoveJapanChika|LoveJapanChika]] ([[User talk:LoveJapanChika|talk]]) 00:29, 17 November 2014 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

{{discussion bottom}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=701284391 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081121075607/http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm to http://sankei.jp.msn.com/politics/policy/071027/plc0710272135004-n2.htm/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 17:22, 23 January 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707784149 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20080618005612/http://www.iht.com:80/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php to http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/news.japan.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier;"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS;"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green;"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:48, 1 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:6|one external link|6 external links}} on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=752250629 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.korea.net/News/News/LangView.asp?serial_no=20070329019&amp;lang_no=1&amp;part=110&amp;SearchDay=
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://lccn.loc.gov/2007553672
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://asia.news.yahoo.com/060804/kyodo/d8j9m1ko0.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090501064407/http://www.nikkei.co.jp:80/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html to http://www.nikkei.co.jp/neteye5/suzuoki/20060816n598g000_16.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227003151/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131225p2a00m0na009000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227012900/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2g00m0dm032000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20131227013006/http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html to http://mainichi.jp/english/english/newsselect/news/20131226p2a00m0na004000c.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp:80/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:59, 30 November 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=771519497 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.tetsusenkai.net/official/yasukuni/english/japanese2.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 00:14, 22 March 2017 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified one external link on [[Controversies surrounding Yasukuni Shrine]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=795197762 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070312020848/http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php to http://www.janjan.jp/government/0607/0607228359/1.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, you may follow the instructions on the template below to fix any issues with the URLs.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false|needhelp=}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style="color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace"&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style="color:green;font-family:Rockwell"&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:40, 12 August 2017 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 03:03, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>96idt87vcnoc5vuhsogbtf318ul53hd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
