<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Akiba Shrines</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23742</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592170</id>
      <parentid>3225675</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:27:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592170</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="26497" sha1="sxnghu1xytb4d0phof7c1wz1mwxt4yz" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:秋葉神社]][[zh:秋葉神社]]


'''Akiba Shrine''' (秋葉神社, Akiba Jinja or Akiha Jinja) refers to Shinto shrines ({{ill|Shinto shrine|en|Shinto shrine|qid=Q845945|lt=Shrine|1=Shinto shrine}}) found throughout {{ill|Japan|en|Japan|qid=Q17|lt=Japan|1=Japan}}. Approximately 400 of these shrines are registered under the {{ill|Association of Shinto Shrines|en|Association of Shinto Shrines|qid=Q908077|lt=Association of Shinto Shrines|1=Association of Shinto Shrines}}. Additionally, according to a 2017 survey by historical geographer Yoneie Taisaku, there are 1,129 Akiba Shrines across Japan.{{sfn|米家(2017)|pp=155-157|qq=}}
Apart from shrines, Akiba is also worshipped in small roadside {{ill|Hokora|en|Hokora|qid=Q1442984|lt=hokora|1=Hokora}} or within Buddhist temples under the name '''Akibasan''' (秋葉山). The main deity worshipped at most Akiba Shrines is '''Akiba Daigongen''' (秋葉大権現), a deity resulting from {{ill|Shinbutsu-shūgō|en|Shinbutsu-shūgō|qid=Q2279088|lt=Shinbutsu-shūgō|1=Shinbutsu-shūgō}} (syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism), widely revered as a guardian deity against fires. Two main centers for this worship are the Enshū Akibasan (now {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}}) and Echigo Tochio Akibasan, known as Akiba Sanjakubō Daigongen, whose temple is {{ill|Jōan-ji|ja|常安寺|lt=Jōan-ji|lt_ja=常安寺|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Jōan-ji|1=Jōan-ji|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11481354}}.&lt;ref name="栃尾観協"&gt;{{Cite web|author=石田哲彌|title=秋葉神社と秋葉三尺坊|url=http://tochiokankou.jp/rekishi/akiba.html|website=一般社団法人 栃尾観光協会 公式ウェブサイト|accessdate=2019-07-29|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.joanji.jp/|title=清瀧山 常安寺 公式ホームページ|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; While it is generally considered that Akiba Daigongen worship spread nationwide during the reign of {{ill|Tokugawa Tsunayoshi|en|Tokugawa Tsunayoshi|qid=Q313745|lt=Tokugawa Tsunayoshi|1=Tokugawa Tsunayoshi}}, in reality, it often merged with pre-existing local traditions and legends related to protection against fire, making it difficult to clearly establish its origins.
Given its role as a deity protecting against fires, small shrines or hokora dedicated to Akiba Daigongen are often built from non-flammable materials such as stone. Frequently, these are modest structures, and multiple shrines can be found within the same local area.
== List of Akiba Shrines by Region ==
{{multiple image
 | align = right
 | direction = vertical
 | header = Head Shrines
 | header_align = center
 | header_background = darkseagreen
 | width = 200
 | image1 = Akiba jinja 17.jpg
 | caption1 = {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}} ({{ill|Shizuoka Prefecture|en|Shizuoka Prefecture|qid=Q131320|lt=ja|静岡県|1=Shizuoka Prefecture}}, {{ill|Hamamatsu|en|Hamamatsu|qid=Q185125|lt=ja|浜松市|1=Hamamatsu}})
 | image2 = Akiba Jinja, Tochio 01.jpg
 | caption2 = Akiha Sanjakubō Daigongen ({{ill|Niigata Prefecture|en|Niigata Prefecture|qid=Q132705|lt=ja|新潟県|1=Niigata Prefecture}}, {{ill|Nagaoka|en|Nagaoka|qid=Q356996|lt=ja|長岡市|1=Nagaoka}})
}}
* This list includes shrines, temples, and small shrines (hokora) associated with Akiha worship, including "Akiba Shrine," "Akiba-sha," "Akibayama Shrine," "{{ill|Akiba Gongen|ja|秋葉権現|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Akiba Gongen|qq=}}", and "Akiba Daigongen."
* If multiple shrines named "Akiba Shrine" exist in the same district, a note distinguishing them is provided.
* Shrine names with confirmed pronunciations have them indicated; shrines without a pronunciation have uncertain readings.
* Prefectures are listed according to the "{{ill|ISO 3166-2:JP|en|ISO 3166-2:JP|qid=Q456671|lt=ISO 3166-2:JP|1=ISO 3166-2:JP}}" standard.
=== Head Shrines ===
* {{ill|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|en|Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|qid=Q500413|lt=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine|1=Akihasan Hongū Akiha Shrine}} (Akihasan Hongū Akiha Jinja) - Located in Ryōke, {{ill|Haruno, Shizuoka|en|Haruno, Shizuoka|qid=Q11513827|lt=Haruno|1=Haruno, Shizuoka}}, {{ill|Tenryū-ku|en|Tenryū-ku|qid=Q1131460|lt=Tenryū-ku|1=Tenryū-ku}}, {{ill|Hamamatsu|en|Hamamatsu|qid=Q185125|lt=Hamamatsu|1=Hamamatsu}}, {{ill|Shizuoka Prefecture|en|Shizuoka Prefecture|qid=Q131320|lt=Shizuoka Prefecture|1=Shizuoka Prefecture}}. Origin of Akiba Daigongen worship. Considered one of two principal sites of Akiba Daigongen worship in Japan, referred to as the "present root." Traditionally established in the year {{ill|Wadō (era)|en|Wadō (era)|qid=Q1373026|lt=Wadō|1=Wadō (era)}} 2 ({{ill|709|en|709|qid=Q23514|lt=709|1=709}} CE).
* Akiha Sanjakubō Daigongen {{r|栃尾観協|qq=}} - Located in Yachi Nichōme, formerly {{ill|Tochio, Niigata|en|Tochio, Niigata|qid=Q1042935|lt=Tochio|1=Tochio, Niigata}} Yachi, {{ill|Nagaoka, Niigata|en|Nagaoka, Niigata|qid=Q540312|lt=Nagaoka|1=Nagaoka, Niigata}}, {{ill|Niigata Prefecture|en|Niigata Prefecture|qid=Q132705|lt=Niigata Prefecture|1=Niigata Prefecture}}. One of the two principal sites of Akiba Daigongen worship in Japan, known as the "ancient root."
*[https://www.joanji.jp Japanese Head Temple Bettō Jōan-ji]  
=== Hokkaido and Tohoku Region ===
==== Hokkaido ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located on Higashitakasu 6-sen in [[:en:Hokkaidō|Hokkaidō]][[Asahikawa City]] Akiba Shrine, Higashitakasu, Asahikawa City ({{googlemap|Akiba Shrine, Higashitakasu, Asahikawa City|qq=}}) *The facility is marked with a red spot. &lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Yoneya (2017)|p=155-157|qq=}}. This is the northernmost Akiba Shrine in Asahikawa City, the northernmost location where Akiba Shrines are located.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Tanyoshi 1-chome, [[Hokuto City]], Hokkaido.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Suzuoka, [[Setana District]][[Imakane Town]], Hokkaido.
* Obihiro Akiba Shrine - A shrine located on Yachiyocho Nishi 2-sen, [[Obihiro City]], Hokkaido.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Yutari, Nakagawa District, Honbetsu Town, Hokkaido.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located at Kita 3-jo Nishi 2-chome, Kamikawa District, Shimizu Town, Hokkaido.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located at Higashi 6-sen Kita 21, Sorachi District, Kamifurano Town, Hokkaido.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Asahi Town, Ashibetsu City, Hokkaido.
==== Aomori Prefecture ====
* Akibayama Shrine - A shrine located in Futsukamachi, Sannohe District, Sannohe Town, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Shimamori, Nango, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Sasinami, Korekawa, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Minato Takadai 1-chome, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Shimamori, Nango, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Nawabari, Minatomachi, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* [[Akibayama Shrine (Hachinohe City)|Akibayama Shrine]] - A shrine located in Katahira, Osawa, Shiroganemachi, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hachiman Hachimancho, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hikei, Hachinohe City, Aomori Prefecture.
==== Iwate Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kindaichi Nozuki, {{ill|Iwate Prefecture|en|Iwate Prefecture|qid=Q48326|lt=Iwate Prefecture|1=Iwate Prefecture}}[[Ninohe City]].
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Suginaka, Fukuoka, Ninohe City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in the 5th district of Oaza Toda, Kunohe District, Kunohe Village, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in the 13th district of Kuzumaki, Kunohe Town, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in the 9th district of Kamiioka, Morioka City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Fukibari Town, Hanamaki City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Shibuya, Futago Town, Kitakami City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located on Esashi Minami Odori, Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located off the coast of Mizusawa Anekata Town, Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Ite Aratani, Esashi, Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akibayama Shrine - A shrine located in Maesawayamashita, Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Miyajiki, Senmaya, Senmaya-cho, Iwate Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Wagata, Yonezaki-cho, Rikuzentakata-shi, Iwate Prefecture.
==== Miyagi Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Matsukawa, Kesennuma-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Minami-machi, Isakomasaka, Kurihara-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Ishinomaki-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Izumi-ku (Sendai-shi)|Izumi-ku 3, Sendai-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
* Fire Prevention Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kawaramachi 1-chome, Wakabayashi-ku, Sendai-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Suita, Inari-cho, Iwanuma-shi, Miyagi Prefecture.
==== Akita Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kitafukuda Iwahorakawahara, {{ill|Akita Prefecture|en|Akita Prefecture|qid=Q81863|lt=Akita Prefecture|1=Akita Prefecture}}[[Yurihonjo City]].
* Akiba Daigongen Shrine - A shrine located in Katsuragimiyakita, Yurihonjo City, Akita Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in 3-chome, [[:en:Akita City|Akita City]][[Omachi (Akita City)|Omachi]], Akita Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hirasawa Shinmachi, [[Nikaho City]], Akita Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Minase Suke Nagane, [[Yuzawa City]], Akita Prefecture.
* Akibayama Shrine - A shrine located in [[Yokote City]][[Omachi (Yokote City)|Omachi]], Akita Prefecture.
==== Yamagata Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in {{ill|Yamagata Prefecture|en|Yamagata Prefecture|qid=Q125863|lt=Yamagata Prefecture|1=Yamagata Prefecture}}[[:en:Sakata City|Sakata City]].
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in [[Higashitagawa District]][[Mikawa Town]], Yamagata Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in [[:en:Tsuruoka City|Tsuruoka City]], Yamagata Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Chojahara, [[:en:Mogami District|Mogami District]][[Funagata Town]], Yamagata Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Akayu, [[:en:Nanyo City|Nanyo City]], Yamagata Prefecture.
==== Fukushima Prefecture ====
* Kaida Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Oaza Kaida, {{ill|Fukushima Prefecture|en|Fukushima Prefecture|qid=Q71707|lt=Fukushima Prefecture|1=Fukushima Prefecture}}[[:en:Date District|Date District]][[Kunimi Town]].
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Aza Teramae, [[Kawamata Town]], Date District, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in the back of Yanagawa Town, [[Date City (Fukushima Prefecture)|Date City]], Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located under the bank of Mukaigawahara, Yanagawa Town, Date City, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Sakaemachi, Fukushima City, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located on Mt. Yuidai, Nihonmatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Nagahata, Haruyama, Funehiki Town, Tamura City, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Funehikidate, Funehiki Town, Tamura City, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Ushikawa, Kawanuma District, Aizubange Town, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kawazoe, Futaba District, Namie Town, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kami Shigeoka, Naraha Town, Futaba District, Fukushima Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hisanohama Higashimachi, Hisanohama Town, Iwaki City, Fukushima Prefecture. An Inari shrine is attached to the shrine.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Umegaoka, Shikura-cho, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima.
* Akihabara Shrine, the Fire Prevention God - A shrine located in Hiraagedo, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Sekitaminami-cho, Nakoso-cho, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Oaza Tanagura, [[Higashi Shirakawa-gun]][[Tanagura-cho]], Fukushima.
=== Kanto Region ===
==== Ibaraki Prefecture ====
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Ukishima, {{ill|Ibaraki Prefecture|en|Ibaraki Prefecture|qid=Q83273|lt=Ibaraki Prefecture|1=Ibaraki Prefecture}}[[Inashiki City]].
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Obara, [[Kasama City]], Ibaraki.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Obara, Kasama-shi, Ibaraki.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Akatsuka 1-chome, [[:en:Mito City|Mito City]], Ibaraki.
* Akihabara Shrine - A shrine located in Jyoto 5-chome, Mito-shi, Ibaraki.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Konosu, Naka City, Ibaraki Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Higashisanmachi, Hitachiota City, Ibaraki Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hitachi City, Ibaraki Prefecture.
==== Tochigi Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Isobe Town, Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Tada Town, Sano City, Tochigi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kaminamuma Town, Kanuma City, Tochigi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Nishikanuma Town, Kanuma City, Tochigi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Tokujiro Town, Utsunomiya City, Tochigi Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Sukagawa, Otawara City, Tochigi Prefecture.
==== Gunma Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A [[sub-shrine|auxiliary shrine]] in the grounds of [[Haruna Shrine]] in {{ill|Gunma Prefecture|en|Gunma Prefecture|qid=Q129499|lt=Gunma Prefecture|1=Gunma Prefecture}}[[Takasaki City]][[Harunayama Town]].
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Oaza Shinozuka, [[Oura District]][[Oura Town]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Mogi Town, [[:en:Ota City|Ota City]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Niijima Town, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Kasukawa Town, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in 2179 Ohara Town, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in 1058 Ohara Town, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Yabutsuka Town, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kokusadacho 1-chome, [[Isesaki City]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Asami, Kasakake Town, [[Midori City]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Shibukawa Motomachi-cho, [[Shibukawa City]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Harunayama-cho, Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Fuse, [[:en:Tone District|Tone District]][[Minakami Town]], Gunma Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Takahinata, Minakami Town, Tone District, Gunma Prefecture.
==== Saitama Prefecture ====
* [[Akiha Shrine (Saitama City Nishi Ward)|Akiha Shrine]] (Akihajinja) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|Japanese book|title= Akiha Shrine |url=http://www.akihajinja.or.jp/ |publisher=Kanto Sosha Akiha Shrine |accessdate=2019-07-29|qq=}}※The reading is based on the URL. &lt;/ref&gt; - A shrine located in {{ill|Saitama Prefecture|en|Saitama Prefecture|qid=Q128186|lt=Saitama Prefecture|1=Saitama Prefecture}}[[:en:Saitama City|Saitama City]][[Nishi Ward (Saitama City)|Nishi Ward]][[Nakakugi]]. It is considered to be the Kanto Sosha. It is said to have been founded during the [[:en:Tenpyo|Tenpyo]] era (between {{ill|729|en|729|qid=Q23561|lt=729|1=729}} and {{ill|749|en|749|qid=Q23624|lt=749|1=749}}).
* Akiha Shrine - A shrine located in [[Iwatsuki Ward]][[Nakacho (Saitama City Iwatsuki Ward)|Nakacho]] 1-chome, Saitama City, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kita Ward (Saitama City)|Kita Ward, Naramachi (Saitama City)|Naramachi, Saitama City, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Renjakucho, Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Tokorozawa City, Saitama Prefecture, Mikkashima (Tokorozawa City)|Mikashima.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kamihata, Hanno City, Saitama Prefecture.
* [[Akiba Shrine and Miza Inari|Akiba Shrine]] - A shrine located in Inaricho, Hanno City, Saitama Prefecture. Miza Inari is also located next to it.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Fujinoki 4-chome, Hasuda City, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Chuo 1-chome, Kasukabe City, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Sugito-machi, Kitakatsushika-gun, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Tsuda, Kumagaya-shi, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Otani, Higashimatsuyama-shi, Saitama Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Ishizaka, Hatoyama-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture.
==== Chiba Prefecture ====
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine in Takane-machi, Funabashi-shi, Chiba Prefecture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|Japanese books|url=https://yaokami.jp/1120296/ |title=Akiba Shrine |website=Eight million gods |publisher=INFO UNITE Co., Ltd. |accessdate=2019-07-29 |qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Sakurai, [[Futtsu City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Hirayama, [[Kimitsu City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Yamamoto, Kimitsu City, Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Mariya, [[Kisarazu City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kuramochi, [[Chōnan Town]], [[Chosen District]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Tsurumai, [[:en:Ichihara City|Ichihara City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Kaburagi, [[Asahi City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Konan, {{ill|Katori District|en|Katori District|qid=Q780284|lt=Katori District|1=Katori District}}, [[Tonosho Town]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Inō, [[Narita City]], Chiba Prefecture.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in 3-chome, [[:en:Chiba City|Chiba City]][[Hanamigawa Ward]][[Kemigawa-cho]], Chiba Prefecture. Mitsumine Shrine and Furumine Shrine are adjacent to it.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in 4-chome, [[Makuhari-cho (Chiba City)|Makuhari-cho]], Hanamigawa Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture. Konyo Shrine is adjacent to it.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in Matsudo City, Chiba Prefecture. Adjacent to [[Matsudo Shrine]].
==== Tokyo ====
* [[Akiba Shrine (Sumida Ward)|Akiba Shrine]] - A shrine located in 4-chome, [[Sumida Ward]][[Mukojima (Sumida Ward)|Mukojima]], Tokyo.
* [[Akiba Shrine (Taito Ward)|Akiba Shrine]] (Akibajinja) - A shrine located in {{ill|Tokyo|en|Tokyo|qid=Q1490|lt=Tokyo|1=Tokyo}}[[Taito Ward]][[Matsugaya (Taito Ward)|Matsugaya]]. Founded in [[Meiji]] 3 ({{ill|1870|en|1870|qid=Q7741|lt=1870|1=1870}}). It is said to be the origin of the place name "Akihabara".
* Satake Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in [[Taito (Taito Ward)|Taito]], Taito Ward, Tokyo.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in [[Mukaigaoka (Bunkyo Ward)|Mukaigaoka]] 2-chome, [[Bunkyo Ward]][[Mukaigaoka (Bunkyo Ward)|Mukaigaoka]], Tokyo.
* Akiba Shrine - A shrine located in [[:en:Shinjuku Ward|Shinjuku Ward]][[Yaraicho]], Tokyo.
* Akiba Shrine - Higashi

== See Also ==
* {{ill|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|en|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|qid=Q713021|lt=Atago Shrine|1=Atago Shrine (Kyoto)}} - Similarly associated with fire prevention.
* {{ill|Ushi Home|ja|牛ほめ|1=Ushihomu|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushi Home|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushihomu|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11570012}} - A {{ill|classical rakugo|ja|古典落語|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/classical rakugo|1=classic rakugo|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11410949}} story. The "Akiba-sama no ofuda" mentioned by Yotaro refers to protective amulets from Akiba Shrine.
* Akihabara Shrine - A separate shrine associated with the Heian religious group led by {{ill|Matsumoto Akeshige|ja|松本明重|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Matsumoto Akeshige|1=Akishige Matsumoto|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11531115}}, a sect of the {{ill|Church of World Messianity|en|Church of World Messianity|qid=Q3273757|lt=Sekai Kyūsei Kyō|1=Church of World Messianity}}. It is unrelated to Akiba Shrines.
== Expressions related to Akiba Shrine ==
'''Fire at Mount Akiba''' (秋葉山から火事, Akiba-san kara kaji) refers to someone in a position of authority or advisement committing the very error they warn against. It means a fire breaking out at Mount Akiba, a place revered as sacred to the fire-prevention deity. Also called "Akiba-sama no kaji."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Shinmeikai Koji Kotowaza Jiten|edition=2nd edition|year=2016|publisher={{ill|Sanseidō|en|Sanseidō|qid=Q1058813|lt=Sanseidō|1=Sanseidō}}|page=7|isbn=978-4385139883|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Okinawa Prefecture ==
* Akiba Shrine (秋葉神社, Akiba Jinja)&lt;ref name="北大東島"&gt;{{Cite web|title=秋葉神社|url=https://www.kitadaito.jp/shop_detail1.html?shop_code=652|website=北大東島観光ナビ|publisher=北大東村役場|accessdate=2019-07-30|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; - Located on {{ill|Kitadaitōjima|en|Kitadaitōjima|qid=Q1111504|lt=Kita Daito Island|1=Kitadaitōjima}} (Minami 44, {{ill|Kitadaitō, Okinawa|en|Kitadaitō, Okinawa|qid=Q1207554|lt=Kitadaitō Village|1=Kitadaitō, Okinawa}}, {{ill|Shimajiri District, Okinawa|en|Shimajiri District, Okinawa|qid=Q1206950|lt=Shimajiri District|1=Shimajiri District, Okinawa}}, {{ill|Okinawa Prefecture|en|Okinawa Prefecture|qid=Q766445|lt=Okinawa Prefecture|1=Okinawa Prefecture}}), founded in 1983 (Showa 58).&lt;ref group="gm"&gt;北大東島 秋葉神社（{{googlemap|北大東島秋葉神社|qq=}}）&lt;/ref&gt;
* Akiba Shrine - Located on {{ill|Minamidaitōjima|en|Minamidaitōjima|qid=Q1204188|lt=Minami Daito Island|1=Minamidaitōjima}} (Kyūhigashi, Minamidaitō Village, Shimajiri District, Okinawa Prefecture). It is the southernmost known Akiba Shrine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=秋葉神社/秋葉山/忠魂碑|url=https://www.ritou.com/spot/view-minamidaito-md41.html|website=沖縄離島ドットコム|accessdate=2019-07-30|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tripadvisor.jp/ShowUserReviews-g1121618-d15201012-r623092088-Akiba_Shrine-Minamidaito_son_Shimajiri_gun_Okinawa_Prefecture.html|title=秋葉神社 - Akiba Shrineの口コミ|website={{ill|Tripadvisor|en|Tripadvisor|qid=Q1770710|lt=TripAdvisor|1=Tripadvisor}}|accessdate=2019-07-30|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group="gm"&gt;南大東島 秋葉神社（{{googlemap|南大東島秋葉神社|qq=}}）&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Shinto topics|qq=}}
{{shinto-stub|qq=}}

== See Also ==
* {{ill|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|en|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|qid=Q713021|lt=Atago Shrine|1=Atago Shrine (Kyoto)}} - Similarly associated with fire prevention.
* {{ill|Ushi Home|ja|牛ほめ|1=Ushihomu|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushi Home|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushihomu|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11570012}} - A {{ill|classical rakugo|ja|古典落語|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/classical rakugo|1=classic rakugo|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11410949}} story. The "Akiba-sama no ofuda" mentioned by Yotaro refers to protective amulets from Akiba Shrine.
* Akihabara Shrine - A separate shrine associated with the Heian religious group led by {{ill|Matsumoto Akeshige|ja|松本明重|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Matsumoto Akeshige|1=Akishige Matsumoto|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11531115}}, a sect of the {{ill|Church of World Messianity|en|Church of World Messianity|qid=Q3273757|lt=Sekai Kyūsei Kyō|1=Church of World Messianity}}. It is unrelated to Akiba Shrines.
== Expressions related to Akiba Shrine ==
'''Fire at Mount Akiba''' (秋葉山から火事, Akiba-san kara kaji) refers to someone in a position of authority or advisement committing the very error they warn against. It means a fire breaking out at Mount Akiba, a place revered as sacred to the fire-prevention deity. Also called "Akiba-sama no kaji."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Shinmeikai Koji Kotowaza Jiten|edition=2nd edition|year=2016|publisher={{ill|Sanseidō|en|Sanseidō|qid=Q1058813|lt=Sanseidō|1=Sanseidō}}|page=7|isbn=978-4385139883|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Shinto topics|qq=}}
{{shinto-stub|qq=}}
== References ==
=== Note ===
{{Reflist|group="*"|qq=}}
; Googleマップ
{{Reflist|group="gm"|qq=}}
=== References ===
{{Reflist|qq=}}
==参考文献==
* {{Cite report|和書|author=米家泰作 |year=2017 |url=https://hdl.handle.net/2433/235233 |title=秋葉信仰の広がり --秋葉神社の分布に着目して-- |publisher=京都大学文学部地理学教室 |journal=2017th year 度実習旅行報告書--浜松市-- |pages=153-160 |hdl=2433/235233 |accessdate=2023-03-28 |ref={{harvid|米家(2017)|qq=}}|qq=}}

== See Also ==
* {{ill|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|en|Atago Shrine (Kyoto)|qid=Q713021|lt=Atago Shrine|1=Atago Shrine (Kyoto)}} - Similarly associated with fire prevention.
* {{ill|Ushi Home|ja|牛ほめ|1=Ushihomu|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushi Home|13=User:Immanuelle/Ushihomu|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11570012}} - A {{ill|classical rakugo|ja|古典落語|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/classical rakugo|1=classic rakugo|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11410949}} story. The "Akiba-sama no ofuda" mentioned by Yotaro refers to protective amulets from Akiba Shrine.
* Akihabara Shrine - A separate shrine associated with the Heian religious group led by {{ill|Matsumoto Akeshige|ja|松本明重|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Matsumoto Akeshige|1=Akishige Matsumoto|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11531115}}, a sect of the {{ill|Church of World Messianity|en|Church of World Messianity|qid=Q3273757|lt=Sekai Kyūsei Kyō|1=Church of World Messianity}}. It is unrelated to Akiba Shrines.
{{Shinto topics|qq=}}
{{shinto-stub|qq=}}



[[ja:秋葉神社]]
{{translated page|ja|秋葉神社|version=103309073|comment=Imported full ja history}}
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[zh:秋葉神社]]
{{wikidata link|Q11595841}}
[[Category:Fire prevention rituals]]
[[Category:Shinto shrines by tradition]]
[[Category:Akiha faith]]
[[Category:秋葉神社]]</text>
      <sha1>sxnghu1xytb4d0phof7c1wz1mwxt4yz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
