<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Akuro O</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21306</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592187</id>
      <parentid>3397055</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:27:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592187</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="10363" sha1="lw1wxl2aiwygs2rezorcpmoacse8er0" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:悪路王]]
{{Infobox person|gender={{ill|male|qid=Q6581097|1=Male (gender)}}}}

{{Good article}}
{{Otheruses|Legendary figure|Historical figure|Aterui}}
[[File:Picture of Head Sculpture of Akuro-ō at Takaku, Shirosato.JPG|thumb|Image of a head-shaped sculpture of Akuro-ō (replica). Displayed in the worship hall of Kashima Shrine in Takaku, Shirosato Town.]]
**Akuro-ō** (悪路王, *Akuro-ō*) is a legendary figure of Mutsu Province who appears in traditions of eastern Japan recorded during the Kamakura period. Depending on the source, the name is also written as **Akura-ō** (悪来王) or **Aguro-ō** (阿黒王), among others.

From the Kamakura period onward, the name appears in documents of eastern Japanese society such as those of Kashima Shrine and the Kamakura shogunate. In the *Kashima Shrine Documents*, “Akura-ō” is said to have been slain by Fujiwara no Yoritsune, while in the *Azuma Kagami*, “Akuro-ō” is described as a bandit leader of the Emishi who, together with Akagashira, was subjugated by Sakanoue no Tamuramaro and Fujiwara no Toshihito. When these eastern traditions were brought to Heian-kyō, they greatly influenced the formation of Muromachi-period otogi-zōshi (Muromachi tales). In particular, the account in the *Azuma Kagami* was carried over into the world of Tamura narratives, such as *The Tale of Suzuka*, compiled in the Muromachi period, where Akuro-ō is depicted as an oni (demon) defeated by Fujiwara no Toshihito, a character in otogi-zōshi.

In the Edo period, in the Tōhoku region, *Tamura Sandai-ki*, based on *Tamura no Sōshi*, spread widely as a representative performance of blind biwa monks narrating Oku-jōruri. It became entrenched as local legend across areas centered on the Date domain, extending through present-day Iwate and Miyagi prefectures and even across the Ōu Mountains into Akita Prefecture, and was incorporated into shrine and temple origin stories where it was performed. In many versions, Akuro-ō is said to have been defeated by the legendary figure Sakanoue no Tamuramaro, and even sequel legends such as the Hitokubemaru tradition were created.

There are also traces of Akuro-ō being conflated and fused with Takamaru, who appears in Suwa Shrine documents from the same era, sometimes being identified as the same figure under the name “Akuji no Takamaru.” From a folkloristic perspective, some theories identify Akuro-ō with the historical figure Aterui or suggest that the Akuro-ō legend arose using Aterui as a motif. In contrast, historians often argue that Akuro-ō is a later-created legend and cannot be accepted as historical evidence, regarding such identifications as mere folklore. As a result, scholarly opinions remain divided.

== History ==
=== Kamakura period ===
==== Kashima Shrine Documents ====
In the “Origins of the White Horse Festival” at Kashima Shrine in Miyauchi, Kashima City, Ibaraki Prefecture, a passage of the *Kashima Shrine Documents* dated the first year of Tenpuku (1233), written by Fujiwara no Saneyasu, mentions the name **Akura-ō**.
{{Quotation|In the reign of Retired Emperor Go-Horikawa, when the shōgun Fujiwara no Yoritsune, son of Regent Fujiwara no Michiie, descended to the Kantō region to subdue Akura-ō, he received a divine oracle from Kashima Shrine. Thereafter, storehouses were built within the shrine precincts, sacred treasures were enshrined, and seasonal rites were conducted without neglect, modeled after those of the imperial court.|Paraphrase from the *Kashima Shrine Documents*}}

Here, the one who defeated Akura-ō is said to be Fujiwara no Yoritsune (also known as Kujō Yoritsune), the first regent-family shōgun, and the episode served to advertise the military authority of the regent-family shōguns.

It is suggested that Fujiwara no Saneyasu, who wrote this “Origins of the White Horse Festival,” may in fact have been Naka no Saneyasu, a powerful gokenin of the early Kamakura period. This view is supported by the coincidence of names, the close relationship between the Naka clan and shōgun Yoritsune, the existence in Naka West District of Takaku Kashima Shrine, which preserves a head sculpture of Akuro-ō, and the fact that this district was an area where Kashima worship and the Takemikazuchi legend were particularly prominent in the medieval period.

Iruma Nobuo has pointed out that this may represent evidence that, in eastern Japan during the early Kamakura period, the mission of the shōgun was increasingly understood as the subjugation of Akuro-ō.

==== Azuma Kagami ====
In a prayer text dated March 24, 1126 (*Chūson-ji Kuyō Ganmon*), Fujiwara no Kiyohira styled himself “the distant chieftain of the eastern barbarians,” and over the course of a century the Ōshū Fujiwara clan carried out numerous projects in an effort to create a new culture in the land of the “eastern barbarians.” The clan fell in the autumn of 1189. These events, along with accounts of Tamuramaro’s deeds in northeastern Japan and Tamura narratives, are recorded in the *Azuma Kagami*, believed to have been compiled around 1300.

An entry dated September 21, 1189 records Minamoto no Yoritomo’s visit to Chinju-fu Hachiman Shrine in Isawa District.
{{Quotation|Yoritomo donated a sacred fence to Chinju-fu Hachiman Shrine, designating it the Second Shrine. This Hachiman shrine was founded when General Tamuramaro was dispatched to subdue the eastern barbarians. Tamuramaro deposited the bows, arrows, and whip he had brought with him, which are said to remain in the treasure house to this day. Yoritomo showed special reverence and ordered that henceforth all rites be conducted as prayers of the Kamakura shogunate.|Paraphrase from the *Azuma Kagami*}}

The record notes the surprise of the Kamakura side that Hachiman, venerated by the Seiwa Genji, had been enshrined at Chinju-fu by Tamuramaro even before the enshrinement of Iwashimizu Hachiman in 859. Yoritomo designated it the Second Shrine of Tsurugaoka Hachimangū and ordered that all rites be conducted as prayers of the shogunate.

An entry dated September 28 of the same year recounts Yoritomo’s passage through Takkoku no Iwaya near Hiraizumi on his return to Kamakura, where the name Akuro-ō appears.
{{Quotation|After defeating Fujiwara no Yasuhira in the Ōshū Campaign, Yoritomo accepted the submission of the surrendered Toshihira of Hinazume, released many captives, and proceeded toward Kamakura with fewer than thirty remaining prisoners. Stopping at a certain mountain, Yoritomo asked the captives about the local traditions.

They replied: “This is called Taya no Iwaya. When Generals Tamuramaro and Toshihito were dispatched by imperial command to subdue the Emishi, this was the rocky stronghold where the bandit leaders Akuro-ō and Akagashira held out.”

Beyond the cave, traveling north for more than ten days leads to Sotogahama. General Sakanoue built a nine-by-four-bay hall in front of the cave, enshrined Bishamonten in imitation of Kurama-dera, named it Saikō-ji, and donated rice fields. The donation extended east to the Kitakami River, south to the Iwai River, west to Zōō Iwaya, and north to Ushiki Nagamine, spanning more than thirty ri east to west and more than twenty ri north to south.|Paraphrase from the *Azuma Kagami*}}

Here, Akuro-ō and Akagashira are described as Emishi leaders defeated by Sakanoue no Tamuramaro and Fujiwara no Toshihito, after which Tamuramaro built Saikō-ji, enshrining Bishamonten in imitation of Kurama-dera. However, since Toshihito lived about a century after Tamuramaro, the tradition shows signs of chronological confusion.

Scholars have proposed various interpretations of how the Akuro-ō legend formed, noting factors such as the introduction of Kyoto-based narratives into the Hiraizumi area and exchanges with Kashima worship from Hitachi Province.

== Name ==
=== “Akuro” as a place name ===
One theory holds that “Akuro” originally referred to a region in northeastern Japan, and that the powerful local leader of that area came to be called “Akuro-ō.”

=== “Akuro” as “Evil Prince” ===
Another theory derives the name from the concept of “evil princes” (aku-ōji), deities embodying fierce spirits who were worshiped to pacify resentful souls after military subjugation. In this view, “evil” does not mean morally bad, but rather “strong and violent.”

== Debate over historicity ==
Some scholars, such as Takahashi Takashi, have argued that Akuro-ō and related Tamuramaro legends are little more than unsubstantiated folklore, while others emphasize the lack of historical evidence supporting Akuro-ō’s existence. Modern historians generally regard Akuro-ō as a legendary figure rather than a historical person.

== Local legends ==
Numerous regional legends concerning Akuro-ō are found across Iwate, Miyagi, Akita, Fukushima, Ibaraki, and Shiga prefectures, often identifying him as a demon or bandit leader defeated by Sakanoue no Tamuramaro and associating his story with caves, mountains, waterfalls, and shrines. These traditions vary widely in detail and often merge Akuro-ō with figures such as Takamaru, Ōtakemaru, or other oni of northeastern lore.

== See also ==
* Akuro-gami no Hi  
* Kinpira Shika  
* Akura-ō  
* Akuru-ō  
* Hyakuryūwaka Daijin  
* Haratai Kenbu-ren  
* Hayasaka  
* The Scarlet-Faced Emissary  
* Leviathan of the Covenant  

{{DEFAULTSORT:Akuro-ō}}
[[Category:Aterui]]
[[Category:Legendary figures of Japan]]
[[Category:People of the Heian period]]
[[Category:People of Mutsu Province]]
[[Category:History of the Tōhoku region]]
[[Category:Emishi]]
[[Category:Oni]]
[[Category:Tamura narratives|Strange Akuro-ō]]
== References ==
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== Related Articles ==
* {{ill|Emishi|en|Emishi|qid=Q932574|lt=Emishi|1=Emishi}}
* [[Sakanoue no Tamuramaro]]
* [[Japanese folklore]]
==References==
{{reflist|qq=}}
{{Suwa Faith|qq=}}
]
{{translated page|ja|悪路王|version=103929448|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:悪路王]]

[[ja:田村三代記]]

&lt;!--Akuro O--&gt;
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q18700408}}
[[Category:Aterui]]
[[Category:Legendary Japanese people]]
[[Category:Tamura storytelling]]
[[Category:蝦夷]]
[[Category:陸奥国の人物]]</text>
      <sha1>lw1wxl2aiwygs2rezorcpmoacse8er0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
