<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Amanoiwato Shrine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17452</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592236</id>
      <parentid>3591605</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:28:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592236</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="18897" sha1="73236vp003080vkndy5cmc4l7f7lzxy" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[en:Amanoiwato Shrine]][[fr:Amano-Iwato-jinja]][[ja:天岩戸神社]]


{{Otheruses|3=Amanoiwato Shrine (Fukuchiyama)|qq=}}{{Short description|Shinto shrine in Miyazaki Prefecture, Japan|qq=}}
{{ref improve|date=January 2014|qq=}}
{{Infobox religious building|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]| map_type = Japan Miyazaki Prefecture#Japan
| name = Amanoiwato-jinja&lt;br&gt;天岩戸神社
| image = File:Torii at Ama-no-Iwato Shrine, Takachiho, Miyazaki Prefecture.jpg
| caption = Torii at Amanoiwato-jinja
| map_type = Japan
| map_alt = 
| coordinates = {{Coord|32.734444|N|131.350556|E|region:JP_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
| map_relief  = 
| map_size = 
| map_caption = 
| religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]
| type = 
| deity = [[Amaterasu]]
| founded_by = 
| established = 
| date_destroyed = 
| location = 1073-1, Iwato, {{ill|Takachiho, Miyazaki|en|Takachiho, Miyazaki|qid=Q1350939|lt=Takachiho|1=Takachiho, Miyazaki}}&lt;br&gt;[[Nishiusuki District, Miyazaki|Nishiusuki District]]&lt;br&gt;{{ill|Miyazaki Prefecture|en|Miyazaki Prefecture|qid=Q130300|lt=Miyazaki|1=Miyazaki Prefecture}} 882-1621
| website = 
| architecture_style = 
| festival = 
| leadership = 
|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]|religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]| religious_affiliation = [[Shinto]]
| name = Amanoiwato Shrine
| location = 1073-1 Iwato, Takachiho Town, [[Nishiusuki District]], {{ill|Miyazaki Prefecture|en|Miyazaki Prefecture|qid=Q130300|lt=Miyazaki Prefecture|1=Miyazaki Prefecture}}
| festival Deities = (West Main Shrine) [[Ōhirume-no-Mikoto]]&lt;br/&gt; (East Main Shrine) [[Amaterasu]]
| Shrine Rank = Former [[Village Shrine]], [[Beppyo Shrine]]
| Shrine Building = (East Main Shrine) [[Shinmei-zukuri]]
| festival = (West Main Shrine) May 2-3&lt;br/&gt; (East Main Shrine) September 22-23
| Religious ceremony = Amanoiwato Kagura festival (November 3)
{{location map+|Japan Miyazaki Prefecture|width=200|float=center|caption=|places=
{{location map~|Japan Miyazaki Prefecture|lat_deg=32|lat_min=44|lat_sec=4|lon_deg=131|lon_min=21|lon_sec=2|position=left|label=West Main Shrine|mark=Shinto torii icon vermillion.svg|marksize=20|qq=}}
{{location map~|Japan Miyazaki Prefecture|lat_deg=32|lat_min=43|lat_sec=58|lon_deg=131|lon_min=21|lon_sec=2|position=right|label=East Main Shrine|mark=Shinto torii icon vermillion.svg|marksize=20|qq=}}|qq=}}
| location = {{ill|Takachiho|qid=Q1350939|1=Takachiho, Miyazaki}}
}}
{{nihongo|'''Amanoiwato-jinja'''|天岩戸神社||qq=}} is a Shinto shrine located in {{ill|Takachiho, Miyazaki|en|Takachiho, Miyazaki|qid=Q1350939|lt=Takachiho|1=Takachiho, Miyazaki}}, {{ill|Miyazaki Prefecture|en|Miyazaki Prefecture|qid=Q130300|lt=Miyazaki Prefecture|1=Miyazaki Prefecture}}, {{ill|Japan|en|Japan|qid=Q17|lt=Japan|1=Japan}}. It is dedicated to the sun goddess[[Amaterasu]] and sits above the gorge containing [[Amano-Iwato|Ama-no-Iwato]], the cave where, according to Japanese legend, the goddesshid after battle with her brother, plunging the world into darkness until lured out by the [[kami|spirit]] of merriment [[Ame-no-Uzume]].
The [[Amano-Iwato]] cave is an object of worship in festivals and is a rock cave on the other side of the Iwato River from nishihongū. You can see the cave from nishihongū after participating in a Shinto ritual for purification.&lt;ref name="JNTO"&gt;{{cite web|title=Amano-iwato Shrine - Japan National Tourism Organization|url=https://www.jnto.go.jp/eng/spot/shritemp/amano-iwato-shrine.html|website=Japan national tourism organization|accessdate=3 May 2017|language=en|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Overview==
'''Amanoiwato Shrine''' (あまのいわとじんじゃ) is a {{ill|Shinto shrine|en|Shinto shrine|qid=Q845945|lt=Shinto shrine|1=Shinto shrine}} located in [[Takachiho Town]], [[Nishiusuki District]], {{ill|Miyazaki Prefecture|en|Miyazaki Prefecture|qid=Q130300|lt=Miyazaki Prefecture|1=Miyazaki Prefecture}}. It consists of the East Main Shrine and West Main Shrine on either side of the [[Iwatogawa River]]. The former [[shrine Rank]] is [[Village Shrine]] and it is a [[Beppyo Shrine]] under the [[Association of Shinto Shrines]].
== Shrine name ==
The name derives from the [[Amano-Iwato]] worshiped by the West Main Shrine. The shrine was unified in Showa 45 and is now known as Amanoiwato Shrine East and West Main Shrines. Previously, the West Main Shrine was called "Amanoiwato Shrine" and the East Main Shrine was called "Ujigami Shrine." The East Main Shrine was also referred to as "Amanoiwato Daijingu," and this name remains on the talismans given at the West Main Shrine's shrine office, and is still used as a colloquial name by older locals.
== festival Deities ==
*West Main Shrine: '''Ōhirume-no-Mikoto''' (another name for [[Amaterasu]]), enshrined in the cave known as [[Amano-Iwato]] across the Iwatogawa River. The shrine also worships seven other deities at its traveling shrine: [[Ame-no-Uzume]], [[Tajikarao-no-Mikoto]], [[Toshigami|Ōtoshi-no-Kami]], [[Susanoo-no-Mikoto]], [[Hikohohodemi-no-Mikoto]], {{ill|Toyotama-hime|en|Toyotama-hime|qid=Q2329261|qid=Q2329261|lt=Toyotama-hime|1=Toyotama-hime}}, and {{ill|Sugawara no Michizane|en|Sugawara no Michizane|qid=Q382005|lt=Sugawara no Michizane|1=Sugawara no Michizane}}.
*East Main Shrine: '''Amaterasu Ōmikami''' (another name for Amaterasu, indicating the deity's role as the imperial ancestor). Historical documents also mention [[:en:Izanagi-no-Mikoto|Izanagi-no-Mikoto]] and {{ill|Izanami|en|Izanami|qid=Q682306|lt=Izanami|1=Izanami}} being enshrined here&lt;ref name="r1"&gt;Heibu Takami, "Hyuga Chishi," reprint edition, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;. A small shrine behind the main building, next to a sacred spring, is dedicated to "Daijingu."
== History ==
Originally, the East and West Main Shrines were independent entities. Both shrines worship Amaterasu Ōmikami, but their primary worshipers were local residents rather than the [[:en:Imperial Family|Imperial Family]] or {{ill|Imperial Court|en|Imperial Court|qid=Q6006523|lt=Imperial Court|1=Imperial Court}}.
[[File:Torii at Ama-no-Iwato Shrine, Takachiho, Miyazaki Prefecture.jpg|thumb|Torii at West Main Shrine]]
Although the foundation date of the West Main Shrine is unclear, its enshrinement of the cave (Amano-Iwato) as a sacred object indicates ancient worship practices. According to shrine tradition, the shrine was established by [[Ninigi-no-Mikoto]] to commemorate the Amano-Iwato incident and was restored by [[Ōkimi no Mikoto]] in [[:en:Kōnin|Kōnin]] 3 (812). The shrine burned down several times during the {{ill|Sengoku period|en|Sengoku period|qid=Q204023|lt=Sengoku period|1=Sengoku period}}. The 1691 record "Takachiho Kyuuki"&lt;ref name="r2"&gt;"Takachiho Town History: Local History Edition," Takachiho Town, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; only mentions a hall of worship and a torii, indicating it was a simple place for remote worship. A plaque from 1707 shows that the shrine site was restored, and in 1821, the main shrine building was rebuilt with the assistance of the {{ill|Nobeoka Domain|en|Nobeoka Domain|qid=Q10863441|lt=Nobeoka Domain|1=Nobeoka Domain}}. The shrine site is described in {{ill|Matsuura Takeshirō|en|Matsuura Takeshirō|qid=Q11531839|lt=Matsuura Takeshirō|1=Matsuura Takeshirō}}'s travelogue "Saikai Zasshi" (1837)&lt;ref name="r2"/&gt;. The former name "Amanoiwato" remained until 1871 when it was renamed "Amanoiwato Shrine." It was designated as a village shrine in 1873, and a new shrine building was constructed in 1897. In the Meiji era, several nearby shrines were merged into Amanoiwato Shrine.
[[File:Amanoiwato-east-shrine.jpg|thumb|Amanoiwato Shrine East Main Shrine]]
The foundation date of the East Main Shrine is also unclear. According to an ancient document from the Shōtai era (898-901), the shrine was established by [[Omoikane-no-Kami]], who asked Amaterasu Ōmikami to be enshrined in a newly built shrine. The 1691 "Takachiho Kyuuki"&lt;ref name="r2"/&gt; mentions the "Iwa Shrine" and "Iwakami" (a local place name), which likely refer to the East Main Shrine. An 1840 stone lantern still stands on the approach. [[Kaku Hikasu]], who visited the shrine in 1841, wrote about its autumn festival and described the shrine in his travelogue "Nanyū Nikki"&lt;ref name="r3"&gt;"Takachiho Town History," Takachiho Town, 1973&lt;/ref&gt;. The shrine was called "Ujigami Shrine" until 1871 when it was renamed "Ujigami Shrine" and designated as a village shrine in 1873.
Both shrines joined the [[Association of Shinto Shrines]] after World War II and were unified in Showa 45. They are currently designated as a Beppyo Shrine.
Today, the shrine office is located at the West Main Shrine, which is also the primary site for visitors. Historically, however, the East Main Shrine, which enshrines Amaterasu Ōmikami, has been the main focus of worship.
== Religious ceremony ==
*West Main Shrine festival (May 2-3): A spring grand festival. The first day features a ceremony with local dignitaries, and on the second day, two portable shrines carry the deity from the East Main Shrine in a procession guarded by stick-fighting and kagura groups, accompanied by a mortar drum. The deity is received at the West Main Shrine's traveling shrine, and kagura and stick-fighting are performed before returning to the East Main Shrine.
*East Main Shrine festival (September 22-23): An autumn grand festival to thank for the harvest. The ceremony and procession are similar to the spring festival. In the past, this festival included the "Goshinka festival" where participants competed in throwing tatami mats. This event was paused in 2010 but was revived in 2015 as the "Tatami Throwing Competition."
*Amanoiwato Night Kagura Thirty-three Dance Performance (November 3): A public performance of all 33 dances of the nationally designated Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property "Takachiho Night Kagura." The event takes place from around 9:30 AM to 11 PM at the West Main Shrine.
*Night Kagura Dances (mid-November to mid-December weekends): These dances, held in local homes and community centers, are part of the nationally designated Important Intangible Folk Cultural Property "Takachiho Night Kagura" and are often called "Iwa Kagura" or "Amanoiwato Kagura" in the Iwato area. The number of locations increased to four in 2011. The schedule is announced annually by the Takachiho Town Hall.
== Shrine Buildings ==
*The East Main Shrine's main hall, rebuilt in 1956, is a three-bay, two-bay [[Shinmei-zukuri]] style building.
*The West Main Shrine has a unique structure without a main hall, rebuilt in 1986. A gabled traveling shrine for the auxiliary deities stands to the left of the worship hall. Part of the old Meiji-era shrine building has been relocated and preserved as the current kagura hall.
== Cultural Properties ==
*Stone Lanterns of Amanoiwato Shrine - Town-designated tangible cultural property (artifacts), designated March 14, 1990.
*Excavated Items of Amanoiwato Shrine - Same as above.
*Ancient {{ill|Ginkgo|en|Ginkgo|qid=Q149461|lt=Ginkgo|1=Ginkgo}} Tree - Town-designated natural monument, designated March 19, 1969.
== Grounds ==
=== West Main Shrine ===
*Amanoiwato Worship: The sacred cave, Amanoiwato, worshiped by the West Main Shrine, is hi11en behind the worship hall. Visitors can request to be guided to a viewing spot by a shrine priest, but photography is prohibited. Only a part of the collapsed cave can be seen. {{ill|Matsuura Takeshirō|en|Matsuura Takeshirō|qid=Q11531839|lt=Matsuura Takeshirō|1=Matsuura Takeshirō}} wrote in his travelogue "Saikai Zasshi" (1837)&lt;ref name="r2"/&gt; that the cave entrance was difficult to discern, and two people who tried to descend the cliff to explore the cave never returned.
*{{ill|Shimenawa|en|Shimenawa|qid=Q1887421|lt=Shimenawa|1=Shimenawa}}: After years of longing, the first-ever shimenawa was hung on the sacred Amanoiwato on December 18, 2020&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.the-miyanichi.co.jp/kennai/_49812.html For the first time since the shrine's establishment, a shimenawa was hung on Amanoiwato - Miyazaki Nichinichi Shimbun, viewed December 19, 2020]&lt;/ref&gt;.
*Seven Cedars: A sacred grove of seven cedars planted during the Edo period. The grove is off-limits, but a walkway completed in August 2014 allows close viewing. The trees can also be seen from the shopping district and the Amanoiwato viewing spot.
*location location: The official location (1073-1 Iwato, Takachiho Town) refers to the West Main Shrine's shrine office. The shrine's publications often use "Amanoiwato 1073-1."
=== East Main Shrine ===
*Sacred Spring: A spring behind the main building, drinkable and associated with a small shrine inscribed "Daijingu."
*Sacred Trees: The East Main Shrine's sacred tree is a cedar, while the West Main Shrine has a large {{ill|Magnolia|en|Magnolia|qid=Q157017|lt=Magnolia|1=Magnolia}} tree in front of the shrine. The magnolia's fruit is said to resemble the original [[kagura]] bell, and the tree is the official tree of Takachiho Town. The West Main Shrine sells magnolia saplings.
== Nearby Mythical Sites ==
[[File:Amanoyasukawara.jpg|thumb|Amanoyasukawara]]
[[File:Gyoubogaiwaya-cave-inside.jpg|thumb|Gyobogaiwaya]]
*Amanoyasukawara: A riverbed 500m upstream from the West Main Shrine, believed to be where the gods gathered to discuss the [[Amano-Iwato]] incident. The central cave, known as Gyobogaiwaya, houses Amanoyasukawara Shrine, dedicated to [[Omoikane-no-Kami]] and the [[Yaoyorozu no Kami]]. Visitors stack stones here, believing it brings good fortune.
*Amanoukihashi: Mentioned in myths as a bridge used in the creation of the world. The Takachiho Kyuuki (1691)&lt;ref name="r2"/&gt; describes a natural bridge's shadow seen on clear days. {{ill|Matsuura Takeshirō|en|Matsuura Takeshirō|qid=Q11531839|lt=Matsuura Takeshirō|1=Matsuura Takeshirō}} (1837) also wrote about a mysterious bridge-like structure. This rock formation is visible from the current Iwatobashi Bridge, though no signage marks the spot&lt;ref&gt;'Amanoiwato Scenic map,' Amanoiwato Town Development Association, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'Amanoiwato River "Amanoukihashi" Survey Report,' Amanoiwato Town Development Association, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;.
*Kagurao: A ridge 400m northwest of Amanoiwato Shrine, where [[Ame-no-Uzume]] is said to have performed the first kagura dance. It is marked by a monument and panels.
*[[Ama-no-Kaguyama]]: A mountain southwest of Amanoiwato Shrine, known locally as Ama-no-Kaguyama. It differs from the similarly named mountain near Takachiho's central area (Sandai district), listed on topographic maps.
*Amanoiwato Five Shrines: Five prominent local shrines in Iwato and Kamiiwato areas worshiped as Ujigami. They include Amanoiwato Shrine, Ochidachi Shrine (Iwatotate Inn), Hoko Shrine (Kamiiwato Hinata), Futatsu-dake Shrine (Kamiiwato Hideo), and Ishigami Shrine (Iwatono Kata-no). Except for Amanoiwato Shrine, these shrines do not have resident priests; shrine offices handle talisman distribution, stamp issuance, and ceremonies.
== Transportation ==
*To the West Main Shrine: From Miyazaki Kotsu Takachiho Bus Center, take the town-operated Fureai Bus (Iwato Line or Hideo Line) to Iwato Bus Stop (about 15 minutes). The East Main Shrine is a 5-minute walk through the shopping district from the West Main Shrine. Amanoyasukawara is a 15-minute walk from the West Main Shrine's rear gate (vehicles not allowed on the approach).
*The regular sightseeing bus (Miyazaki Kotsu) that toured major sites like the shrine and Takachiho Gorge is now discontinued.
*Free parking is available at both the East and West Main Shrines. However, due to increased visitors from the spiritual boom, traffic congestion and parking shortages occur during peak periods. To mitigate this, the shrine operates shuttle buses connecting overflow parking lots with the shrine during busy times.
== References ==
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== Further Reading ==
* Amanoiwato Shrine, "Amanoiwato Guide map and History," Shrine Office.
* Amanoiwato Town Development Association, "Amanoiwato River 'Amanoukihashi' Survey Report," 2013.
* Tetsuya Usui, "Traveler's Sandals," [[Kōmyaku Publishing]], 2007, ISBN 978-4-86061-244-3.
* Tsunetsune Kai, "Takachiho Village Exploration," self-published, 1992.
* Takachiho Town (Ed.), "Takachiho Town History," Takachiho Town, 1973.
* Takachiho Town (Ed.), "Takachiho Town History: Local History Edition," Takachiho Town, 2002.
* Takachiho Town (Supervisor), "Shrines of Takachiho," Takachiho Town Tourism Association, 2007.
* [[Ken'ichi Tanikawa]] (Ed.), "Gods of Japan - Shrines and Sacred Sites," Vol. 1 Kyushu, [[Hakusui Publishing]], 2000, ISBN 978-4-560-02501-7 (first edition, 1984, ISBN 4-560-02211-9).
* Itsusaburo Noguchi (Ed.), "Japanese Historical Place names: Miyazaki Prefecture," {{ill|Heibonsha|en|Heibonsha|qid=Q11482108|lt=Heibonsha|1=Heibonsha}}, 1997, ISBN 4-582-49046-8.
* [[Heibu Takami]], "Hyuga Chishi," 1884 (reprint edition, Seicho Publishing, 1976).
== External Links ==
{{commonscat|Amanoiwato-jinja|qq=}}
*[http://amanoiwato-jinja.jp/ Amanoiwato Shrine (Official Site)]
*{{Wayback|url=http://homepage3.nifty.com/muzina-press/iwatomap.pdf |title=Amanoiwato Scenic map |date=20160913212846|qq=}} (PDF file)
*{{Wayback|url=http://homepage3.nifty.com/muzina-press/iwato5map.pdf |title=Amanoiwato Five Shrines Tour map |date=20130927041903|qq=}} (PDF file)
*{{Wayback|url=http://homepage3.nifty.com/muzina-press/ukihashi-rep.pdf |title=Amanoiwato River "Amanoukihashi" Survey Report |date=20160304200723|qq=}} (PDF file)
*[http://www.kumaya.jp/atikoti44.html Amanoiwato Shrine] (Miyazaki Achi-Kochi)

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery mode="packed" style="text-align: center;" caption="" heights="130px" perrow="3"&gt;
File:Amanoiwato-west-shrine (28795304727).jpg|Amanoiwato-jinja nishihongū
File:Amanoiwato-east-shurine.jpg|Amanoiwato-jinja higashihongū
File:Gyoubogaiwaya-cave-outside.jpg|The Takamagahara pantheon is thought to have gathered and discussed how to get Amaterasu out of the Heavenly Rock Cave, [[Amano-Iwato]], at this riverside cave
&lt;/gallery&gt;
==References==
{{Reflist|qq=}}
==External links==
{{Commons cat|Amanoiwato-jinja|Amanoiwato-jinja|qq=}}
*[http://amanoiwato-jinja.jp Ama-no-Iwato Jinja] Official website
*{{Wikivoyage-inline|Takachiho|qq=}}
{{Shinto shrine|qq=}}
{{Sun temples|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|天岩戸神社|version=102022020|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:天岩戸神社]]

[[en:Amanoiwato Shrine]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{Commons category|Amanoiwato-jinja}}
[[fr:Amano-Iwato-jinja]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{Commons category|Amanoiwato-jinja}}
[[fr:Amano-Iwato-jinja]]
{{wikidata link|Q2841102}}
[[Category:Beppyo shrines]]
[[Category:宮崎県の旧村社]]
[[Category:Shinto shrines in Miyazaki Prefecture]]
[[Category:高千穂町の建築物]]
[[Category:高千穂町の歴史]]</text>
      <sha1>73236vp003080vkndy5cmc4l7f7lzxy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
