<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Inshū Shichō Gōki</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3600278</id>
      <parentid>3595172</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-05T02:22:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Sn crud]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23991619004|time triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3600278</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5600" sha1="0am0k73ov6ba6qkda17p9cts3u4mikr" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:隠州視聴合紀]]


'''Inshū Shichō Gakki''' (隠州視聴合紀) is a geographical record of the Inshū (Oki Province) compiled in the 7th year of Kanbun (1667) during the Edo period. It consists of four volumes and one map and is alternatively referred to as '''Inshū Shichō Gakki'''.

As the oldest surviving geographical description of the Oki Islands, its original manuscript is lost, but copies remain scattered. The author is unknown, though the text is regarded as a significant source for understanding the history of the Oki Islands due to its detailed and sophisticated content.

== Compilation ==
According to the preface:
&lt;blockquote&gt;"In the autumn of the 丁未 year, I received orders to travel to Inshū. (Omitted) I surveyed the remote regions, spreading decrees along the roads. During my leisure, I recorded the words of elderly farmers and described the locations of villages, mountains, shrines, temples, and ancient sites." (original in classical Chinese)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The 丁未 year corresponds to Kanbun 7, establishing the compilation date as 1667.

== Author ==
The author's identity is unknown. However, the ''Matsue City History'' (1941) suggests that the text was written during a visit to the Oki Islands by Saitō Kansuke (豊宣/豊仙), a retainer of the Matsue Domain, who served as the Oki magistrate. This attribution has gained traction.&lt;ref&gt;Even Kansuke’s identity is not entirely clear. (''Shimane Prefecture Place Names'')&lt;/ref&gt; Alternatively, the "orders" in the preface might refer to a government decree. Records preserved by the Inoue family of Kamo in Okinoshima Town indicate that three officials (Inaba Seizaemon, Ichihashi Sanshirō, and Tokunaga Tarumo) visited the islands as part of a grand inspection mission. It is speculated that the author might have been one of them or an accompanying scribe.&lt;ref name="shomin"&gt;''Compilation of Commoner Life Materials''&lt;/ref&gt; The text demonstrates considerable scholarly expertise, suggesting a highly educated author.&lt;ref name="shomin" /&gt;

== Content ==
[[File:Eunju2.jpg|thumb|Geographical map of Oki (Dōzen region)]]
[[File:Eunju1.jpg|thumb|Geographical map of Oki (Dōgo region)]]
The preface mentions that the text was based on a field survey conducted in Kanbun 7 (1667), incorporating oral accounts from locals and observations of ancient sites and temples. The text describes geographical features, population, landmarks, historical sites, rituals, and traditions in a travelogue style. While it does not record data such as household counts, rice yields, or products, it offers detailed and accurate records of the islands' conditions. The distances between locations are particularly useful for comparing contemporary geography and place names.

The text comprises a preface, main body, and an appendix (list of shrines and temples, ''Enki'' of Yaki Fire Mountain, ''Monk Bunka's Commentary,'' and ''Poems on Famous Places'').&lt;ref&gt;The arrangement of these sections varies among surviving copies.&lt;/ref&gt; The preface and some historical sections are in classical Chinese, while the main body is in mixed kanji-kana. Comments and personal views are often rendered in classical Chinese. The descriptions of shrines are detailed and critical of Buddhist practices.&lt;ref&gt;The text laments the prominence of Buddhist temples over local shrines, such as in the entry for Tamawakasu Mikoto Shrine.&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, the text maintains a humble tone.&lt;ref name="shomin" /&gt;

== Mention of Takeshima and Ulleungdo ==
The text includes descriptions of Takeshima (today’s Matsushima) and Ulleungdo (then called Takeshima), islands now involved in a territorial dispute:
{{quotation|"Forty ri northwest of Oki lies Matsushima, a rocky island without vegetation, about one ri in circumference. Seventy ri further west lies Takeshima, known as Isotakeshima, a large island covered with bamboo and trees. From Takeshima, one can see Korea, closer than the distance from Inshū to Unshū (Izumo Province)."|source=Inshū Shichō Gakki}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
* Ishizuka Takatoshi, ed. "Inshū Shichō Gakki" (''Compilation of Commoner Life Materials,'' vol. 20), San'ichi Shobō, 1972.
* ''Shimane Prefecture Place Names'' (Japanese Historical Place Name Series), Heibonsha, 1995. ISBN 4-582-49033-6

== External Links ==
* [http://www.pref.shimane.lg.jp/soumu/web-takeshima/takeshima04/takeshima04_01/takeshima04c.data/4-4-5-01.pdf Scanned copy of Inshū Shichō Gakki] (Takeshima Issue Web Research Center)


== See Also ==
* {{ill|Takeshima (Liancourt Rocks)|ja|竹島 (島根県)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Takeshima (Liancourt Rocks)|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 竹島|1=Liancourt Rocks|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q20317}}

{{translated page|ja|隠州視聴合紀|version=97608549|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:隠州視聴合紀]]

&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;&lt;!--Inshū Shichō Gōki--&gt;
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q11659057}}
[[Category:17th-century books]]
[[Category:Liancourt Rocks]]
[[Category:Oki Province]]
[[Category:Regional geography of the Edo period]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]</text>
      <sha1>0am0k73ov6ba6qkda17p9cts3u4mikr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
