<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ise faith</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18310</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3595224</id>
      <parentid>3571550</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:17:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3595224</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="28450" sha1="t30lq5rc2q6dhy32rrghekyy1qfsyap" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:伊勢神道]][[ru:Исэ синто]]


[[File:Geku 003.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Ise Jingū Geku (Toyōke Daijingū)]]
'''Ise Shintō''' (いせしんとう) is the school of Shinto thought that originated at {{ill|Ise Shrine|en|Ise Shrine|qid=Q687168|lt=Ise Jingū|1=Ise Grand Shrine}}. It came to be advocated among the priests of the Outer Shrine (【Toyōke Daijingū】) belonging to the {{ill|Watarai clan|ja|度会氏|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai clan|qq=}}, and is therefore also known as '''Watarai Shintō''' or '''Geku Shintō'''.

== Overview ==
In the latter part of the {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}}, in contrast to earlier indigenous trace theories (【Honchi Suijaku】) such as those propounded by Ryōbu Shintō and Sannō Shintō, the "Anti-Honchi Suijaku" (or “Divine Origin, Buddhist Trace” theory) arose. Under its influence, Ise Shintō was formulated by Outer Shrine priests such as {{ill|Watarai Yukitada|ja|度会行忠|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Yukitada|1=Watarai Yukitada|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q17217919}} and {{ill|Watarai Ieyuki|ja|度会家行|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Ieyuki|1=Watarai Ieyuki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11486121}}.&lt;ref name="yougo1"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=日本史用語研究会 |title=必携日本史用語|year=2009 |edition=四訂版 |publisher=実教出版}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ise Shintō takes as its fundamental scripture the ''{{ill|Shintō Gobusho|ja|神道五部書|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shintō Gobusho|qq=}}'' (which is considered a forgery). In addition, it is regarded as the first Shintō theory to incorporate elements of Confucianism and Taoism.

Its doctrine develops a theory of enshrined deities by identifying the Outer Shrine’s deity, {{ill|Toyōke Daijingū|ja|豊受大神|lt=Toyouke Ōmikami|1=Toyouke-hime|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Toyōke Daijingū|13=User:Immanuelle/Toyouke-hime|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to トヨウケビメ|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q2983724}}, with the primordial deities that appeared prior to the creation of the world – namely, {{ill|Ame-no-Minakanushi|en|Ame-no-Minakanushi|qid=Q2842779|lt=Ame-no-Minakanushi|1=Ame-no-Minakanushi}} and {{ill|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|en|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|qid=Q478504|lt=Kuni-no-Tokotachi|1=Kuni-no-Tokotachi}} – thereby casting them as a universal divine form (an absolute deity) that surpasses the Inner Shrine’s deity, {{ill|Amaterasu|en|Amaterasu|qid=Q455602|lt=Amaterasu Ōmikami|1=Amaterasu}}. In so doing, the theory seeks not only to elevate the status of the Outer Shrine in opposition to the Inner Shrine but also to emphasize the concept of a divine nation by proclaiming "honesty" and "purity" as the two cardinal virtues of Shinto.&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁&lt;/ref&gt;

As indicated above, Ise Shintō constructed its theoretical framework on the basis of Shinto classics and the ancient traditions of Ise Jingū while skillfully incorporating various philosophical elements from Buddhism, Confucianism, Taoism, and the Yin-Yang Five Phases theory.&lt;ref name="yougo2"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=全国歴史教育研究協議会| title=日本史B用語集―A併記 |year=2009 |edition=改訂版 |publisher=山川出版社}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the influence of Chinese thought is strongly felt in its structure, by emphasizing the existence of an absolute deity, Ise Shintō places the kami above the buddhas, thereby adopting an anti-Buddhist, exclusionary stance.&lt;ref name="yougo2"/&gt;

The ideology of Ise Shintō was established on the foundation of the rituals that had long been practiced at Ise Jingū. The “ideology as ritual”—which had been interwoven with Shinto rites since ancient times—became consciously articulated in the medieval period and was systematized by employing the concepts of foreign religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=大隅和雄|title=中世神道論|year=1977|publisher=岩波書店}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ise Shintō is generally divided into an early period (covering the Kamakura and {{ill|Muromachi period|en|Muromachi period|qid=Q334845|lt=Muromachi period|1=Muromachi period}}) and a later period (covering the {{ill|Edo period|en|Edo period|qid=Q184963|lt=Edo period|1=Edo period}}). Notable Shintō scholars associated with its development include its originator, {{ill|Watarai Ieyuki|ja|度会家行|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Ieyuki|1=Watarai Ieyuki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11486121}}, and also {{ill|Deguchi Enka|ja|出口延佳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Deguchi Enka|1=Deguchi Nobuyoshi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q62601522}}, among others.

== Ideology and Doctrines ==

=== Early Ise Shintō ===

==== Theory of Enshrined Deities ====
The thought of Ise Shintō is first characterized by its theory of enshrined deities. It identifies the Outer Shrine’s deity, {{ill|Toyōke Daijingū|ja|豊受大神|lt=Toyouke Ōmikami|1=Toyouke-hime|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Toyōke Daijingū|13=User:Immanuelle/Toyouke-hime|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to トヨウケビメ|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q2983724}}, with the primordial deities that emerged before the creation of the world – namely, {{ill|Ame-no-Minakanushi|en|Ame-no-Minakanushi|qid=Q2842779|lt=Ame-no-Minakanushi|1=Ame-no-Minakanushi}} and {{ill|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|en|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|qid=Q478504|lt=Kuni-no-Tokotachi|1=Kuni-no-Tokotachi}} – thereby casting it as a universal divine principle (an absolute deity) that surpasses the deity of the Inner Shrine, {{ill|Amaterasu|en|Amaterasu|qid=Q455602|lt=Amaterasu Ōmikami|1=Amaterasu}}. Until then, Toyōke Daijingū had been regarded merely as the deity providing sacred food (御饌津神) to Amaterasu Omikami. However, the Watarai clan, basing their argument on the ''Shintō Gobusho'', asserted that the Outer Shrine should be considered equal to or even superior to the Inner Shrine, seeking thereby to elevate its status.&lt;ref name="yougo1"/&gt;

Furthermore, they positioned the Inner Shrine as representing the fire virtue and the Outer Shrine as representing the water virtue, using the Five Phases theory (where “water overcomes fire”) to justify the precedence of the Outer Shrine. They also reinterpreted the genealogy by identifying the goddess associated with Niwa (the mother of Nininomiya) as a granddaughter of Toyōke Daijingū.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=大隅和雄|title=中世神道論|year=1977|publisher=岩波書店}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the standpoint of viewing Toyōke Daijingū as a water deity, the relationship between Toyōke Daijingū and Amaterasu Omikami was reinterpreted in terms of Yin and Yang, sun and moon, suggesting that just as the sun and moon illuminate the universe through a mysterious contract, the two shrines of Ise jointly preside.&lt;ref name="國學院大學日本文化研究所編「伊勢神道」『神道事典』弘文堂(1999)429頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|title=神道事典|year=1999|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt; This equalization of the Inner and Outer Shrines, by comparing them respectively to the womb and adamantine realms, was influenced by the dual-part theory of Shintō.

However, the identification of the Outer Shrine’s deity with {{ill|Ame-no-Minakanushi|en|Ame-no-Minakanushi|qid=Q2842779|lt=Ame-no-Minakanushi|1=Ame-no-Minakanushi}} and {{ill|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|en|Kuni-no-Tokotachi|qid=Q478504|lt=Kuni-no-Tokotachi|1=Kuni-no-Tokotachi}} was not merely an attempt to elevate its status, but was rooted in a quest for the ultimate origin of the universe. It sought to regard these primordial deities as the fundamental source from which all existence emanates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=大隅和雄|title=神道思想集|year=1970|publisher=筑摩書房}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Honesty and Purity ====
Another major aspect of Ise Shintō’s doctrine is its emphasis on the twin virtues of "honesty" and "purity" as the central ethical principles of Shinto. These doctrines stress rigorous ritual practice, purification rites, and exorcism. Although the concept of "purity" had long been a central tenet in Shinto—as evidenced by rituals such as misogi and harai—in Ise Shintō the issue evolved from one of physical defilement to one concerning the purity of the heart, and the means by which one might achieve spiritual purity.&lt;ref name="神社本庁監修『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|title=神社のいろは 続|year=2013|publisher=扶桑社}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one of the texts of the Gobusho, the "Yamato Hime Monogatari" states, "The ritual for enshrining the kami should be based on purity and carried out with sincere faith," thereby emphasizing the necessity for the individual’s inner purity as a prerequisite for divine protection.&lt;ref name="神社本庁監修『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"/&gt;

The spirit of honesty and purity is expressed in the classical phrase from the "Yamato Hime Monogatari": "Let left remain left and right remain right," which signifies following the divine will without artifice. Additionally, the idea of returning to the primordial state, “the original, unaltered state,” is also a key element of this doctrine.&lt;ref name="阪本是丸・石井研士編『プレステップ神道学』弘文堂(2011)55頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=阪本是丸・石井研士編|title=プレステップ神道学|year=2011|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== National Divine Ideology ====
Ise Shintō also emphasizes the exalted status of the imperial lineage, the sanctity of Ise Jingū, and the dignity of the Three Sacred Treasures. It promulgates a "theory of divine kinship" in which all the people of Japan are considered descendants of the gods.&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|title=神社のいろは 続|year=2013|publisher=扶桑社}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the "Yamato Hime Monogatari" it is stated, "The Great Japanese Nation is a divine nation. It secures its safety through the benevolence of the divine and increases its prestige through the veneration of the gods." This nationalistic view replaced earlier syncretic theories of royal and Buddhist law, positing that the kami protect the imperial authority.&lt;ref name="岡田莊司編『日本神道史』吉川弘文館(2010)178頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=岡田莊司編|title=日本神道史|year=2010|publisher=吉川弘文館}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The Relation between Shinto and Buddhism ====
Regarding the relationship between Shinto and Buddhism, Ise Shintō generally seeks to distinguish and contrast the two, asserting the uniqueness of Shintō. At the same time, however, its overall stance against the "Honchi Suijaku" theory was not uncompromising. In the writings of Watarai Ieyuki, for instance, the genealogical relationship between the kami and the buddhas was acknowledged, and Ise Shintō did not mount a full‐scale critique of the Honchi Suijaku theory.&lt;ref name="國學院大學日本文化研究所編「反本地垂迹説」『神道事典』弘文堂(1999)404頁"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|title=神道事典|year=1999|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fully developed theory of "Kami Origin, Buddhist Trace" had to wait until the later emergence of Yoshida Shintō.

==== The Culmination by Watarai Ieyuki ====
The doctrines of early Ise Shintō were eventually synthesized by Watarai Ieyuki. In his work ''Ruiju Shingi Hongen'', he drew upon Song learning, Taoist thought, and Buddhism to systematize Ise Shintō and expound what became known as the "Kimae Theory." As he writes in the introduction, "That which precedes (kimae) is the law, and that which is practiced, purity shall be paramount." Here, he extols the primordial chaotic state as the supreme value and posits that this state is the true source of one’s heart and the essence of the divine. In the ensuing world, maintaining the purity of the primordial state through the practice of purification became essential.&lt;ref name="神道とは何か"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=伊藤聡|title=神道とは何か|year=2012|publisher=中央公論新社|isbn=978-4-12-102158-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; He further distinguishes between phenomena (yūsō) and the transcendence thereof (musō), thereby deepening the theoretical foundation of Ise Shintō.&lt;ref name="神道思想集"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=石田一良|title=神道思想集|year=1970|publisher=筑摩書房}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Later Ise Shintō ===
During the Edo period, Ise Shintō was further developed by figures such as {{ill|Deguchi Enka|ja|出口延佳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Deguchi Enka|1=Deguchi Nobuyoshi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q62601522}}. In his major work ''Yōfukuki'', he argued that although rituals such as offering tamagushi and reciting divine words are central to ceremonial practice, they constitute only one aspect of Shintō. Rather, he maintained that Shintō permeates everyday life and that there is no aspect of daily living that is not imbued with Shintō. In this view, fulfilling one’s duties as a subject (臣神道) and as a ruler (君神道) in one’s proper station is the essence of Shintō.&lt;ref name="神道思想集"&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=石田一良|title=神道思想集|year=1970|publisher=筑摩書房}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Kamakura Period ===
As ancient practices waned and the Ritsuryō system declined into the medieval period, court rituals and state-sponsored ceremonies diminished, and powerful shrines like Ise Jingū gradually lost the economic support previously provided by the central government. The system of Saigu, dispatched by the court to Ise, ended in Genkō 1 (1333) during the reign of {{ill|Princess Shikishi|en|Princess Shikishi|qid=Q735939|lt=Shikishi Naishinnō|1=Princess Shikishi}}, and revenues from the shrine’s land taxes from areas such as Shintachi, Kamibe, and Kamigun also ceased with the collapse of the Ritsuryō system. In this context, a strong sense of crisis arose among the shrine officials, who began to assert a mystical legitimization of their ritual practices. This social background contributed to the systematic formation of Ise Shintō.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=大隅和雄|title=中世神道論|year=1977|publisher=岩波書店}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, during the medieval period a re-interpretation of mythology—known as medieval mythology—emerged at various shrines, enabling them to proclaim the superiority of their own deities relative to those of Ise Jingū. This spurred renewed advocacy for the exalted status of Ise Jingū.&lt;ref name="高橋美由紀|2001"/&gt;

Furthermore, after the victory over the Mongol invasions and the subsequent rise of the divine wind (kamikaze) legend, the authority of Ise Jingū became widely recognized across Japan, and its propagandistic activities by the Ise no Mikami began to spread nationally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=岡田莊司編|title=日本神道史|year=2010|publisher=吉川弘文館}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Against this backdrop, Buddhist monastics increasingly visited Ise, and they began to expound a form of Shintō—known as Ryōbu Shintō—based on esoteric Buddhist logic. In this synthesis, with the Inner Shrine representing the "womb realm" and the Outer Shrine the "adamantine realm," the Outer Shrine priests argued for the equal status of the two, laying the groundwork for Ise Shintō.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=伊藤聡|title=神道とは何か|year=2012|publisher=中央公論新社}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Nanbokuchō and Muromachi Periods ===
During the Nanbokuchō period, Ise Shintō became more systematized. Watarai Ieyuki, who succeeded Watarai Yukitada as the chief priest of Ise, composed works such as ''Ruiju Shingi Hongen'' expounding the "Kimae Theory," thereby systematizing Ise Shintō.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=伊藤聡|title=神道とは何か|year=2012|publisher=中央公論新社}}&lt;/ref&gt; He not only engaged in scholarly activities as a Shintō specialist but also supported the Southern Court during the internal conflicts and promoted Ise Shintō. His associate, {{ill|Kitabatake Chikafusa|en|Kitabatake Chikafusa|qid=Q683792|lt=Kitabatake Chikafusa|1=Kitabatake Chikafusa}}, influenced the writing of works such as the ''Shin kōtōki'', which propagated the national divine ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=石田一良|title=神道思想集|year=1970|publisher=筑摩書房}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, during the Muromachi period, with the rise of Yoshida Shintō founded by {{ill|Yoshida Kanetomo|en|Yoshida Kanetomo|qid=Q723266|lt=Yoshida Kanetomo|1=Yoshida Kanetomo}}, which came to be embraced by the aristocracy, Ise Shintō was gradually overshadowed. Yoshida Kanetomo claimed divine revelations at his shrine, thereby incorporating Ise Jingū into his system, and the Ise priests protested, but ultimately Yoshida Shintō became dominant.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=國學院大學日本文化研究所編|title=神道事典|year=1999|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Edo Period ===
In the Edo period, Deguchi Enka (Watarai Enka) emerged at Ise Jingū and attempted to revive Ise Shintō by writing works such as ''Yōfukuki'' and ''Daijingu Shintō Arumon''. During this period, the Yoshida family also came to dominate the shrine world, with officials being appointed to oversee the national network of shrines, but Enka was a fierce critic of Yoshida Shintō, as seen in his work ''Shintai Yoshida Kanetomo Mōkei-ki''. He also established the Toyomiya Library near the Outer Shrine for the purpose of collecting, preserving, and disseminating texts related to Ise Jingū.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=國學院大學日本文化研究所編|title=神道事典|year=1999|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt; Influential figures such as Deguchi Enka, followed by his son {{ill|Deguchi Enkyō|ja|出口延経|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Deguchi Enkyō|1=Deguchi Nobutsune|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q108780926}}, as well as Kawabe Seichō, Matsuki Tomohiko, and Kawasaki Nobutada, actively participated in the restoration of shrine rituals and the revival of subsidiary shrines.

In the mid-Edo period, the rise of the kokugaku movement led to a more empirical study of Shintō and its classics. One kokugaku scholar, {{ill|Yoshimi Yukikazu|ja|吉見幸和|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yoshimi Yukikazu|1=Yoshimi Yoshikazu|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q63131320}}, based on meticulous textual analysis, authored the ''Gobusho Setsuben'', demonstrating that although the Shintō Gobusho claim an ancient origin, in reality they were compiled in the medieval period, thereby criticizing Ise Shintō.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|和書|author=國學院大學日本文化研究所編|title=神道事典|year=1999|publisher=弘文堂}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many kokugaku scholars who opposed the syncretism of Confucianism and Buddhism with Shintō attacked Ise Shintō, leading to its decline. By the end of the Edo period, the revival of Shintō initiated by {{ill|Hirata Atsutane|en|Hirata Atsutane|qid=Q2572749|lt=Hirata Atsutane|1=Hirata Atsutane}} through the restoration Shintō movement overwhelmed the Ise school.

In 1871 (Meiji 4), following the proclamation by the Daijōkan, the hereditary system for Shinto priests was abolished, and the Watarai clan, who had long held the position of Outer Shrine priest, were dismissed. This brought an end to Ise Shintō as a coherent power base.

== Shintō Gobusho ==
[[File:倭姫命世記.jpg|thumb|200px|One of the scriptures of Ise Shintō, "Yamato Hime Monogatari" (a copy written in 1769/Meiwa 8)]]
; (1) '''Ame no Terasu Ise Nisho Kōtai Jingū Gochinza Shidai-ki'''
: Also known simply as "Shidaiki."&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed to have been compiled before Ennin 3 (1295) and records the history of the enshrinement and installation of the deities at the Ise shrines.
; (2) '''Ise Nisho Kōtai Jingū Gochinza Denki'''
: Also known simply as "Denki."&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁&lt;/ref&gt; It is thought to have been compiled before Kōan 8 (1285) and recounts the installation process of the deities at Ise Jingū.
; (3) '''Toyouke Kōtai Shin Mikami Gochinza Honki'''
: Also known as "Honki."&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁&lt;/ref&gt; Compiled around the same time as the Denki, this text details the installation history of the Outer Shrine, and discusses the relationship between the Inner and Outer Shrines.
; (4) '''Zō Ise Nisho Ta Jingū Hōkihonki'''
: Also known as "Hōkihonki."&lt;ref name="神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁"&gt;神社本庁編『神社のいろは 続』扶桑社(2013)101頁&lt;/ref&gt; It was compiled in the early Kamakura period and is considered the earliest of the Gobusho. In contrast to the previous three, which focus on historical narrative, this work emphasizes doctrinal teachings. It is notable for its mystical interpretations of architectural forms such as the roof and ridge.
; (5) '''Yamato Hime Monogatari'''
: (やまとひめのみことせいき／やまとひめせいき)&lt;ref name="genryu"&gt;[http://www.nippon-bunmei.jp/topics/turedure/%E3%80%9031%E3%80%91-%E5%85%83%E4%BC%8A%E5%8B%A2%E4%BC%9D%E6%89%BF%E3%81%AE%E6%BA%90%E6%B5%81%EF%BC%88%E4%B8%80%EF%BC%89%E3%80%80%EF%BC%8D%E4%BC%8A%E5%8B%A2%E7%A5%9E%E9%81%93%E3%81%A8%E7%A5%9E.html 【31】 元伊勢伝承の源流（一） －伊勢神道と神道五部書－]&lt;/ref&gt; Dating from the early to mid-Kamakura period, this work is the second to be completed after the Hōkihonki. According to the Nihon Shoki, Yamato Hime was an imperial princess (daughter of the 11th Suinin Tennō) who traveled the country as the bearer of Amaterasu’s sacred scepter, and enshrined Ise Jingū. This scripture, one of the Gobusho, records numerous traces of her journey centered in the Watarai (Watarai) district and serves as a clear doctrinal statement alongside the Hōkihonki. Although it was compiled in the medieval period, it is thought to have been based on ancient Ise traditions, as later research by the kokugaku scholar {{ill|Mikofusa Kiyonao|ja|御巫清直|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mikofusa Kiyonao|1=Mikannagi Kiyonao|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q6537624}} has shown.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sankei.com/article/20170806-YSM4NY42TJPUJP7EXN67PYVOZY/ “Revisiting the Traditional Culture of Ise Jingū” – A guided tour tracing the legend of Yamato Hime]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ise Shintō Proponents ==
* {{ill|Watarai Yukitada|ja|度会行忠|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Yukitada|1=Watarai Yukitada|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q17217919}}
* {{ill|Watarai Ieyuki|ja|度会家行|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Ieyuki|1=Watarai Ieyuki|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11486121}}
* {{ill|Watarai Tsuneyoshi|ja|度会常昌|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Tsuneyoshi|1=Watarai Tsuneyoshi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q62601523}}
* {{ill|Deguchi Enka|ja|出口延佳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Deguchi Enka|1=Deguchi Nobuyoshi|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q62601522}}
* {{ill|Yomura Hiromasa|ja|与村弘正|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yomura Hiromasa|1=Yomura Hiromasa|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q22120843}}
* {{ill|Ryūki Chika|ja|龍煕近|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ryūki Chika|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Kawabe Seichō|ja|河辺精長|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kawabe Seichō|1=Kiyonaga Kawabe|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q92924151}}
* {{ill|Nakanishi Nobukei|ja|中西信慶|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nakanishi Nobukei|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Nakanishi Naokata|ja|中西直方|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nakanishi Naokata|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Deguchi Enkyō|ja|出口延経|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Deguchi Enkyō|1=Deguchi Nobutsune|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q108780926}}
* {{ill|Oda Naratomi|ja|小田成胤|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Oda Naratomi|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Kawasaki Nobutada|ja|河崎延貞|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kawasaki Nobutada|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Kisoh Kiyozai|ja|喜早清在|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kisoh Kiyozai|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Matsuki Tomohiko|ja|松木智彦|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Matsuki Tomohiko|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}
* {{ill|Watarai Tsuneyoshi (Hisamasa)|ja|度会常彰|lt=Hisamasa|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Watarai Tsuneyoshi (Hisamasa)|1=Watarai Tsuneakira|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q62601524}}
* {{ill|Tanaka Yoriyoshi|ja|田中頼庸|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Tanaka Yoriyoshi|1=Yoritsune Tanaka|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q95162647}}

== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist|25em}}

== References ==
* {{Cite book|和書|author=伊藤聡|title=神道とは何か|year=2012|publisher=中央公論新社|series=中公新書|isbn=978-4-12-102158-8|ref={{harvid|『神道とは何か』}}}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=日本史用語研究会|title=必携日本史用語|year=2009|edition=四訂版|publisher=実教出版|isbn=978-4-407-31659-9}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=全国歴史教育研究協議会|title=日本史B用語集―A併記|year=2009|edition=改訂版|publisher=山川出版社|isbn=978-4-634-01302-5}}
* {{Cite book|和書|title=神道行法の本―日本の霊統を貫く神祇奉祭の秘事|year=2005|publisher=学研|series=BooksEsoterica|isbn=4-05-603775-2}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=末木文美士|title=中世の神と仏|year=2003|publisher=山川出版社|series=日本史リブレット|NCID=BA6215284X|ISBN=9784634543201|id={{全国書誌番号|20413066}}|url=https://ndlsearch.ndl.go.jp/books/R100000002-I000004129038|ref={{harvid|『中世の神と仏』}}}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=高橋美由紀|title=伊勢神道の成立と展開|year=1994|publisher=ぺりかん社|NCID=BN11476256|ISBN=4470200409|id={{全国書誌番号|95009511}}|url=https://ndlsearch.ndl.go.jp/books/R100000002-I000002363890|ref={{harvid|『伊勢神道の成立と展開』}}}}
** {{Cite thesis|和書|author=高橋美由紀|url=https://doi.org/10.11501/3189109|title=伊勢神道の成立と展開|volume=東北大学|series=博士 （文学） 乙第8028号|year=2001|doi=10.11501/3189109|id={{naid|500000210878}}|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=松本丘|title=近世の神都と学問・思想|year=2018|publisher=伊勢神宮崇敬会叢書|series=ブックレット}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=大隅和雄|title=中世神道論|series=日本思想大系17|year=1977|publisher=岩波書店|NCID=BN00402677|ISBN=4000700197|id={{全国書誌番号|JP77010053}}|url=https://iss.ndl.go.jp/books/R100000074-I000703642-00|ref={{harvid|『中世神道論』}}}}
* {{Cite book|和書|author=石田一良|title=神道思想集|series=日本の思想|year=1970|publisher=筑摩書房|NCID=BN01912078|id={{全国書誌番号|74001741}}|doi=10.11501/2971570|ref={{harvid|『神道思想集』}}}}

== Related Articles ==
* {{ill|Yamazaki Ansai|en|Yamazaki Ansai|qid=Q6565636|lt=Yamazaki Ansai|1=Yamazaki Ansai}}
* {{ill|Yoshida Shintō|en|Yoshida Shintō|qid=Q1760351|lt=Yoshida Shintō|1=Yoshida Shintō}}
* {{ill|Kokugaku|en|Kokugaku|qid=Q855159|lt=Kokugaku|1=Kokugaku}}

{{神道 横}}

{{Medieval Shinto}}
{{shinto-stub}}

{{translated page|ja|伊勢神道|version=104262450|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:伊勢神道]]

[[ru:%D0%98%D1%81%D1%8D %D1%81%D0%B8%D0%BD%D1%82%D0%BE]]

&lt;!--Ise faith--&gt;&lt;!--Ise faith--&gt;&lt;!-- In the dispute over the enshrinement of Amaterasu Omikami, he prevailed, placing her divine status at the highest level. --&gt;
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[ru:Исэ синто]]
{{wikidata link|Q4205212}}
[[Category:Shinto schools of thought]]
[[Category:Watarai Clan]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]</text>
      <sha1>t30lq5rc2q6dhy32rrghekyy1qfsyap</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
