<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Iwanaga-hime</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18348</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3595421</id>
      <parentid>3572100</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:18:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3595421</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="28864" sha1="5kdf1jy53sbtlz1a2avfk6yrei8tdjj" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[de:Iwanaga-hime]][[en:Iwanaga-hime]][[it:Iwanaga-hime]][[ja:イワナガヒメ]][[ko:이와나가히메]][[mni:ꯏꯋꯅꯒ-ꯍꯤꯃꯦ]][[sv:Iwanaga-hime]][[zh:石長比賣]]

{{Short description|Kami}}
{{Infobox deity|
type=Shinto
|children=
|siblings={{ill|Konohanasakuya-hime|en|Konohanasakuya-hime|simple|User:Immanuelle/Konohanasakuya-hime|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Konohanasakuya-hime|qq=}}&lt;br&gt;
[[Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi]]&lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Konohanachiru-hime|en|Konohanachiru-hime|qid=Q48745675|lt=Konohanachiru-hime|1=Konohanachiru-hime}}&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=181|title=Encyclopedia of Shinto - Home : Kami in Classic Texts : Yashimajinumi|website=eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp}}&lt;/ref&gt;|father=[[Ōyamatsumi]]
|cult_centre=
{{ill|Kumomi Sengen Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|qq=}}&lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)|en|Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)|qid=Q11434371|lt=Ōmuroyama Sengen Shrine|1=Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)}}&lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Kifune Shrine|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|qq=}},&lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Mishima Taisha|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mishima Taisha|qq=}} &lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Sengen shrine|lt=Sengen shrine|lt=Asama Shrine|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Asama Shrine|qq=}} &lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Ōyamazumi Shrine|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ōyamazumi Shrine|qq=}}&lt;br&gt;
{{ill|Daishōgun Shrine|ja|大将軍神社 (京都市北区)|1=Daishōgun Shrine (Kita-ku, Kyoto)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Daishōgun Shrine|13=User:Immanuelle/Daishōgun Shrine (Kita-ku, Kyoto)|qq=}}
|gender={{ill|female|qid=Q6581072|1=Female (gender)}}
|parents={{ill|Ōyamatsumi|qid=Q386563|1=Ōyamatsumi}}
}}

'''Iwanaga-hime''' (岩長姫, "Long Rock Princess"&lt;ref name="King-2000"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2yWu3FbfV1QC&amp;newbks=0&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;pg=PA77&amp;dq=Iwanagahime&amp;hl=en|title=Body Politics and the Fictional Double|last=King|first=Debra Walker|date=2000-10-22|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0-253-10832-6|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is a [[kami]] in [[Japanese mythology]]. She is also the daughter of [[Ōyamatsumi]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Encyclopedia of Shinto - Home : Kami in Classic Texts : Iwanagahime|url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=78|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201125123643/http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=78|archive-date=2020-11-25|access-date=2021-08-21|website=eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Encyclopedia of Shinto詳細|url=https://d-museum.kokugakuin.ac.jp/eos/detail/?id=9389|archive-url=|access-date=2021-09-08|website=國學院大學デジタルミュージアム|language=ja}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="King-2000" /&gt; and sister to {{ill|Konohanasakuya-hime|en|Konohanasakuya-hime|simple|User:Immanuelle/Konohanasakuya-hime|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Konohanasakuya-hime|qq=}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Coulter|first1=Charles Russell|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sEIngqiKOugC&amp;dq=Sakuya-hime&amp;pg=PA347|title=Encyclopedia of Ancient Deities|last2=Turner|first2=Patricia|date=2013-07-04|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-135-96390-3|pages=255|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="King-2000" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7yeo3tU8A9EC&amp;newbks=0&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq=Iwanagahime&amp;hl=en|title=Japanese Mythology and the Primeval World: A Comparative Symbolic Approach|last=Metevelis|first=Peter|date=2009-05|publisher=iUniverse|isbn=978-0-595-49711-9|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is said to be enshrined at {{ill|Kifune Shrine|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|qq=}}.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Cali|first1=Joseph|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J1gEEAAAQBAJ&amp;dq=Iwanagahime&amp;pg=PA123|title=Shinto Shrines: A Guide to the Sacred Sites of Japan's Ancient Religion|last2=Dougill|first2=John|date=2012-11-30|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|isbn=978-0-8248-3775-4|pages=123|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her worship is closely tied to the ancient practice of stone veneration, and she is honored at the {{ill|Kumomi Sengen Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|qq=}} in the {{ill|Izu Peninsula|en|Izu Peninsula|qid=Q822822|lt=Izu Peninsula|1=Izu Peninsula}}.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; She is also linked to matchmaking.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|title=パワースポット|url=https://omuroyama.com/event/powerspot/|access-date=2024-05-17|website=大室山登山リフトオフィシャルサイト}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mythology ==

Ōyamatsumi offered his two daughters, Konohanasakuya hime and Iwanaga hime to Ninigi, for marriage. However Ninigi declined Iwanaga hime due to her lack of appeal. Conveyed this decision to her father [[Ōyamatsumi]].&lt;ref name="Hardacre-2016"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.amazon.com/Shinto-History-Helen-Hardacre/dp/0190621710|title=Shinto: A History|last=Hardacre|first=Helen|date=2016-12-01|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-062171-1|edition=Illustrated edition|location=New York|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|60}}&lt;ref name="en.wikisource.org"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Kojiki (Horne) - Wikisource, the free online library|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Kojiki_(Horne)|access-date=2024-05-17|website=en.wikisource.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|chapter 40}}&lt;ref name="Ponsonby-Fane-2016a" /&gt;

Konohanasakuyahime, also known as the "Princess of Blooming Tree Blossoms " met Ninigi no Mikoto, the Heavenly Grandchild, when he descended to Earth. Enchanted by her beauty Ninigi asked about her background. Discovered that she was the daughter of Oyamatsumi no Kami, a mountain deity. Konohanasakuyahime had a sister named Iwanagahime. Ninigi expressed his wish to wed Konohanasakuyahime and after receiving approval, from Oyamatsumi no Kami both sisters were sent to him. However Ninigi chose to marry Konohanasakuyahime. Turned down Iwanagahime due, to her less appealing appearance..&lt;ref name="Ponsonby-Fane-2016b"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.amazon.ca/Studies-Shinto-Shrines-R-Ponsonby-Fane/dp/1138983225|title=Studies In Shinto &amp; Shrines: Asama Shrine|last=Ponsonby-Fane|first=R. A. B.|date=2016-05-11|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-138-98322-9|edition=1st edition|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As per the Kojiki account Ōyamatsumi presented both daughters to Ninigi no Mikoto with the intention of ensuring immortality to emperors like rocks. Yet because Iwanaga hime was turned down emperors were fated to lead mortal lives instead..&lt;ref name="Hardacre-2016" /&gt;{{rp|60}}&lt;ref name="en.wikisource.org" /&gt;{{rp|chapter 40}}&lt;ref name="Ponsonby-Fane-2016a" /&gt;

Oyamatsumi-no-Kami sent a message expressing disappointment, explaining that Iwanagahime was meant to grant eternal life, like the enduring rocks, while Konohanasakuyahime would ensure prosperity, like the blooming flowers. By rejecting Iwanagahime, Ninigi and his descendants were destined to have lives as fleeting as blossoms.&lt;ref name="Ponsonby-Fane-2016b" /&gt;

According to a variation in the Nihongi narrative Iwanaga hime felt embittered by Ninigis rejection. Subsequently placed a curse upon him his lineage and all humanity—sentencing them to existences resembling tree blossoms. This tale serves as an origin story for the brevity of life..&lt;ref name="Hardacre-2016" /&gt;{{rp|60}}&lt;ref name="en.wikisource.org" /&gt;{{rp|chapter 40}}

In a retelling in the Nihongi version Ninigi encountered both sisters engaged in weaving, within a palace set upon ocean waves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-UNEhdX6ePMC&amp;newbks=0&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=Iwanagahime&amp;hl=en|title=Weaving and Binding: Immigrant Gods and Female Immortals in Ancient Japan|last=Como|first=Michael|date=2009-09-02|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|isbn=978-0-8248-2957-5|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This story might have its roots in folklore as similar motifs are often found in myths drawing inspiration from tales, like Ninigi and the Tenson Korin.

=== Family Background ===
Iwanaga-hime is the daughter of Ōyamatsumi, the god of mountains, and the elder sister of Konohanasakuya-hime. The mythological narratives depict Iwanaga-hime as embodying the enduring nature of stone, symbolizing permanence and immortality. In contrast, her sister Konohanasakuya-hime represents the ephemeral beauty of flowers and the transient nature of life.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Iwanaga hime and her sister, Konohanasakuya hime are daughters of Ōyamatsumi, a mountain deity in mythology. Legend has it that Ōyamatsumi sends both sisters to marry Ninigi no Mikoto, the grandson of the sun goddess Amaterasu Ōmikami (or Susanoo in some versions).

=== The Tale of Ninigi ===
The most famous myth involving Iwanaga-hime is her rejection by the god Ninigi, the grandson of the sun goddess Amaterasu. When Ninigi descended from the heavens to pacify and cultivate the earth, Ōyamatsumi offered both his daughters in marriage. However, Ninigi chose only the younger sister, Konohanasakuya-hime, for her beauty, rejecting Iwanaga-hime. This spurning led Iwanaga-hime to curse humanity with mortality, decreeing that humans would have fleeting lives like her sister's blossoms instead of enduring like stones.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== The Tale of Rejection; ===
Ninigi no Mikoto, captivated by Konohana no Sakuyahimes beauty accepts her as his bride. Spends a night with her. However he rejects Iwanaga hime due to her perceived unattractiveness sending her untouched. Upon Iwanaga himes return Ōyamatsumi reveals his intention behind sending both daughters; he envisioned lives to be as enduring as rocks symbolized by Iwanaga hime and as beautiful as blooming flowers represented by Sakuyahime. By rejecting Iwanaga hime Ninigi inadvertently condemned humans to brief and transient lives resembling the beauty of flowers, than the lasting strength of rocks.

Iwanaga hime felt deeply saddened by the rejection. Retreated to Kumomi causing a rift, between the close sisters. 

== Folklore and analysis ==
This section will focus on the legends around {{ill|Kumomi Sengen Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|qq=}}

In some versions of the myth it is believed that Iwanaga hime herself foretold that humanity would suffer from lifespans as a consequence of Ninigi no Mikoto turning away from her. This element of the story draws parallels to {{ill|Izanami|en|Izanami|qid=Q682306|lt=Izanami|1=Izanami}}, who vowed to take a thousand lives each day symbolizing death. Both Iwanaga hime and Izanami are portrayed as figures whose actions have repercussions for mankind.&lt;ref name="King-2000" /&gt;

Legend has it that Iwanaga hime was considered unattractive but marrying her promised longevity akin to a rock while her beautiful sister Konohanasakuya hime offered life like a flower. Ninigi no Mikoto, descendant of the sun goddess fell in love with Konohanasakuya hime and spurned Iwanaga hime returning her to Ōyamatsumi no Mikoto. According to {{ill|Motoori Norinaga|en|Motoori Norinaga|qid=Q384647|lt=Motoori Norinagas|1=Motoori Norinaga}} "{{ill|Kojiki-den|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kojiki-den|qq=}}" the envious Iwanaga hime escaped to Kumomi after feeling jealousy towards her sister ({{ill|Mount Fuji|en|Mount Fuji|qid=Q39231|lt=Mount Fuji|1=Mount Fuji}}) where she was revered as a rocky mountain. Concerned, for her siblings well being the beautiful sister extended herself in search of Iwanaga hime growing taller and more exquisite in appearance.

Local stories around {{ill|Kumomi Sengen Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|qq=}} suggest that when Mount Eboshi is clear Mount Fuji is covered in clouds and vice versa. It is believed that speaking highly of Mount Fuji from Mount Eboshi can lead to being cast into the sea. As a result locals refrained from climbing Mount Fuji and mentioning the name "Fuji" was prohibited for a time.

Another tale revolves around Zenroku, a woodcutter, from Iwashina Village. Despite being a man and a poor woodcutter Zenroku undertook a 21 day period of prayer. Fasting at the shrine acquiring spiritual strength. He eventually became a craftsman renowned across Amagi and Edo. A sizable rock thought to be where Zenroku tested his saw still stands on the mountain.

Historical records from 1866 mention that during the festival day hammerhead sharks measuring over 3 meters long and large sea turtles emerge in the sea waters, around Mount Eboshi circling it throughout the day.

== Interpretation and Analysis ==

=== Connection, to the Ocean ===
The connection between Iwanaga hime and the sea is somewhat ambiguous in tales considering her shrines location near the coast. Unlike sea gods revered on headlands Iwanaga himes main symbolism revolves around mountains and rocks. This contrast might mirror themes of division and unity land versus sea.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Sibling Relationships ===
The legends surrounding Iwanaga hime and her sister Konohanasakuya hime showcase patterns found in folklore, where older siblings often defer to younger ones. This trend can be seen in the stories of their offspring like Umi no sachi hiko and Yama no sachi hiko embodying the contrast between the ocean and land. The younger sibling usually emerges victorious symbolizing the triumph of life over everlasting existence.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Wider Mythological Concepts ===
Her myth takes the form of similar austronesian {{ill|Banana-type myth|ja|バナナ型神話|User:Immanuelle/draft|lt=Banana-type myths|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Banana-type myth|qq=}} about the origin of death, which is common among Austronesian cultures.&lt;ref name="Hardacre-2016" /&gt;{{rp|60}}

== Shrines ==
These shrines worship her primarily
*{{ill|Kumomi Sengen Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Sengen Shrine|qq=}}
*{{ill|Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)|en|Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)|qid=Q11434371|lt=Ōmuroyama Sengen Shrine|1=Mount Ōmuro (Shizuoka)}} (go take photos none exist)
*{{ill|Izu Shrine|ja|伊豆神社|simple|User:Immanuelle/Izu Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Izu Shrine|qq=}}
*{{ill|Sazareishi Shrine|ja|細石神社|1=Sazareishi Shrine|simple|User:Immanuelle/Sazareishi Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Sazareishi Shrine|qq=}}

=== Kumomi Sengen Shrine ===
The Kumomi Sengen Shrine, in the village of Kumomi on the coast of the Izu Peninsula honors Iwanaga hime. This ancient shrine stands atop a mountain rising 163 meters above sea level. Legend holds that the goddess resides within a rock at the mountains peak.

Key structures at Kumomi Sengen Shrine include;

* Worship Hall; Located at the mountains base this hall caters to those unwilling to climb. It houses items. Lacks an altar.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
* Onna Miya; Positioned up the slope this temple historically marked womens limit of access. Inside is a shrine dedicated to {{ill|Amitābha|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Amitabha|qq=}}, a figure.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
* Chojusha; Situated at the summit near the rock this sanctuary features an altar only to ordained individuals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Worship at this shrine is self guided, with visitors engaging in rituals like ringing a bell to signal the goddess offering coins and offering prayers.The sacred spaces of Onna Miya and Chojusha are usually closed except, for ceremonies.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Festivals and Traditions ===
When it comes to festivals and traditions Kumomi Sengen Shrine mainly celebrates the New Year and a local mid July festival that lasts for three days. These events involve Shinto rituals of purification and offerings often accompanied by dances to honor the deity. In the past these festivals also featured performances. They have become less frequent due to changes in the economy and population.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

=== Symbolism of the Cherry Trees ===
Cherry trees, which symbolize Iwanaga himes sister grow at the foot of the mountain as a representation of a local legend about reconciliation between the sisters. Despite Iwanaga himes anger leading her to retreat to the mountain the presence of these trees indicates a resolution, with the priest suggesting that the goddess is now in harmony, with her sister.

=== Ōmuroyama Sengen Shrine ===
Ōmuroyama Sengen Shrine is dedicated to Iwanaga hime, where she is worshipped through a [[Kannabi]] that represents her residing directly within the mountain as her [[shintai]].&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Omuroyama itself was once believed to be divine. Now houses Sengen Shrine on its mid slope near the crater.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

The shrine houses the deity Iwanaga hime no mikoto, known for her connection, to safe childbirth and matchmaking. She is the sister of Konohanasakuya hime the goddess revered at the peak of Mount Fuji.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Located on the summit along a mountain path are five life sized Wisdom Buddhas (Gochi Nyorai). 300 years ago a nine year old girl, daughter of Asakura Seibee, an official from Iwamura in Sagami Province (now Ashigarakami District, Kanagawa Prefecture) had a safe delivery thanks to prayers offered at Ōmuroyama Sengen Shrine. In gratitude for this blessing these Buddhas were enshrined.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

In times local fishermen sought protection and safety from sea disasters, at Omuroyama facing Oshima Island. This led to the dedication of eight Jizo statues known as Yatsugatake Jizo at the summit of Omuroyama.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

At Omuroyama stands the haiku monument honoring Takaha Shugyo, who admired and cherished the Izu region alongside his master Akimoto Fujio.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

The haiku says, "Izu is where the sun gently falls, blooming with mandarin flowers " beautifully capturing the beauty of Izus landscape in the summer.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

=== Gogo Island ===
A shrine dedicated to her can be found on {{ill|Gogo Island|ja|興居島|ceb|Gogo-shima|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Gogo Island|qq=}}.
*

== Lesser Shrines ==
These shrines worship her but are parts of larger shrines

=== Mishima Taisha ===
Iwanaga-hime is worshipped at {{ill|Mishima Taisha|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mishima Taisha|qq=}}, located in {{ill|Mishima, Shizuoka|en|Mishima, Shizuoka|qid=Q653478|lt=Mishima|1=Mishima, Shizuoka}}, {{ill|Shizuoka Prefecture|en|Shizuoka Prefecture|qid=Q131320|lt=Shizuoka Prefecture|1=Shizuoka Prefecture}}. It is traditionally believed to be connected to [[Ōyamatsumi|Ōyamatsumi no Mikoto]], the deity of mountains. However, the deity worshipped at Mishima Shrine has been a topic of historical and scholarly debate.&lt;ref name="Ponsonby-Fane-2016a"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.amazon.ca/Studies-Shinto-Shrines-R-Ponsonby-Fane/dp/1138983225|title=Studies In Shinto &amp; Shrines: Mishima Taisha|last=Ponsonby-Fane|first=R. A. B.|date=2016-05-11|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-138-98322-9|edition=1st edition|language=English|qq=draft}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anaba Shrine at Oyamatsumi Shrine ===
[[File:Ōyamazumi-jinja_keigaisessha_(Anaba-jinja).JPG|thumb|Anaba Shrine]]
Anaba Shrine is a sessha at {{ill|Ōyamazumi Shrine|en|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ōyamazumi Shrine|qq=}} dedicated to Iwanaga-hime and people go there for help with longevity and female fertility. Offerings of female undergarmets are often given.

== Kifune Shrine ==
{{Main|User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|qq=draft}}
At {{ill|Kifune Shrine|en|Kifune Shrine|simple|User:Immanuelle/Kifune_Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kifune Shrine|qq=}} there is a shrine known as the middle shrine dedicated to Iwanaga hime.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

This shrine, called Yuinoyashiro is situated between the shrine (Hongū) and the inner shrine (Okumiya) located 300 meters upstream, from the shrine. It is often referred to as Chūgū or intermediate shrine due, to its position.

The deity enshrined here is Iwanaga hime, revered as the goddess of matchmaking. There's a legend why Iwanaga hime became associated with matchmaking. When Ninigi no Mikoto, a grandchild sought to marry Konohanasakuya hime, her father Ōyamatsumi no Mikoto proposed both his daughters – Iwanaga hime and Konohanasakuya hime. However Ninigi no Mikoto chose to marry Konohanasakuya hime. Feeling saddened by this outcome Iwanaga hime declared, "I shall bless relationships as the deity of matchmaking " and made this place her home.

In the past people used to tie together grass leaves found within the shrine grounds in hopes of fostering relationships.

To safeguard the plants it has become a practice to inscribe wishes on "Musubi bumi" (binding letters) provided at the shrine and fasten them at a specified location.

=== Main Shrine (Hongū) ===

* Deity Enshrined; Iwanaga hime no Mikoto
* Place of Worship (Haiden)
* Celestial Rock Ship (Amano Iwabune); A natural rock resembling a ship consecrated in 1996 as the vessel of "Iwanaga hime no Mikoto."
* Waka Monument of {{ill|Izumi Shikibu|en|Izumi Shikibu|qid=Q239898|lt=Izumi Shikibu|1=Izumi Shikibu}}
{{commons|Yuinoyashiro, Kifune-jinja}}

==== Gallery ====
&lt;gallery mode="packed"&gt;
File:Kifune-jinja_Shintô_Shrine_-_Matsuo_Iwao_Haiku_inscription.jpg|alt=|Matsuo Iwao Haiku inscription at Yuinoyashiro, Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_Shintô_Shrine_-_Sacred_tree_"Cercidiphyllum_japonicum".jpg|alt=|Sacred tree "Cercidiphyllum japonicum" at Yuinoyashiro, Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_Shintô_Shrine_-_Yui-no-yashiro.jpg|alt=|Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja, a shrine dedicated to matchmaking and love
File:Kifune-jinja_yuinoyashiro-ema.jpeg|alt=|Ema (wooden prayer plaques) at Yui-no-yashiro, Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_yuinoyashiro.jpeg|alt=|Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja, a shrine dedicated to matchmaking and love
File:Kifune-jinja_Yuinoyashiro1.jpg|alt=|Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja, a shrine dedicated to matchmaking and love
File:Kifune-jinja_yuinoyashiro2.jpeg|alt=|Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja, a shrine dedicated to matchmaking and love
File:Kifune-jinja_Yuinoyashiro2.jpg|alt=|Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja, a shrine dedicated to matchmaking and love
File:貴船神社_-_panoramio_-_くろふね_(8).jpg|alt=|View of Yui-no-yashiro at Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_amenoiwafune.jpeg|alt=|Ame-no-iwafune, sacred rock at Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_Shintô_Shrine_-_Rock_"Ame-no-iwafune".jpg|alt=|Ame-no-iwafune, sacred rock at Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_Yuinoyashiro_amenoiwafune.jpg|alt=|Ame-no-iwafune, sacred rock at Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja-Greenonstone.jpg|alt=|Ame-no-iwafune, sacred rock at Kifune-jinja
File:Kibune7256.jpg|alt=|Izumi-Shikibu-kahi at Kifune-jinja, a monument inscribed with poetry by Izumi Shikibu
File:Kifune-jinja_Izumi-Shikibu-kahi.jpeg|alt=|Izumi-Shikibu-kahi at Kifune-jinja, a monument inscribed with poetry by Izumi Shikibu
File:Kifune-jinja_Shintô_Shrine_-_Izumi_Shikibu_Tanka_inscription.jpg|alt=|Izumi Shikibu Tanka inscription at Kifune-jinja
File:Kifune-jinja_Yuinoyashiro_Izumishikibu_kahi.jpg|alt=|Izumi-Shikibu-kahi at Kifune-jinja, a monument inscribed with poetry by Izumi Shikibu
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== List of Shrines for Iwanaga-hime ==

* {{ill|Yasaka Shrine|en|Yasaka Shrine|qid=Q692714|lt=Yasaka Shrine|1=Yasaka Shrine}}
* {{ill|Musashi-Mitake Shrine|ja|武蔵御嶽神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Musashi Mitake Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Anumi Shrine|ja|阿沼美神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Anumi Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Ōyamazumi Shrine|en|Ōyamazumi Shrine|qid=Q703904|lt=Ōyamazumi Shrine|1=Ōyamazumi Shrine}}
* {{ill|Hijiri Shrine|ja|聖神社 (和泉市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hijiri Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kifune Shrine|en|Kifune Shrine|qid=Q276779|lt=Kifune Shrine|1=Kifune Shrine}}
* {{ill|Chiba Shrine|en|Chiba Shrine|qid=Q11406700|lt=Chiba Shrine|1=Chiba Shrine}}
* {{ill|Ishigami Shrine (Ome)|ja|石神社 (青梅市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ishigami Shrine (Ome)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Wadanoki Shrine|ja|和田乃神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Wadanoki Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Aoshima Shrine|en|Aoshima Shrine|qid=Q2857985|lt=Aoshima Shrine|1=Aoshima Shrine}}
* {{ill|Inage Asama Shrine|ja|稲毛浅間神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Inage Asama Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Yohara Shrine|ja|楊原神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yohara Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Sengen shrine|en|Sengen shrine|qid=Q3471785|lt=Asama Shrine|1=Sengen shrine}}
* {{ill|Nomii Shrine (Takatsuki)|ja|野見神社 (高槻市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nomii Shrine (Takatsuki)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kasuga Shrine (Inabe)|ja|春日神社 (いなべ市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kasuga Shrine (Inabe)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Daishōgun Shrine (Kita-ku, Kyoto)|ja|大将軍神社 (京都市北区)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Daishōgun Shrine (Kita-ku, Kyoto)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Narao Hachiman Shrine|ja|鳴尾八幡神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Narao Hachiman Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Nawakuri Shrine|ja|縄久利神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nawakuri Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Iwa Shrine (Kashiwara)|ja|石神社 (柏原市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Iwa Shrine (Kashiwara)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kumomi Asama Shrine|ja|雲見浅間神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kumomi Asama Shrine|1=Kumomi Sengen Shrine|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11660082}}
* {{ill|Hakusan Nakai Shrine|ja|白山中居神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hakusan Nakai Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Izu Shrine|ja|伊豆神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Izu Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Bekkyū Ōyamazumi Shrine|ja|別宮大山祇神社|1=Bekkyū Ōyamazumi Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Betsugu Oyamatsumi Shrine|13=User:Immanuelle/Betsugu Oyamatsumi Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Ashitaka Shrine|ja|足高神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ashitaka Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kawakami Yamawaka Hachiman Shrine|ja|川上山若宮八幡宮|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kawakami Yamawaka Hachiman Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Oyamatsumi Shrine (Nishi Aizu)|ja|大山祇神社 (西会津町)|1=Oyamatsumi Shrine (Nishi Aizu)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Oyamatsumi Shrine (Nishi Aizu)|13=User:Immanuelle/Oyamatsumi Shrine (Nishi Aizu)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Hikawa Shrine (Itabashi)|ja|氷川神社 (板橋区氷川町)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Hikawa Shrine (Itabashi)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Sazareishi Shrine|ja|細石神社|1=Sazareishi Shrine|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Sazareishi Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Misono Shrine|ja|御祖神社|1=Adachi Myokengu|2=ja|3=御祖神社|4=fr|5=Adachi Myokengu|6=simple|7=User:Immanuelle/Adachiyama Myokengu|1=Adachi Myokengu|4=fr|5=Adachi Myokengu|6=simple|7=User:Immanuelle/Adachiyama Myokengu|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Misono Shrine|13=User:Immanuelle/Adachi Myokengu|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kaina Shrine|ja|甲斐奈神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kaina Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Iina Shrine|ja|飯名神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Iina Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Mishima Shrine (Taito)|ja|三島神社 (台東区)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mishima Shrine (Taito)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kōtai Shrine (Shijōōji, Nara)|ja|皇大神社 (奈良市平松町)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kōtai Shrine (Shijōōji, Nara)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Daishōgun Shrine (Nara City)|ja|大将軍神社 (奈良市)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Daishōgun Shrine (Nara City)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Shinta Shrine|ja|信太神社|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinta Shrine|qq=}}
* {{ill|Kamo Shrine (Tottori Nanbu)|ja|賀茂神社 (鳥取県南部町)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kamo Shrine (Tottori Nanbu)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Nakayama Shrine (Tottori Daisen)|ja|中山神社 (鳥取県大山町)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nakayama Shrine (Tottori Daisen)|qq=}}
* {{ill|Murakami Shrine (Kakamigahara)|ja|村上神社 (各務原市那加長塚町)|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Murakami Shrine (Kakamigahara)|qq=}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{stub}}
{{Iwanaga Faith}}

{{translated page|ja|イワナガヒメ|version=103212763|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[en:Iwanaga-hime]]
[[ja:イワナガヒメ]]

[[ja:Iwanaga-hime]]

&lt;!-- For some reason the encyclopedia of Shinto is not working the best. --&gt;&lt;!--Iwanaga-hime--&gt;&lt;!--Iwanaga-hime--&gt;&lt;!--Iwanaga-hime--&gt;
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[de:Iwanaga-hime]]
[[ko:이와나가히메]]
[[mni:ꯏꯋꯅꯒ-ꯍꯤꯃꯦ]]
[[sv:Iwanaga-hime]]
[[zh:石長比賣]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[de:Iwanaga-hime]]
[[ko:이와나가히메]]
[[mni:ꯏꯋꯅꯒ-ꯍꯤꯃꯦ]]
[[sv:Iwanaga-hime]]
[[zh:石長比賣]]

[[en:Iwanaga-hime]]
{{wikidata link|Q8191705}}
[[Category:Goddesses]]
[[Category:Japanese deities]]
[[Category:Kunitsukami]]
[[Category:Mountain deities]]
[[Category:translated pages with valid en interwikis]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]</text>
      <sha1>5kdf1jy53sbtlz1a2avfk6yrei8tdjj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
