<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Help:Interlanguage links</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>1764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>594370</id>
      <timestamp>2024-07-07T01:12:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>wikipedia&gt;Lazesusdasiru</username>
        <id>0</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Correcting "non-deafult links" to "non-default links"</comment>
      <origin>594370</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16544" sha1="6szrzybzsoalvelbqyxvcybosctnflm" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]</text>
      <sha1>6szrzybzsoalvelbqyxvcybosctnflm</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594371</id>
      <parentid>594370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-07-10T15:48:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 revision imported from [[:wikipedia:Help:Interlanguage_links]]: importing single revision from english wikipedia to provide context instead of writing an inferior article for here</comment>
      <origin>594370</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16544" sha1="6szrzybzsoalvelbqyxvcybosctnflm" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]</text>
      <sha1>6szrzybzsoalvelbqyxvcybosctnflm</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594376</id>
      <parentid>594371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-19T15:36:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SuperHamster</username>
        <id>340</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Featured articles and good articles */ Noting stars</comment>
      <origin>594376</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="17133" sha1="qstz9zqf8s4ands31gjycgdy1r82szx" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}

'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a Wikipedia article in one language to a corresponding page in another language. These links are accessible through the language dropdown menu, which appears as: {{border|[[File:OOjs UI icon language-ltr-progressive.svg|20px|class=s kin-invert]] {{color|#3568CD|'''''XX'' languages'''}}}}, in the upper right corner of the page when using the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin. In other skins, it can be found in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]].&lt;ref&gt;Skins can be changed in your [[Special:Preferences#mw-prefsection-rendering|Special:Preferences § Appearance]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page using the {{tlg|Interlanguage link}} template.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on ''Edit links'' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"Languages" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "Edit interlanguage links" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This can happen for one of two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
{{Ombox
| type  = content
| text  = '''Deprecated''': Local interlanguage links should not be used in the article namespace and should only be used in [[#exceptions|exceptional cases]]. 
}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was ''deprecated'' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

{{anchor|exceptions}}The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by creating a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata (see [[Wikipedia:Wikidata#Interlanguage_links_for_redirects|interlanguage links for redirects]]).
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links (if you were to want to generate them) might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:{{A note}} '''Typically these links do not need to be generated manually like this, and will not show up in the page’s source text .''' These links are usually generated by the wiki software language selector extension in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
[[Wikipedia:Featured content|Featured]] or [[Wikipedia:Good articles|good]] articles are represented via Wikidata.

In an article's list of interlanguage links, featured articles are displayed with a gold star, while good articles are displayed with a gray star.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to foreign language articles.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{langx|fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{langx|ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{langx|fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{langx|ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
# To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{langx|fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{langx|fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikidata#Managing interlanguage links]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]</text>
      <sha1>qstz9zqf8s4ands31gjycgdy1r82szx</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594372</id>
      <parentid>594371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-20T04:29:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:pages from wikipedia]][[en:{{subst:PAGENAME}}]][[Category:pages from wikipedia]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594372</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16637" sha1="0uaaqbzlmnhth76eipxxztzazs2ejg1" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]
[[Category:pages from wikipedia]][[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:pages from wikipedia]]</text>
      <sha1>0uaaqbzlmnhth76eipxxztzazs2ejg1</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594373</id>
      <parentid>594372</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-20T10:16:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Moving from [[Category:Pages from wikipedia]] to [[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594373</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16668" sha1="2d2wnipaqlzj34do4m0esd3yc88m62v" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]
[[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia]]</text>
      <sha1>2d2wnipaqlzj34do4m0esd3yc88m62v</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594374</id>
      <parentid>594373</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-20T11:53:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Moving from [[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia]] to [[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia1]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594374</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16670" sha1="75677yzio1xiif6ly5jjseotoy4pty2" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]
[[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia1]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia1]]</text>
      <sha1>75677yzio1xiif6ly5jjseotoy4pty2</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594375</id>
      <parentid>594374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-26T13:30:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Moving from [[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia1]] to [[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia01]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594375</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16672" sha1="s5duov79fobs74x9kzgont4yf75ndny" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]
[[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia01]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia01]]</text>
      <sha1>s5duov79fobs74x9kzgont4yf75ndny</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594377</id>
      <parentid>594375</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-31T10:04:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 revision imported: importing to remove the lang-fr redlinks</comment>
      <origin>594375</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16672" sha1="s5duov79fobs74x9kzgont4yf75ndny" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{short description|Links between different language versions of Wikipedia}}
{{for-multi|style guidelines about links|MOS:LINK|linking between Wikimedia sister projects (e.g. from Wikipedia to Wiktionary)|Help:Interwiki linking|a list of Wikipedias in other languages with their language codes|List of Wikipedias#Details table|a list of interlanguage codes|list of ISO 639-1 codes|and|meta:List of Wikipedias}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|H:IL|WP:ILL}}
{{Linking and page manipulation|linking and diffs}}
'''Interlanguage links''' are links from a page in one [[Wikipedia]] language to an equivalent page in another language. These links can appear as links in a dropdown menu in the top right corner of the page if you use the default [[Wikipedia:Vector 2022|Vector 2022]] skin, or in the "Languages" section of the page's left [[sidebar (computing)|sidebar]] in other skins.

Less commonly, interlanguage links can be used as inline links in the text of a Wikipedia page.

These two types of links are created and handled differently.

== Links in the "Languages" list&lt;span class="anchor" id="The list of links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|WP:ILLSIDEBAR}}
[[File:Interwiki Languages Ænglisc.png|thumb|In non-default skins, a list of available languages is visible in the left sidebar of the desktop version of Wikipedia under the "Languages" section.]]
Pages on Wikipedia can link to equivalent pages in other languages. The English article on [[Spain]] includes a link to the Spanish article [[:es:España|España]] in the "Languages" list, and vice versa. These links are primarily maintained in  Wikidata and can be overridden in rare cases using [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]] in the text of the page. Using Wikidata is the preferred method.

=== Wikidata ===
[[File:Interlanguage links provided by WikiData.png|thumb|Click on '''Edit links''' to add links to the Wikidata page]]

[[WP:Wikidata|Wikidata]] is a sister project of Wikipedia; it is a collaboratively edited knowledge base. Part of this project is to centralize the interlanguage links for all the Wikipedia projects. The "Languages" list for a page contains  a list of links to a version of that page in different languages. Editing that list on Wikidata is the standard procedure to add or modify interlanguage links.

==== Adding a new link ====
"'''Languages'''" in a menu at the upper right (or in the sidebar in non-default skins) shows the Wikidata language list. At the bottom is a link labelled "'''Edit interlanguage links'''" (or "Edit links" in non-default skins; mobile viewers may lack such a feature). Clicking on this will reveal the Wikidata page. To modify entries on the Languages list:
# Scroll, if necessary, to the box marked "Wikipedia" and click on "edit" at the top of that box.
# Click on the greyed-out "wiki" field, the final item on the list, and enter a language code (see [[list of ISO 639-1 codes]] for all language codes).
# Click on the greyed-out "page" field (now visible) and paste or type in the name of the article as it appears in that language's Wikipedia.
# Click on "publish" at the top of the box.

Modifying or removing an existing interlanguage link is similar. To modify a link, click "edit", then modify the text of a link and click "publish". To remove a link, click "edit", then click the trash can icon for the link you wish to remove.

If you get an error message like "Site link{{nbsp}}... is already used by item Q{{nbsp}}...", this means that there is already an item in Wikidata pointing to the article you are trying to link to. Wikidata does not allow more than one item to point to a single article in a Wikipedia. This happens for two reasons:
* The two items really are the same, and might need to be merged: see [[d:Help:Merge]].
* The scope of the two items is not in fact the same (typically, the article in one language is wider in scope than the article in the other language) and they should not be linked, unless there exists a [[Wikipedia:Redirect|redirect]] between the two items on one of the languages. Unfortunately, there is no mechanism in Wikidata at present for linking articles that are related, but different in a scope – it is possible to do this with [[#Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links|local links]], however.

It may take several minutes for the link to show up in the article's "Languages" list. To enable links between [[Wikipedia:Template namespace|template]]s, you must explicitly [[Wikipedia:Purge|purge the server's cache]] for each template.

===== Finding interlanguage links for an article =====
There are many ways Wikipedia articles in other languages can be found. These include translating the article's title and its synonyms to other languages and searching for them on the respective language-versions of Wikipedia or on Google, searching for &lt;code&gt;articletitle site:wikipedia.org -site:en.wikipedia.org&lt;/code&gt; (for non-English Wikipedia articles), and checking related or superordinate articles or categories in other Wikipedias.

=== Local links to override Wikidata interlanguage links ===
{{sh|WP:LOCALLINK}}
Before 2013, the only method of generating a link to the article in another language was to use a "local" interlanguage link in the text of the page itself. As of 2013, the use of such "local links" for interlanguage linking was '''deprecated''' except in the situations listed below, with interlanguage link data being centralized on [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]]. The problem with having links on each page was that each language had to maintain its own separate lists. So for example, if the name of a page on the English Wikipedia changed, then each Wikipedia article in a different language that linked to that English Wikipedia page would have to separately notice this fact and change their own links.

For most pages, these links are no longer needed and can be safely removed, but you should verify that the local list and the Wikidata lists match before doing so. There is an [[d:Wikidata:Tools/User scripts#Userscripts for Wikipedia|automated tool]] to help with that.

The local links do however still serve some purposes:

# They override the information that comes from Wikidata.
# They were required if more than one article (or redirect) in one language should point to a target article in another language. This can now be resolved by doing a redirect to a section of the article and adding the redirect to Wikidata.
# They are required for pages that are not allowed on Wikidata, such as your userpage.

==== Syntax ====
Although they are useful only in rare cases, you can force the generation of one of these local interlanguage [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Linking|link]] overrides in the article using the following form:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;[[language code:Title]]&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

where the language code is the two-letter code as per [[ISO 639-1]]. (see [[m:list of Wikipedias|complete list of language Wikipedias available]]. English is "en", German is "de", etc.) So for example in the English language article on [[plankton]], which is available on many other wikis, the "local" interlanguage links might look like this:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="wikitext"&gt;
[[ar:عوالق]]
[[el:Πλαγκτόν]]
[[fa:پلانکتون]]
[[he:פלנקטון]]
[[ja:プランクトン]]
[[ko:플랑크톤]]
[[ru:Планктон]]
[[ta:மிதவைவாழி]]
[[te:ప్లవకాలు]]
[[th:แพลงก์ตอน]]
[[zh:浮游生物]]
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

:'''NOTE: These links are treated specially, and don't show up in the body of the text, but in a special sidebar section or drop-down menu, "{{int:otherlanguages}}", listed by language name.''' They can go anywhere in the article source, as their placement does not alter the visual appearance of the links on the rendered page except for the order. However, the convention is to put them at the bottom of the page. Remember, you need these links only if you are overriding the information from Wikidata; in the vast majority of cases, you should edit the links on the Wikidata entry.

To force the "local" generation in the Languages list of the article of all the languages of a different Wikidata item, use [[:Template:Interwiki extra]]. For example, the [[Murder of Kitty Genovese]] automatically links languages listed at {{Q|Q18341392}}; to add the language links at {{Q|Q238128}},  use &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Interwiki extra|Q238128}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  Links to non-English Wikipedia articles to both topics will then appear in the Languages list.

=== Featured articles and good articles ===
Featured or good articles are represented via Wikidata.

== Inline links (links in the text of the article)&lt;span class="anchor" id="Inline links"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ==
{{shortcut|H:FOREIGNLINK}}
{{see also|WP:External links#Non-English-language content|WP:MOSSIS|label 2=Guideline on use of inline links to sister projects}}
When the English Wikipedia doesn't have an article, the links to it show up as [[WP:RED|red links]]. For example, we don't have an article on [[Erich Anders]] (it shows up as a red link), but the German Wikipedia does. There are a few options available:
# The best practice is to use the template {{tl|interlanguage link}} which gives both a redlinked English link and a German blue link, but hides the German link if the English redlink turns blue when the article is created. For instance, by writing {{tlc|interlanguage link|Erich Anders|de}} we get "{{ill|Erich Anders|de}}"; however, if we write {{tlc|interlanguage link|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}} we get "{{ill|Ludwig van Beethoven|de}}", as the page does exist on the English Wikipedia. (Alternatively, the shortcut {{tl|ill}} may be used in place of {{tl|interlanguage link}}.)
# If the foreign language article has a different title, use the following parameters: {{tlxi|ill|English article title|language code|Title in foreign language}} – for example, {{tlc|ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}} gives {{ill|Marivan and Sarvabad constituency|fa|حوزه_انتخابیه_مریوان_و_سروآباد}}.
# To show the language code and the link to the other language article, but don't link to an English article: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都]]. The language abbreviation is displayed, so the reader knows that they are links to the French article on the Olympic Games and the Japanese article on Tokyo.
# To show the ''name'' of the other language instead of its ''code'', which can be easier to read for less experienced readers, you can use the ''[[:Template:Lang|lang]]'' template or one of its class: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; These links look like this: {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}} or {{lang-ja|[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]}}.
#To show only the title: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:東京都|東京都]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; which would look like this in your text: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or [[:ja:東京都|東京都]].
# Using the [[Help:pipe trick|pipe trick]] to simplify methods 4 and 5: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|]]}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These give the same results: ''[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]'' or {{lang-fr|[[:fr:Jeux olympiques|Jeux olympiques]]}}.
# To link to a [[WP:namespace|namespace]] other than the main article namespace, add the namespace after the language abbreviation. For example, the page for general discussions on the Japanese Wikipedia is located in the Wikipedia namespace. You can link to it as follows: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端]] or [[:ja:Wikipedia:井戸端|Wikipedia:井戸端]].
# On [[Wikipedia:Talk pages|Talk pages]] and on [[Wikipedia:Meta|Meta]], you can omit the leading colon. An interlanguage link like &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[fr:Jeux olympiques]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will appear inline in the text, like a regular link.
# An inline link to a Wiktionary entry, such as &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[wikt:model|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, can be directed to another language's Wiktionary: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;''[[wikt:fr:modèle|]]''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; gives ''[[wikt:fr:modèle|fr:modèle]]''.

== Links to pages that do not exist ==
On the English Wikipedia, links to pages that do not exist are displayed in a different color (usually red). But this check is not performed for links to pages on another wiki (including other [[Wikimedia Foundation]] sites). Unlike internal links, these links do not indicate whether the target page exists or not.&lt;ref&gt;[[bugzilla:11|Bug 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; If the target page does not exist, the link leads to a message on the target wiki informing you that the page does not exist and inviting you to create it.

If you find interlanguage links to non-existent pages on the English Wikipedia, they may be deleted as having no content. Alternatively, you can create at least a [[Wikipedia:Stub|stub]] page on the target wiki before adding an interlanguage link to it. Later, interested people can complete the rest of the page.

'''Note''': if the language prefix is wrong, it is considered to be part of the name of a page on the English Wikipedia. This page will probably not exist, so the link will be displayed in red.

The {{tl|interlanguage link}} template can help with this.

== Linking with external links ==
{{main|Wikipedia:External links}}
You can also link to Wikipedia pages in other languages by using external links, in the same way as linking to other sites on the Internet. This method should not be used in the body of an article, but it may be useful on User pages or Talk pages. For example, this method can be used to link to [[Help:Diff|diff pages]] that show the editing history of a page on another Wikipedia.

The following code:

:&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

renders as:

:Tokyo 2020 was added to the French page on the Olympics in [https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeux_olympiques&amp;diff=96480208&amp;oldid=96417677 this diff].

Templates {{tlx|Cross-wiki language diff}} and {{tlx|Cross-wiki language free diff}} are also available to construct diffs for other languages and projects, as is the [[WP:SPEC|special-page]] term &lt;code&gt;:Diff/&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will show the [[:fr:Special:Diff/96480208|same diff]] as above.

== Multilingual links and QR codes ==
https://qrpedia.org/ offers a tool to create a multilingual link to a Wikipedia article in any language. The user's browser will be redirected to the corresponding page in the language of the browser. Just replace '''en.wikipedia.org/wiki/''' with '''en.qrwp.org/''' in the URL to get a multilingual link. For example: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat, if changed to https://en.qrwp.org/Cat, will be redirected in a French browser to https://fr.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chat.
You can also make QR codes using the tool at: https://qrpedia.org/ and 3D print them into plaques for zoos, botanical gardens, monuments, etc. using https://printer.tools/qrcode2stl/

== See also ==
* [[Help:Menu/Links]] – overview

'''Different languages'''
* {{tl|Interlanguage link}}
* [[Wikipedia:Translation]]
* [[List of Wikipedias]]

'''Sister projects'''
* [[Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[Wikipedia:Wikimedia sister projects]]
* {{tl|Sister project}}
* {{tl|Sister-inline}}
* [[List of Wiktionaries]]

'''Miscellanea'''
* [[Wikipedia:Babel]] – Userpage language proficiency banners
* [[Wikipedia:TemplateData]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [[meta:Help:Interwiki linking]]
* [[meta:Interlanguage links]] for details on linking different languages on Meta.
* [[wikt:Wiktionary:Interlanguage links|Wiktionary:Interlanguage links]]

{{Wikipedia technical help|collapsed}}
[[Category:Wikipedia how-to|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia multilingual coordination|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Wikipedia link help]]
[[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia01]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Pages and Categories from wikipedia01]]</text>
      <sha1>s5duov79fobs74x9kzgont4yf75ndny</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594378</id>
      <parentid>594377</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-31T11:16:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Replaced content with "#redirect[[en:{{subst:FULLPAGENAME}}]][[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects]]"</comment>
      <origin>594378</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="82" sha1="9mppwk8hv26bmj954mm30iaw2j1za82" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects]]</text>
      <sha1>9mppwk8hv26bmj954mm30iaw2j1za82</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594379</id>
      <parentid>594378</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-11T03:09:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>moving them to the second thousand</comment>
      <origin>594379</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="140" sha1="o0ls4ikwlfduizum4jmgtw797mdz688" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]][[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects]]</text>
      <sha1>o0ls4ikwlfduizum4jmgtw797mdz688</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594380</id>
      <parentid>594379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-11T03:17:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:automatic wikipedia redirects 1k to 2k]] second go using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594380</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="192" sha1="40wthw8xhfhefjjltjgbiad7ij6u5e5" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]][[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects]]
[[Category:automatic wikipedia redirects 1k to 2k]]</text>
      <sha1>40wthw8xhfhefjjltjgbiad7ij6u5e5</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594381</id>
      <parentid>594380</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-11T03:39:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594381</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="149" sha1="pr40753z9rc2cih8bidoj9nz0wy3re6" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]][[Category:automatic wikipedia redirects 1k to 2k]]</text>
      <sha1>pr40753z9rc2cih8bidoj9nz0wy3re6</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594382</id>
      <parentid>594381</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-11T04:18:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects 1k to 2k]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594382</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="98" sha1="rkwoe2pqh1zlytsr7z7ym3qaeufvqg3" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]]</text>
      <sha1>rkwoe2pqh1zlytsr7z7ym3qaeufvqg3</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594383</id>
      <parentid>594382</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-11T04:59:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:bbb]] adding a dummy category again to make the cateroies show up using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594383</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="115" sha1="td41zkq5vese8aswt15dns4ocilyxqf" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]]
[[Category:bbb]]</text>
      <sha1>td41zkq5vese8aswt15dns4ocilyxqf</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594384</id>
      <parentid>594383</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-14T02:05:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>confirming the redirects</comment>
      <origin>594384</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="180" sha1="4mqkocbmb7ms8jox346x2ihy7jzvooa" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Automatic_wikipedia_redirects_second_thousand]]
[[Category:bbb]]</text>
      <sha1>4mqkocbmb7ms8jox346x2ihy7jzvooa</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594385</id>
      <parentid>594384</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-14T02:15:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:Automatic wikipedia redirects second thousand]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594385</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="121" sha1="0g867dfh4vc4os7ecggn4l7bmajatkc" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]</text>
      <sha1>0g867dfh4vc4os7ecggn4l7bmajatkc</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594386</id>
      <parentid>594385</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-14T02:47:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:refreshing the redirects]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594386</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="159" sha1="4el2vjpid41pi1ni43uyiqoamviz7b5" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]
[[Category:refreshing the redirects]]</text>
      <sha1>4el2vjpid41pi1ni43uyiqoamviz7b5</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594387</id>
      <parentid>594386</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-14T04:46:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>mass editing for the third subcategory</comment>
      <origin>594387</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="164" sha1="rglnrsksi9pegbx3tz2y3qfvugzwbfa" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]
[[Category:refreshing the redirects]]</text>
      <sha1>rglnrsksi9pegbx3tz2y3qfvugzwbfa</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594388</id>
      <parentid>594387</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-14T05:14:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Copying from [[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects]] to [[Category:Tt]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594388</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="180" sha1="qt1j6hc71g7dlludqxs7pj40wfu8604" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]
[[Category:refreshing the redirects]]
[[Category:Tt]]</text>
      <sha1>qt1j6hc71g7dlludqxs7pj40wfu8604</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594389</id>
      <parentid>594388</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-28T02:34:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]][[Category:{{subst:FULLPAGENAME}}]][[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594389</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="338" sha1="ga70k447heredn4pjvflbgb7i04djcp" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]
[[Category:refreshing the redirects]]
[[Category:Tt]]
[[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]][[Category:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]]</text>
      <sha1>ga70k447heredn4pjvflbgb7i04djcp</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594390</id>
      <parentid>594389</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-01-28T02:44:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]][[Category:{{subst:PAGENAME}}]][[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594390</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="333" sha1="4o4b8tnk8j78v1msof5oiiiid73g3yh" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bbb]]
[[Category:refreshing the redirects]]
[[Category:Tt]]
[[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]][[Category:Interlanguage links]][[Category:second attempt at refreshing on January 27 2024]]</text>
      <sha1>4o4b8tnk8j78v1msof5oiiiid73g3yh</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594391</id>
      <parentid>594390</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-02-13T19:59:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>594391</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="377" sha1="qf2whrvts3kz0j1mmbys2s3225ume24" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]</text>
      <sha1>qf2whrvts3kz0j1mmbys2s3225ume24</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594392</id>
      <parentid>594391</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-02-13T22:27:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:bump {{subst:CURRENTMONTHNAME}} {{subst:CURRENTDAY}}, {{subst:CURRENTYEAR}} bump]][[en:{{subst:PAGENAME}}]][[Category:bump {{subst:CURRENTMONTHNAME}} {{subst:CURRENTDAY}}, {{subst:CURRENTYEAR}} bump]] on (CatAlot)</comment>
      <origin>594392</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="484" sha1="cta7pj6b3u00gl7bmsmbvzha5eehowo" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[category:confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]][[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]][[Category:Confirmed_wikipedia_redirects_3]]
[[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]][[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]]</text>
      <sha1>cta7pj6b3u00gl7bmsmbvzha5eehowo</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594393</id>
      <parentid>594392</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-02-18T22:31:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Copying from [[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]] to [[Category:qq]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594393</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="599" sha1="scdzishmeycleveggo5ixli8ccn5luw" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:qq]]
[[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]][[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]]</text>
      <sha1>scdzishmeycleveggo5ixli8ccn5luw</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594394</id>
      <parentid>594393</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-03-19T20:47:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "qq" to "11"</comment>
      <origin>594394</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="599" sha1="9kehviybr24si2wm0qquae6km6gh9ns" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]][[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:bump February 13, 2025 bump]]</text>
      <sha1>9kehviybr24si2wm0qquae6km6gh9ns</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594395</id>
      <parentid>594394</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-04-17T00:41:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:Bump February 13, 2025 bump]] on using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594395</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="519" sha1="2g6f3nykgw1pkavp7874fuh9e1pplom" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>2g6f3nykgw1pkavp7874fuh9e1pplom</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594396</id>
      <parentid>594395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-04-17T00:55:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding [[Category:qq]][[sn:{{subst:PAGENAME}}]][[Category:qq]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <origin>594396</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="576" sha1="gj4krv477fidzivlfaibh11qry20lf6" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]
[[Category:11]]
[[Category:qq]][[sn:Interlanguage links]][[Category:qq]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>gj4krv477fidzivlfaibh11qry20lf6</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594397</id>
      <parentid>594396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-04-29T10:46:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "[[Category:11]]" to ""</comment>
      <origin>594397</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="471" sha1="1eji3ikf5j3kfynwmlexce0el87f9vj" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:qq]][[sn:Interlanguage links]][[Category:qq]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>1eji3ikf5j3kfynwmlexce0el87f9vj</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594398</id>
      <parentid>594397</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-04-29T10:47:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "[[Category:qq]]" to ""</comment>
      <origin>594398</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="441" sha1="jpbfj2fcbgcural5dpqbp03ppal6fej" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]][[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[Category:Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3]]

[[sn:Interlanguage links]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>jpbfj2fcbgcural5dpqbp03ppal6fej</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594399</id>
      <parentid>594398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-19T00:36:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove deleted category Confirmed wikipedia redirects 3</comment>
      <origin>594399</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="133" sha1="oolbst2bcilr4gbbap36gj7wyn1b65s" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]











[[sn:Interlanguage links]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>oolbst2bcilr4gbbap36gj7wyn1b65s</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>594400</id>
      <parentid>594399</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-11-22T14:00:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "↵↵↵" to "
"</comment>
      <origin>594400</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="125" sha1="g0tvyjytfd3i09zbjtjph45oummcpzv" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]



[[sn:Interlanguage links]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>g0tvyjytfd3i09zbjtjph45oummcpzv</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>1765</id>
      <timestamp>2025-11-22T14:00:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>imported only latest revision from https://archive.org/details/miraheze-wiki-shintowiki-20251218 to avoid excessive disk usage, comment on the revision was Text replacement - "↵↵↵" to "
"</comment>
      <origin>1765</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="123" sha1="966co5gkoepn0qhuhygfwos210n6sl1" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]

[[sn:Interlanguage links]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>966co5gkoepn0qhuhygfwos210n6sl1</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>359574</id>
      <parentid>1765</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-20T01:49:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "[[sn:" to "[[Category:sn_crud|TEST"</comment>
      <origin>359574</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="141" sha1="o5k69oxfjwp4pgmp60rzuwirutq20dr" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]

[[Category:sn_crud|TESTInterlanguage links]]
[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>o5k69oxfjwp4pgmp60rzuwirutq20dr</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3604410</id>
      <parentid>359574</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-10T02:27:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Sn crud]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24221752933|time triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3604410</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="96" sha1="gf1c1rk0moiiuf9hz7s1t3odxpm9co6" xml:space="preserve">#redirect[[en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>gf1c1rk0moiiuf9hz7s1t3odxpm9co6</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3695754</id>
      <parentid>3604410</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-02T22:28:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>removing these dumb broken links that cause problems</comment>
      <origin>3695754</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="96" sha1="98k58j17yt6rc862ctugh5hkjhw4r5i" xml:space="preserve">redirect[[:en:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Help:Interlanguage links]]

[[en:Interlanguage links]]</text>
      <sha1>98k58j17yt6rc862ctugh5hkjhw4r5i</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3713121</id>
      <parentid>3695754</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-06T05:54:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: consolidate 2 interlanguage link(s) into wikidata link template (has duplicate-language pairs) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/25416871275|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3713121</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="165" sha1="cqwgbx187dun2tgurqp64p01aap98ff" xml:space="preserve">redirect[[:en:Interlanguage links]]
{{wikidata link||en|Help:Interlanguage links|en|Interlanguage links}}
[[Category:Pages with interwikis with duplicate languages]]</text>
      <sha1>cqwgbx187dun2tgurqp64p01aap98ff</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
