<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ceremonial vessel stands or jars</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10313</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3599848</id>
      <parentid>3592852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-05T00:51:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Sn crud]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23989927232|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3599848</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="17294" sha1="ocpv009m2a0jumqr8xwy2di8ljgvtnl" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:特殊器台・特殊壺]]

{{複数の問題
|Referencesの明記=2024th year 5月
|More footnotes needed=2024th year 5月
|独自研究=2024th year 5月
}}

[[File:特殊器台・特殊壺 (複製).JPG|thumb|220px|right|Special Pedestal and Jar (Replica){{small|Exhibited at the {{ill|National Museum of Japanese History|en|National Museum of Japanese History|qid=Q3330690|lt=National Museum of Japanese History|1=National Museum of Japanese History}}.}}]]
[[File:都月坂1号墳出土 特殊器台形埴輪・楯築墳丘墓出土 特殊器台.JPG|thumb|220px|right|Right: Special Pedestal from {{ill|Tatetsuki Site|en|Tatetsuki Site|qid=Q11541408|lt=Tatetsuki Site|1=Tatetsuki Site}}Left: Special Pedestal-shaped Haniwa from Tsukizaka No.1 Kofun

{{small|Exhibited at the Okayama University Archaeological Materials Display Room.}}]]

'''Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo''' (特殊器台・特殊壺) are cylindrical and jar-shaped pottery items originating in the {{ill|Kibi|en|Kibi|qid=Q404065|lt=Kibi region|1=Kibi}} (modern {{ill|Okayama Prefecture|en|Okayama Prefecture|qid=Q132936|lt=Okayama Prefecture|1=Okayama Prefecture}}) during the late {{ill|Yayoi period|en|Yayoi period|qid=Q207858|lt=Yayoi period|1=Yayoi period}} (2nd century). These ornate pottery pieces were decorated with intricate patterns and painted red with cinnabar, showing a high level of artistry. They were used in the burial rites of local chiefs and are considered precursors to {{ill|cylindrical haniwa|ja|円筒埴輪|1=Cylindrical Haniwa|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/cylindrical haniwa|13=User:Immanuelle/Cylindrical Haniwa|qq=}} and {{ill|morning-glory-shaped haniwa|ja|朝顔形埴輪|1=Morning glory-shaped haniwa|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/morning-glory-shaped haniwa|13=User:Immanuelle/Morning glory-shaped haniwa|qq=}}. They are also referred to as "Tokushu Kidai-type pottery" and "Tokushu Tsubo-type pottery" {{Sfn|Kondō|Harunari|1967|pp=13-35}}.

== Overview ==
The emergence of '''Tokushu Kidai''' and '''Tokushu Tsubo''' dates to the middle of the {{ill|Yayoi period|en|Yayoi period|qid=Q207858|lt=Yayoi period|1=Yayoi period}}, with particular development and widespread use in the late period before declining in the early {{ill|Kofun period|en|Kofun period|qid=Q459939|lt=Kofun period|1=Kofun period}}. This phenomenon provides valuable clues for identifying the earliest {{ill|Zenpokoenfun|en|Zenpokoenfun|qid=Q11268718|lt=Zenpokoenfun|1=Zenpōkōenfun}} and their locations.

=== From Regular Stands and Jars to Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo ===
Jar-shaped pottery appeared during the earliest Yayoi period, followed shortly by stands. Due to their large size and elaborate decoration, stands were likely not used for everyday purposes. They served as supports for jars, bowls, and plates, but their archaeological rarity suggests they were special items. By the middle Yayoi period, jars and stands were found together across various sites, suggesting that stands, supporting jars and other items, were likely used in rituals.

During harvest festivals, it is believed that jars were filled with sake made from freshly harvested rice or rice porridge, while stands displayed harvested crops. Deities were invited to partake in a feast alongside humans, offering gratitude for the harvest and making requests. Such rituals were referred to as {{ill|Ainame Festival|lt=Ainame|ja|相嘗|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ainame Festival|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 相嘗祭}} (ainame) or {{ill|Naorai|ja|直会|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Naorai|comment=enwiki is a redirect}} (naorai). Chiefs, as community leaders and often kin to the villagers, would oversee these ceremonies, offering sake and food to deities such as crop spirits, rice field gods, water gods, mountain gods, and land gods, while conducting prayers {{Citation needed|date=2020-04-23}}. During this time, stands and jars became integral tools for rituals, especially in western Japan during the middle Yayoi period.

Ordinary stands of this period were relatively long and slender in shape, but during the early part of the late Yayoi period, they became increasingly weighty. By the late part of the late Yayoi period, stands gained significant mass and were decorated with intricate patterns such as {{ill|sawtooth designs|ja|鋸歯文|1=Sawtooth patterns|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/sawtooth designs|13=User:Immanuelle/Sawtooth patterns|qq=}} and carved motifs. Their cylindrical sections lengthened, and square openwork elements became common. Jars, meanwhile, developed elongated necks in a flared "V" shape—a feature that transitioned into Tokushu Tsubo. 

By the time the late Yayoi period transitioned to the Kofun period, Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo emerged, originating in southern {{ill|Bitchū Province|en|Bitchū Province|qid=Q1047514|lt=Bitchū Province|1=Bitchū Province}} and spreading across {{ill|Kibi Province|en|Kibi Province|qid=Q1155128|lt=Kibi Province|1=Kingdom of Kibi}}. During this era, regular stands and jars fell out of use in many Kibi villages, being replaced by these highly specialized ceremonial objects.

== Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo ==
'''Tokushu Kidai''' and '''Tokushu Tsubo''' have only been excavated from mound burials of chieftains ({{ill|Yayoi Kofuns|ja|弥生墳丘墓|1=Yayoi mounded tombs|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yayoi Kofuns|13=User:Immanuelle/Yayoi mounded tombs|qq=}}) from the late phase of the {{ill|Yayoi period|en|Yayoi period|qid=Q207858|lt=Yayoi period|1=Yayoi period}}. Prior to this, regular stands and jars were used during village harvest festivals for summoning deities and performing rituals. However, for the funerary rites of deceased chieftains, Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo replaced these ordinary items. The enshrined chieftains, central figures in their communities, became deified along with their ancestors. Over time, ancestral deities became the focal point of rituals, accompanied by reverence and awe. The rituals to pass the spiritual power of the deceased chieftain and ancestral deity to the succeeding leader employed Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo.

=== Tokushu Kidai (Special Stands) ===
The basic shape is cylindrical, resembling the letter "I," with both the top and bottom ends flaring outward. The upper section can reach a vertical width of 15 centimeters, while the bottom section is shaped like a sturdy trapezoid, providing ample stability.

The height of Tokushu Kidai ranges from 70–80 centimeters to over 1 meter, significantly larger than ordinary stands, which measure 20–40 centimeters. The diameter of the cylindrical section exceeds 30 centimeters, with some reaching over 40 centimeters. Around 6–10 ring-shaped raised bands encircle the cylinder, serving to reinforce its structure and divide it into sections. These bands alternate between decorated zones and plain horizontal bands. Decorated zones include abstract motifs resembling twisted yarn bundles or waves, as well as patterns like chevron designs, complex diagonal lines, or {{ill|sawtooth patterns|ja|鋸歯文|1=Sawtooth patterns|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/sawtooth patterns|13=User:Immanuelle/Sawtooth patterns|qq=}}. 

Openwork elements are often incorporated into the decorated zones. For example, motifs such as tomoe-shaped or triangular cutouts appear in wavy patterns, while rectangular perforations are common in designs like chevrons. Many stands display traces of red pigment (丹) applied to the exterior surface and the inner surface of the rim. In some cases, the pigment was applied in stages as the clay coils were built up, suggesting that the production process itself was imbued with ritual significance. Special clay was chosen for these stands, often mixed with minerals such as amphibole. After firing, the stands exhibited a characteristic brownish hue.

=== Tokushu Tsubo (Special Jars) ===
Tokushu Tsubo feature slightly elongated necks in a flared "V" shape, with wide, rounded bodies that convey a sense of mass and stability. The mouth section has a double rim with significant vertical width. The neck tapers slightly toward the top and is decorated with horizontal incised or grooved lines. Near the neck's base, where it connects to the shoulder, rows of small dot patterns are applied.

The base is flat, and most jars feature perforations made after firing, preventing the jars from holding liquid such as sake. The onion-shaped body often includes 2–3 raised or broad bands, between which patterns such as sawtooth designs or grid motifs are drawn. Above the bands, the body is further decorated with multiple horizontal incised lines. The jars are coated in red pigment (丹) across their entire exterior, and like Tokushu Kidai, they are made of special clay mixed with specific materials to enhance their ceremonial significance.

== Transition of Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo ==
[[File:宮山墳墓群出土 特殊器台.JPG|thumb|220px|right|{{center|Tokushu Kidai from the {{ill|Miyayama Kofun Cluster|ja|宮山墳墓群|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Miyayama Kofun Cluster|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}&lt;br /&gt;(Designated as a {{ill|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|en|Important Cultural Property (Japan)|qid=Q1188622|lt=Important Cultural Property|1=Important Cultural Property (Japan)}})}}{{small|Exhibited at {{ill|Okayama Prefectural Museum|en|Okayama Prefectural Museum|qid=Q3247162|lt=Okayama Prefectural Museum|1=Okayama Prefectural Museum}}.}}]]

=== Tachizaka Type (Early Phase of Tokushu Kidai) ===
The type is named after the {{ill|Tachizaka Site|ja|立坂遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Tachizaka Site|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} in {{ill|Sōja|en|Sōja|qid=Q873536|lt=Sōja|1=Sōja}}, Okayama Prefecture, where it was first noted. This category can be further divided into the Tachizaka type (Tatezuka) from the {{ill|Tatetsuki Site|en|Tatetsuki Site|qid=Q11541408|lt=Tatetsuki Site|1=Tatetsuki Site}} in {{ill|Kurashiki|en|Kurashiki|qid=Q467487|lt=Kurashiki|1=Kurashiki}}, the Tachizaka type (Tachizaka) from the Tachizaka Site in Sōja, and the Tachizaka type (Nakayama) from the {{ill|Nakayama Site|ja|中山遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nakayama Site|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} in {{ill|Maniwa|en|Maniwa|qid=Q861230|lt=Maniwa|1=Maniwa}}, previously part of {{ill|Ochiai, Okayama|en|Ochiai, Okayama|qid=Q7076314|lt=Ochiai Town, Okayama|1=Ochiai, Okayama}}.

; Tachizaka Type (Tatezuka)
This type features combinations of herringbone patterns, sawtooth patterns, herringbone patterns, and triangular designs. Horizontal patterns are not observed. The curved-band motifs resemble intertwined, looped, or knotted bands. At this stage, no horizontal curved-band motifs have yet appeared. The rim width reaches approximately 10 centimeters, adorned with multiple embossed bands interspersed with decorations.

; Tachizaka Type (Tachizaka)
This type introduces curved-band motifs that resemble twisted yarn bundles or abstract waves, marking the beginning of this decorative style.

; Tachizaka Type (Nakayama)
This subtype alternates between curved-band motifs and vertically divided herringbone patterns. Horizontal curved-band motifs dominate without herringbone patterns. Such characteristics are also noted in {{ill|Yadani Kofun|en|Yadani Kofun|qid=Q28688908|lt=Yadani Kofun|1=Yadani Kofun}} in {{ill|Miyoshi, Hiroshima|en|Miyoshi, Hiroshima|qid=Q840591|lt=Miyoshi, Hiroshima|1=Miyoshi, Hiroshima}}, Hiroshima Prefecture.

=== Mukōgimi Type (Later Phase of Tokushu Kidai) ===
Named after the {{ill|Mukōgimi Site|ja|向木見遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mukōgimi Site|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} in Kurashiki, the Mukōgimi type has been excavated from over 30 sites, with more than 100 individual examples identified. At the {{ill|Yadani Kofun|en|Yadani Kofun|qid=Q28688908|lt=Yadani Kofun|1=Yadani Kofun}}, five distinct patterns were discovered in a single site. Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo were detected within the surrounding moats. Other notable finds include three pieces with five distinct patterns from the {{ill|Nishie Site|ja|西江遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nishie Site|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} in {{ill|Niimi|en|Niimi|qid=Q873596|lt=Niimi|1=Niimi}} and two pieces with two patterns from the {{ill|Nishiyama Site|ja|西山遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nishiyama Site|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} in Kurashiki.

Mukōgimi patterns exhibit thicker, more rigid lines compared to Tachizaka styles. During this phase, some jars began to include pre-fired perforations in their bases, preventing the storage of liquids like sake.

=== Miyayama Type (Terminal Phase) ===
The terminal phase includes two types: the Yatōjiyama Type and the Miyayama Type. Each has only been identified at a single site. Tokushu Tsubo from both sites indicates their contemporaneous nature. During this period, Tokushu Tsubo began to resemble {{ill|Haji pottery|en|Haji pottery|qid=Q5639938|lt=Haji pottery|1=Haji pottery}} with double-rim features. The bases of jars were perforated before firing, ensuring they could not hold liquids.

; Yatōjiyama Type
Found exclusively at the {{ill|Yatōjiyama Kofun|ja|矢藤治山古墳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Yatōjiyama Kofun|qq=}} in {{ill|Okayama|en|Okayama|qid=Q200078|lt=Okayama City|1=Okayama}}, this type represents the culmination of the Mukōgimi type after simplifications and transitions. The decorative band of Tokushu Tsubo features sawtooth patterns.

; Miyayama Type
The Miyayama Tokushu Kidai has only been found at the {{ill|Miyayama Site|ja|宮山遺跡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Miyayama Site|qq=}} in Sōja. The rim is thick and inward-slanting, with unique structural features. The patterns differ from earlier types like Tachizaka and Mukōgimi, resembling expanded versions of Yatōjiyama motifs. These patterns include parallel lines—two or three thick curved bands—connected by short straight lines. The decoration is highly intricate and represents a newly conceived style. Additionally, the rims and necks of Tokushu Tsubo from this phase feature brush-stroke patterns.

== Relationship with the Beginning of the Kofun Period ==
The Miyayama-type Tokushu Kidai has been discovered at one site in {{ill|Kibi|en|Kibi|qid=Q404065|lt=Kibi|1=Kibi}} and four sites in {{ill|Nara Prefecture|en|Nara Prefecture|qid=Q131287|lt=Nara Prefecture|1=Nara Prefecture}} ({{ill|Yamato Province|en|Yamato Province|qid=Q907495|lt=Yamato Province|1=Yamato Province}}), but it is unclear where production began. The {{ill|Hashihaka Kofun|en|Hashihaka Kofun|qid=Q11603420|lt=Hashihaka Kofun|1=Hashihaka Kofun}} in {{ill|Sakurai, Nara|en|Sakurai, Nara|qid=Q127026|lt=Sakurai, Nara|1=Sakurai, Nara}}, considered one of the earliest kofun, is believed to have been constructed around the 3rd century. Miyayama-type Tokushu Kidai have been unearthed at this Kofun, suggesting that the beginning of the Kofun period coincides with the appearance of terminal-phase Tokushu Kidai and Tokushu Tsubo.

In addition to the Hashihaka Kofun (280 meters), other relatively large kofun with paddle-shaped front portions and classified among the earliest keyhole-shaped Kofuns include the {{ill|Nishitonozuka Kofun|ja|西殿塚古墳|1=Nishitonozuka Kofun|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nishitonozuka Kofun|13=User:Immanuelle/Nishitonozuka Kofun|qq=}} (219 meters) in {{ill|Tenri, Nara|en|Tenri, Nara|qid=Q502196|lt=Tenri, Nara|1=Tenri, Nara}}, the {{ill|Nakayama Ōtsuka Kofun|lt=Nakayama Ōtsuka Kofun|lt=Nakayama Otsuka Kofun|ja|中山大塚古墳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nakayama Otsuka Kofun|qq=}} (120 meters) in the same city, and the {{ill|Benten-tsuka Kofun|ja|弁天塚古墳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Benten-tsuka Kofun|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} (over 100 meters) in {{ill|Kashihara, Nara|en|Kashihara, Nara|qid=Q496319|lt=Kashihara, Nara|1=Kashihara, Nara}}. These kofun have also yielded Miyayama-type Tokushu Kidai.

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

== Further Reading ==
* {{Cite journal|和書|last=近藤|first=義郎|authorlink=近藤義郎|last2=春成|first2=秀爾|authorlink2=春成秀爾|year=1967|date=1967-02|title=埴輪の起源|ncid=AN00081939|issn=03869148|journal=考古学研究|volume=13|issue=3|pages=13-35|publisher=[[考古学研究会]]|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|和書|last=近藤|first=義郎|title=前方後円墳に学ぶ（第1版）|publisher=[[山川出版社]]|year=2001|date=2001-01|isbn=4634604906|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|和書|last=寺沢|first=薫|authorlink=寺沢薫|title=日本の歴史02 王権誕生（第1版）|publisher=[[講談社]]|year=2008|date=2008-12|isbn=9784062919029|ref=harv}}

== See Also ==
* {{ill|Haniwa|en|Haniwa|qid=Q849376|lt=Haniwa|1=Haniwa}}
* {{ill|Zenpokoenfun|en|Zenpokoenfun|qid=Q11268718|lt=Zenpokoenfun|1=Zenpōkōenfun}}
* {{ill|Yayoi period|en|Yayoi period|qid=Q207858|lt=Yayoi period|1=Yayoi period}}

{{japanese-history-stub}}

{{Kofun navbar}}

{{translated page|ja|特殊器台・特殊壺|version=100222215|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:特殊器台・特殊壺]]

&lt;!--Special platforms and jars--&gt;

&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;

{{wikidata link|Q11570998}}
[[Category:土器]]
[[Category:Yayoi period]]</text>
      <sha1>ocpv009m2a0jumqr8xwy2di8ljgvtnl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
