<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Daijosai</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2197</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3593287</id>
      <parentid>3591975</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:41:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3593287</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="43032" sha1="kuj71sp2sqokyfjy1tgf2s1ygt5zw8d" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[de:Daijō-sai]][[en:Daijosai]][[fa:دایجوسای]][[fr:Daijosai]][[ja:大嘗祭]][[ru:Дайдзёсай]][[th:ไดโจไซ]]


{{Short description|Japanese imperial ceremony|qq=}}
{{Rough translation|Japanese|date=March 2023|qq=}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2022|qq=}}
{{Infobox recurring event
| name               = Daijosai
| native_name        = 大嘗祭
| native_name_lang   = ja
| logo               = [[File:Imperial Seal of Japan.svg|45px]] [[File:Inari - daiwa torii.svg|55px]]
| logo_caption       = 
| image              = [[File:Dengai-omi-akusha (Reiwa Daijokyu).JPG|300px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Emperor Akihito Daijōsai(1990).jpg|300px]]
| caption            = Top: Daijō-sai of Reiwa ([[Imperial Palace East Garden]]) &lt;br /&gt; Bottom: The Daijō-sai of Emperor {{ill|Akihito|en|Akihito|qid=Q37979|lt=Akihito|1=Akihito}} in 1990
| genre              = *[[Shinto|Shinto ceremony]]
*[[Ritual ceremonies of the Imperial Palace]]
*[[Miyanaka ritual]]
| frequency          = {{plainlist|
*The first [[Niiname-no-Matsuri]] after the Emperor's accession to the throne.
*Once in a generation, occurring only once per accession
}}
| venue              = Daijokyu (Sukiden, Yukiden, and Kairyuden)
| location           = Residence of the Emperor of Japan（Has changed over the ages, currently [[Tokyo Imperial Palace]]）
| country            = Japan
| first              = It is rooted in farming rituals, and its original form is thought to be from around the [[Yayoi period]], and the current scale and style are from the era of {{ill|Emperor Tenmu|en|Emperor Tenmu|qid=Q335181|lt=Tenmu|1=Emperor Tenmu}} and [[Empress Jito|Jito]]. Around (7th century)
| prev               = 2019 (2022) 14 and 15 November
| next               = Upon a new Emperor succeeding to the [[Chrysanthemum Throne]]
| attendance         = Approximately 730 people in total
| activity           = A ceremony in which the newly enthroned emperor makes an offering to the gods of [[grain|new grain]] offered from the east and west of Japan, and eats it himself to pray for a bountiful harvest, peace of mind during his reign, and the well-being of the nation and its people, according to [[Shinto]].
| patron             = [[Japanese government]]
| organised          = [[Imperial Household Agency]]
| website            = [https://www.kunaicho.go.jp/ 宮内庁]
}}
The '''Daijō-sai''' {{nihongo||大嘗祭|qq=}} is a special religious service conducted in November after the [[Enthronement of the Japanese emperor|enthronement]], in which the {{ill|Emperor of Japan|en|Emperor of Japan|qid=Q208233|lt=Emperor of Japan|1=Emperor of Japan}} gives thanks for peace of mind and a rich harvest to the {{ill|Solar deity|en|Solar deity|qid=Q511056|lt=Solar deity|1=Solar deity}} [[Amaterasu]] (天照大神) and her [[Kami|associated deities]], and pray for Japan and its citizens. From a [[Shinto]] viewpoint, the emperor is believed to be united with the deity Amaterasu in a unique way and share in her {{ill|Divinity|en|Divinity|qid=Q1379405|lt=Divinity|1=Divinity}}. In general, the Daijosai is considered as a kind of thanksgiving harvest festival, in the same way as [[Niiname-no-Matsuri|Niiname-sai (新嘗祭)]] is conducted annually on 23 November, a {{ill|Public holidays in Japan|en|Public holidays in Japan|qid=Q1195354|lt=public holiday|1=Public holidays in Japan}} of {{ill|Labor Thanksgiving Day|en|Labor Thanksgiving Day|qid=Q82405|lt=Labor Thanksgiving Day|1=Labor Thanksgiving Day}}. However, in the year the Daijō-sai is held, the Niiname-sai (新嘗祭) is not held.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Tsunetada Mayumi |author-link=:ja:真弓常忠 |title=大嘗祭 |publisher=[[Chikuma Shobō]] |year=2019 |series=Chikuma Shinsyo |trans-title=Enthronement of the Japanese emperor|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The emperor and empress both perform the Daijosai ceremony in November after ascending the throne in a partly televised ceremony and since 2019 it is a live-streamed event. It is only performed once during their reign. Akihito performed it in November 1990 and Naruhito on 14 November 2019. The emperor offers gifts such as rice, kelp, millet and abalone to the gods.  Then he reads an appeal to the gods and eats the offering and prays. The emperor and empress perform the rites separately. It takes about 3 hours. Over 500 people are present including the {{ill|Prime Minister of Japan|en|Prime Minister of Japan|qid=Q274948|lt=Prime Minister|1=Prime Minister of Japan}}, government officials, representatives of state and private sector firms, society groups and members of the press. It originates as a [[Shinto]] rite from at least the 7th century. It is held as a private event by the Imperial Household so that it does not violate the {{ill|Separation of church and state|en|Separation of church and state|qid=Q753623|lt=Separation of church and state|1=Separation of church and state}}. A special complex with over 30 structures (大嘗宮, ''daijōkyū'') is built for the event. Afterward, they are accessible to the public for a few weeks and then dismantled. In 1990, the ritual cost more than 2.7&amp;nbsp;billion yen ($24.7&amp;nbsp;million).&lt;ref name="reiwa-daijo-sai"&gt;{{Cite web |author=Yukihiro Enomoto |title=Japan emperor performs centuries-old succession rite |url=https://asia.nikkei.com/Spotlight/Japan-s-Reiwa-era/Japan-emperor-performs-centuries-old-succession-rite |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200923130825/https://asia.nikkei.com/Spotlight/Japan-s-Reiwa-era/Japan-emperor-performs-centuries-old-succession-rite |archive-date=23 September 2020 |access-date=24 September 2020 |publisher=Nikkei Asian Review|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Daijosai is a highly secret ritual that very few people know the full details of, this has led to controversy with some claiming it violates {{ill|Women's rights|en|Women's rights|qid=Q223569|lt=Women's rights|1=Women's rights}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-11-21 |title=Daijosai ritual: Why Japanese Emperor Naruhito spent a night with the sun goddess |url=https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/explained-daijosai-japanese-emperor-naruhitos-controversial-accession-rite-6125819/ |access-date=2022-04-20 |website=The Indian Express |language=en|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Article 20 of the {{ill|Constitution of Japan|en|Constitution of Japan|qid=Q237082|lt=Japanese constitution|1=Constitution of Japan}}, which separates religion from government.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Jones |first=Colin P. A. |date=2019-12-23 |title=The Reiwa Daijosai: Pomp, circumstance and litigation |url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/community/2019/12/23/issues/reiwa-daijosai-pomp-circumstance-litigation/ |access-date=2023-04-24 |website=The Japan Times |language=en-US|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Overview ==
{{multiple image|direction=horizontal|total_width=360
|image1=Emperor_Akihito,_Daijosai_(1990).jpg |caption1=Akihito (the 125th Emperor) wearing a Haku-Goho (ceremonial robe) at the Omamesai (tasting of the first rice harvest)
|image2=Empress Michiko, Daijosai (1990).jpg |caption2={{ill|Empress Michiko|en|Empress Michiko|qid=Q87610|lt=Michiko|1=Empress Michiko}} wearing a white five-garment Tang costume on the occasion of Meinong's Taemae Festival in 1990.
}}
In general, like the ''[[Niiname-no-Matsuri|Niinamesai]]'', the ''Daijosai'' is understood as an autumn festival of thanksgiving for the harvest. In fact, there are some similarities in the ritual schedule, and in the same year that Omame-sai is held, Niinamesai is not held. Before the {{ill|Taihō Code|en|Taihō Code|qid=Q1059892|lt=Daiho Ritsuryo|1=Taihō Code}}, "Otamesai" and "Shinamesai" were different names for the same ritual.
Since rituals are a secret affair, there have been various discussions about their contents. In the past, the theory of the "bedding over the bedding" advocated by {{ill|Shinobu Orikuchi|en|Shinobu Orikuchi|qid=Q3482286|lt=Orikuchi Nobuo|1=Shinobu Orikuchi}}, that is, a ritual in which the emperor's spirit is put on the new emperor by reproducing the scene of [[Tenson kōrin|Amagasaki]] in [[Japanese mythology]], was proposed. The hypothesis was supported, and research was conducted in the form of development or modification of the hypothesis.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=21|qq=}}　In 1983, Okada Seiji sharply criticized this theory, advocating the rite of holy matrimony, and it gained a certain amount of support in the Japanese historical community.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=22|qq=}}
However, from 1989 to 1990, Shoji Okada published an essay that rejected both the "{{nihongo|makuro-covered bedding|真床覆衾|qq=}}" theory and the sacred marriage rite theory.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=23|qq=}}　According to Okada Shoji's theory, the Omamesai is a simple ritual in which the new emperor welcomes [[Amaterasu]] for the first time, centering on the offering of sacred food and a communal meal ritual.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=23|qq=}}　This view, that the emperor enjoys the divine authority of Amaterasu by enhancing the divine authority of Amaterasu, is consistent with the common view before Orikuchi, as well as the view of {{ill|Middle Ages|en|Middle Ages|qid=Q12554|lt=Middle Ages|1=Middle Ages}} lords such as {{ill|Ichijō Kaneyoshi|en|Ichijō Kaneyoshi|qid=Q1656375|lt=Ichijō Kaneyoshi|1=Ichijō Kaneyoshi}}.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=23|qq=}}　Okada Shoji also noted that the feast of Omameshi-Matsuri is not only to give thanks for the rice harvest, but also for millet, which was an emergency food for the common people in ancient times, and that Omameshi-Matsuri is a prayer for the stability of the people and the prevention of natural disasters that would disturb agriculture. He opined that it is "a prayer for the calming of nature in mountains and rivers" and "the nation's highest ritual to pray for the peace of the nation and its people".&lt;ref name="岡田荘司ほか『大嘗祭』國學院大學博物館（2019）8-9頁"&gt;岡田荘司ほか『大嘗祭』國學院大學博物館（2019）&lt;/ref&gt;
Later, Masahiro Nishimoto introduced a newly published anecdote from "Nairashiki" and its examination has resulted in the almost complete rejection of both the "mashitoko-covering-bedding" theory and the sacred marriage rite theory by the Japanese historical community.{{Sfn|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|p=24|qq=}}
== History ==
The form of the tamesai (= new tasting rice) ceremony was established in the 7th century during the reign of {{ill|Empress Kōgyoku|en|Empress Kōgyoku|qid=Q235296|lt=Empress Kōgyoku|1=Empress Kōgyoku}}, but at that time there was still no distinction between the regular tamesai (= new tasting rice) ceremony and the Jinsō tamesai ceremony. The first time that a ceremony of a different scale was held in addition to the regular Omamesai was during the reign of {{ill|Emperor Tenmu|en|Emperor Tenmu|qid=Q335181|lt=Emperor Tenmu|1=Emperor Tenmu}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=大嘗祭｜皇位継承式典 平成から令和へ 新時代の幕開け |url=https://www3.nhk.or.jp/news/special/japans-emperor6/articles/articles_ceremony_05.html |access-date=28 November 2019 |website=NHK NEWS WEB|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;　However, at that time, it was not yet a once-in-a-generation event associated with accession to the throne, but was held several times during the reign.&lt;ref&gt;斎忌（悠紀国）と次（主基国）とその[[卜定]]について史上初めて言及されるのは『日本書紀』巻第29のEmperor Tenmu5th year の[[相嘗祭]]と新嘗祭に関してであるが、即位後最初の大嘗祭はEmperor Tenmu2nd year に既に行われている. &lt;/ref&gt; With the establishment of the Ritsuryo system, the festival was named the "Shansho Otamesai" as a once-in-a-generation ritual, and the details of the ceremony, including the ritual procedures, were also established. Of the ceremonial rites stipulated in the [[:en:Engi-Shiki|Engi-Shiki]], only the Omamesai was designated as a "daisai" (ritual of the Great Taste of Rice). The name "Dajo-e" was derived from the fact that a three-day long festival was held after the tasting of the first taro.&lt;ref&gt;小山田義夫「大嘗会役小考」（『一国平均役と中世社会』（岩田書院、2008th year ） {{ISBN|978-4-87294-504-1|qq=}}（原論文は1976th year ））&lt;/ref&gt;　Later on, the ordinary tamesai (= new tamesai) was sometimes referred to as "the annual tamesai" and the practice of tamesai as "the tamesai of every generation". Originally, in the Chronicles of Japan, the tame and the new tame were neither referred to as "festival" nor "assembly. They are simply described as "ote" and "shintame. In the Nara period (710–794), they were called "Otame-kai" and "Shintame-kai," and in the Heian period (794–1185), they were officially called "Otamesai" and "Shintamesai," but in most diaries, "Otamesai" and "Shintame-kai" are used. This indicates that one of the most important components of the tasting of taro and the tasting of shin-tame was the "meeting".&lt;ref&gt;『神社のいろは用語集　祭祀編』、[[Association of Shinto Shrines|神社本庁]]監修 p.271 {{ISBN|978-4-594-07193-6|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, in the late [[:en:Muromachi Period|Muromachi Period]] and the [[:en:Sengoku Period|Sengoku Period]], the shogunate was weakened by warfare, and the imperial court became impoverished, which hampered the imperial rites. The tame festival was held until 1466, the first year of {{ill|Emperor Go-Tsuchimikado|en|Emperor Go-Tsuchimikado|qid=Q380623|lt=Emperor Go-Tsuchimikado|1=Emperor Go-Tsuchimikado}}'s reign, but after the outbreak of the [[:en:Onin War|Onin War]] the following year, it became impossible to collect temporary expenses (tame-kaiyaku). For more than a year, he was forced to abort. In August 1545, {{ill|Emperor Go-Nara|en|Emperor Go-Nara|qid=Q349467|lt=Emperor Go-Nara|1=Emperor Go-Nara}} wrote a decree to the Ise Jingu Shrine to pray for the restoration of the imperial family and the people, and at the same time to apologize for the inability to hold the tame-matsuri ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;[[岡田荘司]]、『大嘗祭と古代の祭祀』あとがきに続く「大嘗祭の年表」p.3 ISBN 978-4-642-08350-8&lt;/ref&gt;
After domestic stability was restored by the Oryoho regime and the Tokugawa Shogunate, there was a period of time when the tasting of the tithes was not practiced, but {{ill|Emperor Reigen|en|Emperor Reigen|qid=Q313808|lt=Emperor Reigen|1=Emperor Reigen}} was intent on reviving the imperial rites, and first restored the rite of the Crown Prince Asahito in 1683, the first time in approximately 340 years. In 1684, the Emperor wished to transfer the throne to the Crown Prince and to restore the Great Tamesai Ceremony, and had the Shogunate negotiate with the Emperor. At that time, he explained in the form of a precedent that the tame-matsuri should be held upon the accession of the crown prince to the throne. The Shogunate, which had been at loggerheads with the Imperial Court due to the Murasaki Incident and other events, was reluctant to request the same ceremonial protocol as in the previous case (when Emperor Reigen ascended to the throne), but after negotiations, the reestablishment was approved on condition that the entire budget for the succession to the throne be paid in the same amount as in the previous case. In 1687, the emperor abdicated and the crown prince acceded to the throne (Emperor Higashiyama), and the Great Taste of Rice Ceremony was held for the first time in 221 years. However, due to budgetary constraints, the reconstruction was a shortened version at this point.
When the next generation {{ill|Emperor Nakamikado|en|Emperor Nakamikado|qid=Q314817|lt=Emperor Nakamikado|1=Emperor Nakamikado}} succeeded to the throne, Daijosai was not held. This is attributed to the pledge during the reign of Emperor Reigen. At the time of the succession to the throne of {{ill|Emperor Sakuramachi|en|Emperor Sakuramachi|qid=Q313870|lt=Emperor Sakuramachi|1=Emperor Sakuramachi}}, the imperial court initially declined the offer from the shogunate side, but eventually the imperial court side revived [[Niiname-no-Matsuri]]. There was an offer, and after negotiations between the imperial courts, the Daijosai was held again in 1738,{{efn|From the following year, the Shinmame Festival was also held every year.|qq=}} three years after the succession to the throne, and after that, the Daijosai was held without interruption every time it was replaced. It came to be done.{{Sfn|古相|pp=74–75|qq=}}
From the {{ill|Nara period|en|Nara period|qid=Q189178|lt=Nara era|1=Nara period}} to the {{ill|Heian period|en|Heian period|qid=Q193292|lt=Heian era|1=Heian period}} of the {{ill|Emperor Heizei|en|Emperor Heizei|qid=Q353558|lt=Heijo|1=Emperor Heizei}}, the site for the Taimae Ceremony was the Ryuo-dan garden in the front yard of Chodoin, located in the southern center of the {{ill|Heian Palace|en|Heian Palace|qid=Q304501|lt=Ouchiura|1=Heian Palace}}. The first two are the first two. After the burning down of Chodoin at the end of the Heian period, it was still built roughly on the former site of Daigoku-den, under the Ryuo-dan. During the reign of {{ill|Emperor Antoku|en|Emperor Antoku|qid=Q316651|lt=Emperor Antoku|1=Emperor Antoku}}, the capital was temporarily relocated to {{ill|Fukuhara-kyō|en|Fukuhara-kyō|qid=Q6031707|lt=Fukuhara-kyō|1=Fukuhara-kyō}} and was postponed due to the death of {{ill|Emperor Takakura|en|Emperor Takakura|qid=Q357261|lt=Emperor Takakura|1=Emperor Takakura}}, but was finally moved to {{ill|Emperor Go-Shirakawa|en|Emperor Go-Shirakawa|qid=Q317984|lt=Emperor Go-Shirakawa|1=Emperor Go-Shirakawa}} by the ruling of {{ill|Emperor Shirakawa|en|Emperor Shirakawa|qid=Q60949|lt=Emperor Shirakawa|1=Emperor Shirakawa}}. The ceremony was held in 1182 (Juei 1), but due to the current circumstances, including the {{ill|Genpei War|en|Genpei War|qid=Q737542|lt=Genpei War|1=Genpei War}} (Genpei War), it was held at Shikikakuden. {{Sfn|加瀬|pp=58–59|qq=}}　When {{ill|Emperor Higashiyama|en|Emperor Higashiyama|qid=Q313801|lt=Emperor Higashiyama|1=Emperor Higashiyama}} was reestablished, perhaps because the site of Daigoku-den was not yet clear, he followed the precedent set by Emperor Antoku and used the forecourt of Shikikakuden, leading to the {{ill|Meiji era|en|Meiji era|qid=Q3125096|lt=Meiji|1=Meiji era}} period. In the Meiji period (1868–1912), the accession ceremony was held in Shikikinden, but the tamesai ceremony was held at the Fukiage Palace in Tokyo. During the {{ill|Taishō era|en|Taishō era|qid=Q329174|lt=Taishō|1=Taishō era}} and {{ill|Shōwa era|en|Shōwa era|qid=Q327567|lt=Shōwa|1=Shōwa era}} eras, the former {{ill|Sentō Imperial Palace|en|Sentō Imperial Palace|qid=Q909444|lt=Sentō Gosho|1=Sentō Imperial Palace}} in the {{ill|Ōmiya Palace|en|Ōmiya Palace|qid=Q3891686|lt=Omiya Gosho|1=Ōmiya Palace}} in Kyoto was used under the "Togoku Order". Since the Heisei era, the ceremony has again been held at the East Gardens of the Imperial Palace in Tokyo.
* During the {{ill|Edo period|en|Edo period|qid=Q184963|lt=Edo period|1=Edo period}}, the Emperor decided to follow the old ways and forbid {{ill|Buddhism|en|Buddhism|qid=Q748|lt=Buddhism|1=Buddhism}} {{ill|Sangha|en|Sangha|qid=Q193944|lt=Sangha|1=Sangha}} {{ill|Bhikkhunī|en|Bhikkhunī|qid=Q854979|lt=Bhikkhunī|1=Bhikkhunī}} to enter the palace and remove the [[Spirit tablet|title]] of successive emperors. {{ill|Emperor Reigen|en|Emperor Reigen|qid=Q313808|lt=Reigen|1=Emperor Reigen}} and {{ill|Regent|en|Regent|qid=Q477406|lt=Regent|1=Regent}} {{ill|Ichijō Kaneteru|en|Ichijō Kaneteru|qid=Q3072989|lt=Ichijō Fuyūketsu|1=Ichijō Kaneteru}} (Kaneteru), who opposed the Emperor's brother, Prince Gyōjo, and {{ill|Minister of the Left|en|Minister of the Left|qid=Q949008|lt=Minister of the Left|1=Minister of the Left}} {{ill|Konoe Motohiro|en|Konoe Motohiro|qid=Q922862|lt=Konoe Motohiro|1=Konoe Motohiro}} Hui and others were at odds with each other. This movement to exclude Buddhism was reinforced each time the new emperor held the first Grand Tasting Ceremony, in conjunction with the rise of {{ill|Kokugaku|en|Kokugaku|qid=Q855159|lt=Kokugaku|1=Kokugaku}} and the theory of the reverence for the emperor, which led to criticism of the long-established court practice of [[Shinbutsu-shūgō|shimbutsu shugō]] and to debates about the pros and cons of the exclusion of Buddhism and its attendant enthronement ceremony. Some believe that it developed into a distant cause of the [[Shinbutsu bunri|Separation of Shinto and Buddhism]] at the Imperial Court in the Meiji period.&lt;ref&gt;山口和夫「神仏習合と近世天皇の祭祀」（初出：島薗進 他編『シリーズ日本人と宗教1 将軍と天皇』（春秋社、2014th year ）/所収：山口『近世日本政治史と朝廷』（吉川弘文館、2017th year ） ISBN 978-4-642-03480-7 P352-356）&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the {{ill|Ōei|en|Ōei|qid=Q1193078|lt=Ōei|1=Ōei}} Taimeikai (Records of the Great Tasting Ceremony) written by {{ill|Ichijō Tsunetsugu|en|Ichijō Tsunetsugu|qid=Q3147660|lt=Ichijō Tsunetsugu|1=Ichijō Tsunetsugu}} in the Muromachi period, it is written that "The national event is the Taimeikai, and the event is no more than a Shinto meal", and in the {{ill|Eiwa|en|Eiwa|qid=Q1145780|lt=Eiwa|1=Eiwa}} Taimeikai, it is written that only the emperor and his attendants may enter the temple (Taimekiya). However, in the historical background of the period when young emperors between the ages of two and seven continued from {{ill|Emperor Horikawa|en|Emperor Horikawa|qid=Q464267|lt=Emperor Horikawa|1=Emperor Horikawa}} to Emperor Antoku and {{ill|Emperor Go-Toba|en|Emperor Go-Toba|qid=Q316658|lt=Emperor Go-Toba|1=Emperor Go-Toba}}, we can see "Nigyo" and "Gode" in Oe Masafusa's "Eke Yadai" and "Enkei Datame Ki" and "Go-Toba" in the "Enkei Datame Ki" and "Go-Toba". If the emperor was 10 years of age or older (an adult who had reached the age of full age), as described in the "Oei Taiteki," the emperor himself offered the "Nigyo" service, and if the emperor was 9 years of age or younger, the regent offered the "Gode" service. In addition, a few days before the Omame-sai, a preliminary ritual of the offering of the offering of the offering of the offering of the food to the gods is held.&lt;ref&gt;安江和宣『大嘗祭神饌御供進儀の研究』p.25&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ceremonies related to the coronation ceremony were designated as national events, while the ceremonies related to the Daijosai were designated as imperial events. It is often misunderstood that "imperial event" here does not mean "private event of the imperial family" but "public event of the imperial family". The budget for Daijosai is extraordinary, other than the usual court fees. According to the government announcement (final answer) at that time, the reason why Daijosai was not regarded as "state affairs" is that the emperor's "state affairs" under the Constitution of Japan requires "advice and approval of the Cabinet". This is because the Daijosai, which is a traditional ritual of the imperial family, does not fall under the Category:11]]
[[Category of "state affairs."
== Details ==
First, two special [[:en:Rice paddies|Rice paddies]] (斎田, ''saiden'') are chosen and purified by elaborate [[Shinto]] purification rites. The families of the farmers who are to cultivate the rice in these paddies must be in perfect health. Once the rice is grown and harvested, it is stored in a special Shinto shrine as its ''go-shintai'' (御神体), the embodiment of a [[kami]] or divine force. Each kernel must be whole and unbroken, and is individually polished before it is boiled. Some [[sake]] is also brewed from this rice. The two sets of rice seedlings now blessed each come from the western and eastern prefectures of Japan, and the chosen rice from these is assigned from a designated prefecture each in the west and east of the country, respectively.
Two [[:en:Thatched roof|Thatched roof]] two-room [[:en:Hut (dwelling)|huts]] (悠紀殿 ''yukiden,'' lit. East-region hall) and (主基殿 ''sukiden,'' lit. West-region hall) are built within a corresponding special enclosure, using a native Japanese building style that predates and is thus devoid of all [[:en:Culture of China|Chinese]] cultural influence. The Yukiden and Sukiden represent the east and west halves of Japan, respectively. Each hall is divided into two rooms, with one room containing a large {{ill|Couch|en|Couch|qid=Q131514|lt=Couch|1=Couch}} made of tatami mats at its center, in addition to a seat for the emperor and a place to enshrine the kami; the second is used by musicians. All furniture and household items also preserve these earliest, and thus most purely Japanese forms: e.g., all {{ill|Pottery|en|Pottery|qid=Q11642|lt=Pottery|1=Pottery}} objects are fired but unglazed. These two structures represent the house of the preceding emperor and that of the new emperor. In earlier times, when the head of a household died his house was burned; before the founding of {{ill|Kyoto|en|Kyoto|qid=Q34600|lt=Kyoto|1=Kyoto}}, whenever an emperor died his entire capital city was burned as a rite of purification. As in the earlier ceremony, the two houses represent housing styles from western and eastern parts of Japan. Since 1990, the temporary enclosure is located at the eastern grounds of the Imperial Palace complex.
[[File:Igimono1.JPG|thumb|Ritual items from the enthronement of the Japanese emperor]]
=== Ceremony day ===
This ceremony, also known as ''O-ni-e-matsuri'' (大嘗祭) and ''O-name-matsuri'' (大嘗まつり (大嘗祭) is marked as an Imperial court ritual performed by the Emperor of Japan upon his succession to the throne, and is an [[Ritual ceremonies of the Imperial Palace|Imperial Household Ritual]]. In olden times, it was also called "Ohonimatsuri" or "Ohonamatsuri".&lt;ref&gt;[[井原頼明]]『皇室事典』[[冨山房]]、1943rd year 、[{{NDLDC|1908898/63|qq=}} 8ページ]&lt;/ref&gt; In modern times, however, it is read phonetically as "Daijosai".&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.kunaicho.go.jp/word/word-sokui.html ご即位・立太子・成年に関する用語] [[宮内庁]]ホームページ（2019th year 6月4日閲覧）.&lt;/ref&gt;
After a ritual {{ill|Bathing|en|Bathing|qid=Q327651|lt=bath|1=Bathing}} on the night of the ceremony, the emperor is dressed entirely in the white silk dress of a Shinto priest, but with a special long train. Surrounded by {{ill|Courtier|en|Courtier|qid=Q1511216|lt=Courtier|1=Courtier}}s (some of them carrying torches), the emperor solemnly enters first the enclosure and then each of these huts in turn and performs the same ritual—from 6:30 to 9:30&amp;nbsp;pm in the first, and in the second from 12:30 to 3:30&amp;nbsp;am on the same night. A {{ill|Mat|en|Mat|qid=Q1136834|lt=Mat|1=Mat}} is unrolled before him and then rolled up again as he walks, so that his feet never touch the ground. A special {{ill|Umbrella|en|Umbrella|qid=Q41607|lt=Umbrella|1=Umbrella}} is held over the sovereign's head, in which the shade hangs from a phoenix carved at the end of the pole and prevents any defilement of his sacred person coming from the air above him. Kneeling on a {{ill|Mat|en|Mat|qid=Q1136834|lt=Mat|1=Mat}} situated to face the [[:en:Grand Shrine of Ise|Grand Shrine of Ise]], as the traditional [[gagaku]] court music is played by the court orchestra the emperor makes an offering of the sacred rice, the sake made from this rice, {{ill|Millet|en|Millet|qid=Q259438|lt=Millet|1=Millet}}, fish and a variety of other foods from both the land and the sea to the kami, the offerings of east and west being made in their corresponding halls. Then he eats some of this sacred rice himself, as an act of divine communion that consummates his singular unity with Amaterasu-ōmikami, thus making him (in Shinto tradition) the {{ill|intermediary|en|intermediary|qid=Q1666223|lt=intermediary|1=Intermediary}} between Amaterasu and the Japanese people.  The significance of the offerings and the ceremonial dinner of the tithes is as an act of thanksgiving to Amaterasu and {{ill|Kami#Amatsukami and Kunitsukami|lt=Tenjin Jigami|ja|天神地祇|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kami#Amatsukami and Kunitsukami|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 天津神・国津神|1=Kami#Amatsukami_and_Kunitsukami|lt=Amatsukami and Kunitsukami|2=ja|3=天津神・国津神|4=zh|5=天津神與國津神6=ko|7=아마쓰카미·구니쓰카미}}, the ancestors of the Emperor, and as a prayer for the nation and its people's peace and good harvests in his reign.{{Sfn|鎌田|p=178|qq=}} He then prays to the gods in gratitude, and then leaves the huts so that the Empress may then performs the same ceremonial protocol there before departing the complex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Schoenberger |first=Karl |date=23 November 1990 |title=Akihito in Final Ritual of Passage |work=Los Angeles Times |url=https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-11-23-mn-5212-story.html |access-date=2 May 2010|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Controversies of the Daijosai ==
=== Relationship to the Constitution's principle of separation of church and state ===
Some members of the public, including {{ill|Christianity|en|Christianity|qid=Q5043|lt=Christian|1=Christianity}} and {{ill|Buddhism|en|Buddhism|qid=Q748|lt=Buddhist|1=Buddhism}} officials, are of the opinion that government spending on the Omameshi-Matsuri and the participation of [[Governor (Japan)|prefectural governors]] in the Omameshi-Matsuri are unconstitutional due the [[:en:Japanese Constitution|Constitution's]] principle of a separation of church and state.&lt;ref&gt;[[金子勝 (法学者)|金子勝]]『日本国憲法の原理と「国家改造構想」』1994th year &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2018-11-30 |title=全国２２０人：「大嘗祭は違憲」１２月１０日に提訴へ |url=https://mainichi.jp/articles/20181201/k00/00m/040/087000c |website=毎日新聞 |publisher= |accessdate=1 September 2019|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some {{ill|Constitutional lawsuits|ja|憲法訴訟|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Constitutional lawsuits|1=constitutional litigation|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q11495259}} have been filed from the viewpoint of this separation of church and state, but all the lawsuits have been dismissed. These {{ill|plaintiff|en|plaintiff|qid=Q468489|lt=plaintiff|1=Plaintiff}}s were defeated due to the judgment that the expenditure of state funds did not disadvantage the plaintiffs and that the governors' attendance did not violate the separation of church and state in light of the purpose-effect standard of the separation of church and state&lt;ref name="kantei2"&gt;[https://www.kantei.go.jp/jp/singi/taii_junbi/dai2/siryou6.pdf 平成の御代替わりに伴う儀式に関する最高裁判決]&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the decision of the Japanese Supreme Court in July 1977, "The separation of church and state in the Constitution does not mean that the state is not allowed to have relations with religion at all, but that it is not allowed when it is deemed to exceed reasonable limits. It does not allow the state to have relations with religion at all, but only in cases where such relations are deemed to exceed reasonable limits." This is one of the reasons why the government has approved the expenditure of government funds for the Omameshigai.&lt;ref name="kantei2"/&gt; However, in 1995, the {{ill|Osaka High Court|ja|大阪高裁|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Osaka High Court|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 大阪高等裁判所|1=Ōsaka High Court|comment=changed title based on wikidata|qid=Q74996}} rejected the plaintiff's lawsuit, stating that "the tasting of the Heisei era has already been completed and the plaintiff is not disadvantaged," but in a side argument, the court pointed out that "the suspicion of a violation of the Constitution cannot be denied in general."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.courts.go.jp/app/hanrei_jp/detail5?id=16367 即位の礼・大嘗祭国費支出差止等請求控訴事件] 裁判所&lt;/ref&gt;
On 10 December 2018, 241 plaintiffs filed a lawsuit against the government in the Tokyo District Court seeking an injunction to stop the government from spending money and compensation for damages on the grounds that the implementation of the "Rei (retirement)", "Sokui-no-rei (enthronement)", and "Taitei-Matsuri (tasting of rice)" ceremonies following the abdication of Emperor {{ill|Akihito|en|Akihito|qid=Q37979|lt=Akihito|1=Akihito}} and accession of Crown Prince {{ill|Naruhito|en|Naruhito|qid=Q217096|lt=Naruhito|1=Naruhito}}, under the provisions of the Special Act on the Imperial Household Law concerning the Abdication of the Emperor, violates the Constitutional provision stipulating separation of church and state.
=== Expenses and facilities ===
==== Opinions of the Emperor and members of the Imperial Family ====
[[:en:Emperor Shōwa|Emperor Shōwa]] reportedly told his aides that they should save and accumulate the money for the inner court.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-10-23 |title=（社説）即位の礼 前例踏襲が残した課題 |url=https://www.asahi.com/articles/DA3S14228225.html |access-date=30 November 2019 |website=朝日新聞デジタル|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{ill|Nobuhito, Prince Takamatsu|en|Nobuhito, Prince Takamatsu|qid=Q1030368|lt=Nobuhito, Prince Takamatsu|1=Nobuhito, Prince Takamatsu}} once suggested, "Why don't we just do it at the [[Three Palace Sanctuaries]], where the annual [[Niiname-no-Matsuri|Niinamesai]] is held, without building a large daijokyu?" &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-01-09 |title=続く皇室からの発信 雅子さまに触れなかった意図は？ |url=https://dot.asahi.com/wa/2019010800044.html?page=1 |work=wezzy |accessdate=30 November 2019|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
If {{ill|Fumihito, Crown Prince of Japan|en|Fumihito, Crown Prince of Japan|qid=Q311174|lt=Prince Fumihito Akishino|1=Fumihito, Crown Prince of Japan}} were to become emperor, he has proposed a plan similar to that of Prince Takamatsu, that the expenses for the Daijosai be paid from the national budget, and that they be covered by the expenses of the Imperial Court by utilizing the Shinkaden, a smaller building near the Three Palace Sanctuaries used for the ordinary Niinamesai.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=25 December 2018 |title=私費で賄う大嘗祭、秋篠宮さま自ら提案 既存の神殿活用 |url=https://digital.asahi.com/articles/ASLD561DXLD5UTIL050.html |access-date=29 January 2019 |website=朝日新聞デジタル|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-01-10 |title=「"貯金"のできる内廷費でやりたい」が皇族がたの本音？ 27億円の国費を投じる大嘗祭と、"国事行為"たる即位の礼が持つ意味 |url=https://wezz-y.com/archives/62736 |access-date=30 November 2019 |website=wezzy|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==== Budget, construction, and changes in the Reiwa era ====
The government and the Imperial Household Agency followed the precedent of the Heisei era and spent money from the national budget, but changed the roof of the daijokyu, which had previously been {{ill|Thatching|en|Thatching|qid=Q874531|lt=Thatching|1=Thatching}}, to {{ill|Roof shingle|en|Roof shingle|qid=Q2227106|lt=shingles|1=Roof shingle}}, and reduced expenses by building some facilities such as the kashiwaya (kitchens for the offerings of food to be prepared in) in reinforced concrete under the premise that it was acceptable as long as it didn't alter the rituals or serve as an impediment to them. The original planned construction cost of the daijokyu was 1.97 billion yen,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=多田晃子 |date=21 December 2018 |title=大嘗宮の設営費、4億円増え19億円に 儀式後には解体 |url=https://digital.asahi.com/articles/ASLDN66QWLDNUTIL05H.html |access-date=29 January 2019 |website=朝日新聞デジタル|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; actually in 2019 (the first year of the 2025 {{ill|Shimizu Corporation|en|Shimizu Corporation|qid=Q7496874|lt=Shimizu Corporation|1=Shimizu Corporation}} won the bid for 957 million yen, 60% of the planned price, in a competitive bidding process held at the Imperial Household Agency on 10 May 2019.
On the occasion of the Heisei Daijosai, the East Gardens of the Imperial Palace were completely closed as an anti-terrorist measure during the construction of the Imperial Palace, due to the active anti-emperor {{ill|Extremism|en|Extremism|qid=Q466439|lt=extremist|1=Extremism}} movement at the time, and once completed, the main buildings were covered with large protective tents of extremely solid construction, and four 2,500-liter Fire prevention tanks and fire pumps were installed in four locations. In contrast, the East Palace Garden was not closed during the 2021 Daijosai, and the construction of the daijokyu was open for all to see, in order to "deepen the public's understanding of the expenditure of national funds for the Daijosai."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=INC |first=SANKEI DIGITAL |date=26 July 2019 |title=大嘗宮建設中に東御苑公開 大嘗祭へ理解促す 警備に工夫も |url=https://www.sankei.com/life/news/190726/lif1907260017-n1.html |access-date=1 September 2019 |website=産経ニュース |language=ja|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;　It was also decided that after the Daijosai, the daijokyu would remain open to the public as it had been during construction, and that materials would be reused after dismantling.
== See also ==
* [[:en:Saiten|Saiten]]
* [[Festival of the Deva and Naraka]]
* [[:en:Sacrifice to Taishan|Sacrifice to Taishan]]
* {{ill|Secular Games|en|Secular Games|qid=Q739680|lt=Secular Games|1=Secular Games}}
== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery class="center" mode="packed" heights="170" caption="Daijosai"&gt;
File:Heisei-Daijōkyu.jpg|Scale model of the Heisei era daijokyu, built in 1990
File:Prince Morimasa.png|{{ill|Prince Nashimoto Morimasa|en|Prince Nashimoto Morimasa|qid=Q339595|lt=Prince Nashimoto Morimasa|1=Prince Nashimoto Morimasa}} at {{ill|Emperor Taishō|en|Emperor Taishō|qid=Q157052|lt=Emperor Taishō|1=Emperor Taishō}}'s ceremony
File:Enthronement of Emperor Hirohito 10sen.JPG|The daijokyu, where the festival was held, depicted on a postage stamp commemorating the Emperor Showa's accession and Daijosai.
File:朱塗剣璽案.png|A table in red lacquer for holding the sword and jewel of the [[:en:Three Sacred Treasures|Imperial regalia]]
File:御椅子.png|Imperial throne
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery class="center" mode="packed" heights="130"&gt;
File:風俗舞（悠紀地方）.jpg|Traditional dancing of eastern Japan, performed during the rituals in the Yukiden.
File:風俗舞（主基地方）.jpg|Traditional dancing of western Japan, performed during the rituals in the Sukiden.
File:錦軟障（にしきのぜじよう）.png|Kinshitsu Kakusa (from the Showa Tairekiroku)
&lt;/gallery&gt;
== Notes ==
{{notelist|qq=}}
== References ==
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== Bibliography ==
* 田中初夫『践祚大嘗祭』木耳社、1983rd year 
* 岡田精司編『大嘗祭と新嘗』学生社、1979th year 、復刊1989th year （特に折口信夫「大嘗祭の本義」）
* {{ill|Shinobu Orikuchi|en|Shinobu Orikuchi|qid=Q3482286|lt=折口信夫|1=Shinobu Orikuchi}}『古代研究II　[[Norito|祝詞]]の発生』中公クラシックス、2003rd year 。上記を収録
** 『古代研究III　民俗学篇3』角川ソフィア文庫、2017th year 。上記を収録
** 『大嘗祭の本義　民俗学からみた大嘗祭』森田勇造現代語訳、三和書籍、2019th year 
* 吉野裕子『天皇の祭り』講談社学術文庫、2000th year 
* 岡田荘司『大嘗祭と古代の祭祀』 吉川弘文館、2019th year 3月 ISBN 978-4-642-08350-8
* {{Cite journal |last=[[加瀬直弥]] |date=25 July 2019 |title=中世の大嘗祭 |journal=季刊 悠久 |location=東京都千代田区 |publisher=おうふう |volume= |issue=158 |issn=0388-6433 |ref={{SfnRef|加瀬|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=[[福羽美静]] |title=硯堂叢書 |publisher=八尾書店 |year=1895 |ref={{SfnRef|福羽|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=鈴木暢幸、小松悦二 |title=御即位式大典録 後編 |publisher=御即位大典紀念会 |year=1915 |ref={{SfnRef|鈴木、小松|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=大礼記録編纂委員会 |title=昭和大礼要録 |publisher=内閣印刷局 |year=1931 |ref={{SfnRef|大礼記録編纂委員会|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=[[鎌田純一]] |title=即位禮・大嘗祭 平成大禮要話 |publisher=[[錦正社]] |year=2003 |isbn=4-7646-0262-8 |ref={{SfnRef|鎌田|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite journal |last=[[加茂正典]] |date=25 July 2019 |title=古代の大嘗祭 |journal=季刊 悠久 |location=東京都千代田区 |publisher=おうふう |volume= |issue=158 |issn=0388-6433 |ref={{SfnRef|加茂|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=[[小倉慈司]]・[[山口輝臣]] |title=天皇の歴史９：天皇と宗教 |date=2018th year  |publisher=[[講談社]] |isbn=978-4065126714 |series=[[講談社学術文庫]] |ref={{SfnRef|小倉・山口（2018th year ）|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite journal |last=[[武田秀章]] |date=25 July 2019 |title=近現代の大嘗祭 |journal=季刊 悠久 |location=東京都千代田区 |publisher=おうふう |volume= |issue=158 |issn=0388-6433 |ref={{SfnRef|武田|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite journal |last=[[古相正美]] |date=25 July 2019 |title=大嘗祭の中絶と復興 |journal=季刊 悠久 |location=東京都千代田区 |publisher=おうふう |volume= |issue=158 |issn=0388-6433 |ref={{SfnRef|古相|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=[[真弓常忠]] |title=大嘗祭 |publisher=[[ちくま学芸文庫]] |year=2019 |isbn=978-4-480-09919-8 |ref={{SfnRef|真弓|2019a|qq=}}|qq=}}
* {{Cite book |last=[[真弓常忠]] |title=大嘗祭の世界 &lt;small&gt;新版&lt;/small&gt; |date=April 2019 |publisher=[[学生社]] |isbn=978-4-311-80128-0 |ref={{SfnRef|真弓|2019b|qq=}}|qq=}}
* 安江和宣『大嘗祭神饌御供進儀の研究』神社新報社、2019th year 5月。ISBN 978-4-908128-23-3
== External links ==
* {{Cite web |date=2005 |title=皇位の継承に係わる儀式等（大嘗祭を中心に）について（皇室典範に関する有識者会議（第8回）配付資料） |url=https://www.kantei.go.jp/jp/singi/kousitu/dai8/8siryou3.pdf |access-date=24 May 2018 |publisher=首相官邸 |qq=}}



[[en:Daijosai]]

&lt;!-- not reviewed yet--&gt;
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{Commons category|Daijō-sai}}
[[de:Daijō-sai]]
[[fa:دایجوسای]]
[[fr:Daijosai]]
[[ja:大嘗祭]]
[[ru:Дайдзёсай]]
[[th:ไดโจไซ]]
{{wikidata link|Q11433653}}
[[Category:Japanese Imperial Rituals]]
[[Category:November]]
[[Category:Shinto festivals]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]
[[Category:Enthronement ceremony]]
[[Category:旧暦11月]]
[[Category:皇位継承]]
[[Category:Pages with 50+ untranslated japanese characters]]
[[Category:Pages with 100+ untranslated japanese characters]]
[[Category:Pages with 150+ untranslated japanese characters]]
[[Category:Pages with 200+ untranslated japanese characters]]</text>
      <sha1>kuj71sp2sqokyfjy1tgf2s1ygt5zw8d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
