<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Heijō Palace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3596204</id>
      <parentid>3594305</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T20:05:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Sn crud]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23985667504|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3596204</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="27176" sha1="c0417ojgce2cekpyua4rhqyo10p723z" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[af:Heijō Paleis]][[ca:Palau Heijō]][[cs:Palác Heidžó]][[el:Ανάκτορο Χεϊτζό]][[en:Heijō Palace]][[es:Palacio Heijō]][[fa:کاخ هیجو]][[fr:Palais Heijō]][[hr:Carska palača u Nari]][[id:Istana Heijō]][[it:Palazzo Heijō]][[ja:平城宮]][[ko:헤이조궁]][[pt:Palácio Heijō]][[sh:Carska palača u Nari]][[sl:Palača Heidžo]][[tr:Heijō Sarayı]][[wuu:平城宫]][[zh-yue:平城宮]][[zh:平城宫]]


{{Short description|Imperial residence in Nara, Japan}}
{{more citations needed|date=August 2016}}

[[File:Heijokyo - Map of major buildings.png|thumb|Map of the major sites of Heijō-kyō, with the palace to the north]]
[[File:200730 Model of the main part of Heijō Palace.jpg|thumb|250px|A model of the main part of Heijō Palace, a part of the Heijōkyō 1/1000 model held by Nara City Hall. &lt;br/&gt;View from the north.]]
'''{{nihongo|Heijō Palace|平城宮|Heijō-kyū}}''' was the imperial residence in the Japanese capital city [[Heijō-kyō]] (today's {{ill|Nara (city)|en|Nara (city)|qid=Q169134|lt=Nara|1=Nara (city)}}), during most of the {{ill|Nara period|en|Nara period|qid=Q189178|lt=Nara period|1=Nara period}}. The palace, which served as the imperial residence and the administrative centre of for most of the Nara period from 710 to 794 AD, was located at the north-central location of the city in accordance with the {{ill|China|en|China|qid=Q148|lt=Chinese|1=China}} models used for the design of the capital.

The palace consisted of a {{nihongo||大内裏|'''daidairi'''|also pronounced ''taidairi''}}, a large rectangular walled enclosure which contained several ceremonial and administrative buildings including the government ministries. Inside this enclosure was the separately walled [[#Inner Palace (Dairi)|residential compound]] of the {{ill|Emperor of Japan|en|Emperor of Japan|qid=Q208233|lt=emperor|1=Emperor of Japan}} or the ''Inner Palace''. In addition to the emperor's living quarters the Inner Palace contained the residences of the imperial consorts as well as certain official and ceremonial buildings more closely linked to the person of the emperor.

The original role of the palace was to manifest the centralised government model adopted by Japan from China in the 7th century—the ''[[Daijō-kan]]'' and its subsidiary Eight Ministries.  The palace was designed to provide an appropriate setting for the emperor's residence, the conduct of state affairs, and associated ceremonial functions.

After the capital was moved to Heian, the palace structures were either moved there or suffered several fires and other disasters and disappeared. The site was converted to agricultural use and almost no trace of it remained, however the location was still known. Excavations started in the {{decade|1970}} and large-scale reconstruction based on contemporary literary sources and excavations starting in the {{decade|2000}}.

The excavated remains of the palace and the surrounding area were established as a {{ill|UNESCO|en|UNESCO|qid=Q7809|lt=UNESCO|1=UNESCO}} {{ill|World Heritage Site|en|World Heritage Site|qid=Q9259|lt=World Heritage Site|1=World Heritage Site}} in 1998 along with a number of other buildings in the area such as the "{{ill|Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara|en|Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara|qid=Q1055749|lt=Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara|1=Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara}}."

== History ==
[[File:Miniature Model of Heijo Palace Daigokuden.jpg|thumb|Miniature model of the former imperial audience hall compound]]
[[File:Heijokyo Choshuden (edit).jpg|thumb|Miniature model of the east assembly hall (''Choshu-den'') of the latter imperial audience hall compound]]
One year after {{ill|Empress Genmei|en|Empress Genmei|qid=Q233224|lt=Empress Genmei|1=Empress Genmei}}'s succession to the {{ill|Chrysanthemum Throne|en|Chrysanthemum Throne|qid=Q1981690|lt=Chrysanthemum Throne|1=Chrysanthemum Throne}} in {{ill|Keiun|en|Keiun|qid=Q428753|lt=Keiun 4|1=Keiun}}  (707 AD), a rescript was issued deciding on the move from [[:en:Fujiwara-kyo|Fujiwara-kyo]] near Asuka towards the northern edge of the Nara basin.&lt;ref name="Hashimoto_1954" /&gt;{{rp|pages=27,207–224,233–270}} In {{ill|Wadō (era)|en|Wadō (era)|qid=Q1373026|lt=Wadō 3|1=Wadō (era)}} (710 AD), the new capital was officially established, but the completion of the palace had to wait further.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Research Institute for Cultural Properties|url=http://www.nabunken.go.jp/|access-date = 2007-03-09|df=dmy-all}} Navigate to English page from top menu bar&lt;/ref&gt; The new capital city's name was written Heijō ({{lang|ja|平城}}) but also pronounced Nara at the time.

The city, and the palace grounds, was based largely on {{ill|Chang&amp;#39;an|en|Chang&amp;#39;an|qid=Q6501000|lt=Chang&amp;#39;an|1=Chang'an}} (present-day {{ill|Xi&amp;#39;an|en|Xi&amp;#39;an|qid=Q5826|lt=Xi&amp;#39;an|1=Xi'an}}), the capital of {{ill|China|en|China|qid=Q148|lt=China|1=China}} during the {{ill|Tang dynasty|en|Tang dynasty|qid=Q9683|lt=Tang dynasty|1=Tang dynasty}}, which was contemporary to the time when Nara was capital. Chang'an was in turn, like many ancient east Asian cities, based on a complex system of beliefs &amp; laws of {{ill|Feng shui|en|Feng shui|qid=Q170537|lt=geomancy|1=Feng shui}}. This dictated the grid system of streets, as well as the necessity for spiritually protective shrines or temples to be placed at particular cardinal directions around the city. The city area measured {{convert|6|km}} from east to west and {{convert|5|km}} from north to south.

In accordance with this system, the palace was placed at the northern end, on an extended line from Suzaku Street, the main thoroughfare running north–south straight through the centre of the city. The street ended at the [[:en:Suzaku Gate|Suzaku Gate]], and the rest of the palace buildings were then placed beyond to the north of this gate. The primary buildings of the palace compound were the ''Daigoku-den'', where governmental affairs were conducted, the ''Chōdō-in'' where formal ceremonies were held, the ''Dairi'', the emperor's residence, and offices for various administrative agencies.

The Nara period covers 75 years from 710 to 784 AD. Emperor Shōmu moved the capital to other places such as [[:en:Kuni-kyo|Kuni-kyo]] and [[Shigaraki-kyo]] in the period between 740 and 745 AD. The imperial buildings and government offices were drastically transformed around this period. In the later Nara period, the audience hall was erected in the eastern part, at the south side of the imperial domicile. This is called the latter audience hall. A number of buildings in the imperial domicile and the government offices were replaced and renovated several times. This was probably not due to the repair of the old buildings but due to another reason.

When the capital was moved to Heian-kyō (now called {{ill|Kyoto|en|Kyoto|qid=Q34600|lt=Kyoto|1=Kyoto}}), Nara's Imperial Palace was simply abandoned. Over the ensuing centuries, the ravages of time and the elements slowly destroyed the buildings, until by the beginning of the {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}} in the late 12th century there was practically nothing left above ground. However, those sections that lay underground were preserved, and re-discovered by modern archaeologists.&lt;ref name="narashikanko" /&gt;

While the site was designated a Special Historical Site by the Agency for Cultural Affairs in 1952, archaeological efforts headed by the National Research Institute for Cultural Properties, such as excavations are continuing since 1959. The Suzaku Gate and East Palace Garden have been restored and opened to the public in 1998. The {{ill|Takenaka Corporation|en|Takenaka Corporation|qid=Q3116531|lt=Takenaka Corporation|1=Takenaka Corporation}} was mainly responsible for the reconstruction.&lt;ref name="Takenaka_01" /&gt;

Heijō Palace was the main event site of {{nihongo|[[Heijō-kyō|Heijo Relocation 1300 Year Festival]]|平城遷都1300th year 祭|Narasento 1300-nen-sai|lead=no}} in 2010, and the {{nihongo|First Great Hall|第一次大極殿|First Daigokuden|lead=no}} was restored for the occasion.&lt;ref name="Takenaka_02" /&gt; In commemorative events of the 1300th anniversary, a variety of seasonal events were held throughout Nara Prefecture.

== Structures ==

=== Suzaku Gate ===
[[File:Heijokyo Suzakumon 05.JPG|thumb|The [[:en:Suzaku Gate|Suzaku Gate]] is the main entrance to the palace]]
The main entrance to the capital through the Suzaku Avenue was the {{nihongo|Rajō Gate|羅城門|Rajōmon|lead=no}}. The main avenue was approximately {{convert|75|m}} wide and extended north for {{convert|3.7|km}} up to the {{nihongo|[[:en:Suzaku Gate|Suzaku Gate]]|朱雀門|Suzakumon|lead=no}}. The name "Suzaku" derives from the Chinese name for the legendary bird which acted as a southern guardian. The palace was surrounded by great earthen walls and had twelve gates, with the Suzaku Gate as the largest gate and the main entrance. The southern open spaces was part of the main avenue, and the {{nihongo|Nijo Oji|二条大路|Nijō-Ōji|lead=no}}, the second great street, approximately {{convert|37|m}} wide was extending in the east–west direction in front of the gate.

The gate measured {{convert|10|x|25|x|22|m}}. Built on a platform, the gate was probably a two-storied structure, conspicuously larger than the other gates of the palace. The open space to the front was used for ceremonies such as New Year celebrations. It was reconstructed in {{year|1998}}.

=== Second Street and Mibu Gate ===
The Second Street was a major thoroughfare running east–west along the southern side of the palace precinct. Around 35 metres in width, it was second only to Suzaku Avenue in size. The Suzaku Gate, which was the main gate, together with the Mibu Gate to its east and the Wakainukai Gate to its west, all opened onto this avenue.

In the latter half of the Nara period, the Great Hall of State and the Halls of State compound that comprised the centre  of politics shifted to the eastern sector of the precinct. The Mibu Gate served in effect as the main gate to the palace.

The area immediately to the south of the Second street is known to have been used for state offices and detached residences located outside the palace grounds, and was thus a district rivaling the palace itself in importance.

=== Greater Palace ===
The daidairi was a walled rectangular area extending from north to south between the first and second major east–west avenues and from west to east between the north–south avenues.

The three main structures within the Greater Palace were the {{Nihongo|Official Compound|朝堂院|Chōdō-in}} and the {{Nihongo|Inner Palace|内裏|Dairi}}.

=== ''Chōdō-in'' ===
The ''Chōdō-in'' was a rectangular walled enclosure situated directly to the north of the Suzaku Gate in the centre of the southern wall of the Greater Palace. It was based on Chinese models and followed Chinese architectural styles, and archaeological evidence from earlier capitals shows that this building complex was present in earlier palaces and had a remarkably stable design from the 7th century onwards.

=== Former audience hall ===
[[File:Front view of Daigokuden.jpg|thumb|The Great Hall of State]]
[[File:Imperial throne of Heijo palace.jpg|thumb|The ''Takamikura'' throne in the Great Hall of State]]
The {{Nihongo|Great Hall of State|大極殿|Daigokuden}} was the most important state building in the palace. It was facing south at the northern end of the compound. It was the largest building, measuring {{convert|20|x|44|x|27|m}} 44 metres in width and 20 metres in depth, with a height of 27 metres. The hall was thought to have been a two-storey Chinese-style structure with a hipped and gabled roof, and an open front façade having no doors.

No data directly indicating the audience hall's true appearance have survived. For the reconstruction, locations of the pillars were inferred through reference to the building's remains at {{ill|Kuni-kyō|en|Kuni-kyō|qid=Q1155335|lt=Kuni-kyō|1=Kuni-kyō}}, to where it had been relocated. For the upper part of the building, research was conducted on the main hall of [[Hōryū-ji]], the eastern pagoda of [[Yakushi-ji]], and other buildings that survived from the Nara period. The depiction of the Heian Palace audience hall depicted in the ''Nenchu gyoji emaki'' (Illustrated scroll of annual events and ceremonies) was also consulted.

The reconstruction was started in 2001 and completed in 2010. For the reconstruction, Japanese cypress wood was used. The building's pillars and beams were painted in {{ill|Vermilion|en|Vermilion|qid=Q737438|lt=Vermilion|1=Vermilion}}, the walls in white, the roof with ceramic tiles. The upper part of the interior of the hall was painted with symbols of the {{ill|Chinese zodiac|en|Chinese zodiac|qid=Q1976204|lt=Chinese zodiac|1=Chinese zodiac}} such as the {{ill|Tiger (zodiac)|en|Tiger (zodiac)|qid=Q740762|lt=Tiger|1=Tiger (zodiac)}}, the {{ill|Horse (zodiac)|en|Horse (zodiac)|qid=Q869595|lt=Horse|1=Horse (zodiac)}} and the [[Ox (zodiac)|Ox]] alongside the walls, and floral pattern on the ceiling. The paintings were executed by the renowned painter [[Atsushi Uemura]] based on designs from the Nara period.&lt;ref name="1300_Festival" /&gt;&lt;ref name="nmzk" /&gt;

==== ''Takamikura'' ====
In the middle of the audience hall was the emperor's throne, called {{Nihongo|''Takamikura''|高御座}}. This was an important item that symbolised the imperial office, and at state events such as the [[Enthronement of the Japanese emperor|enthronement]] and [[Japanese New Year|New Year's Day ceremonies]] the emperor proceeded to the audience hall and took his seat on the throne. Nobles lined up in the inner court south of the hall and paid their respect.

With no records of the construction or design of the ''Takamikura'' of the Nara period, the details are unknown. The reconstructed model of the ''Takamikura'' was made after experts consulted various literature and historical materials, and based on the throne in the Kyoto Imperial Palace which dates to the {{ill|Taishō era|en|Taishō era|qid=Q329174|lt=Taishō era|1=Taishō era}}. Details of the design and patterns were created by referring to materials such as the treasure of the [[Shōsōin]] repository.

=== Office of Foods ===
This area, stretching northward from the centrally located Great Hall of State, is believed to have been the site of the Office of Foods. This office stocked foods other than the rice that was paid as tax, and was in charge of providing meals for state banquets and rituals held in the palace.

Surrounding a large well, itself provided with a roof and from which numerous eating utensils have been excavated, stood a group of buildings used as offices and storehouses. The first inscribed wooden tablet recovered from the palace site was found in 1961 in a rubbish pit belonging to this office.

=== Latter audience hall ===
The latter audience hall dates to the time after the capital was re-established after the relocation from Shigaraki.

Traces of the platforms of the latter audience hall and the eastern state halls had remained by the Meiji era, which led to the discovery of the site by Sekino Tadashi, a researcher of architecture history. Tanada Kajuro, a local gardener, worked on a public movement for protection of the site.

The area on the north side of the latter audience hall is the site of the imperial domicile.

=== Imperial Domicile ===
The emperor and empress lived, worked, and received visitors in the imperial domicile section. It was surrounded by a roofed walkway, divided lengthwise by an earthen wall. The Office of the Court Ladies was also located here.

Inside the imperial domicile was a stone-paved area containing a large well, of which remains were found in {{year|1973}}. The well was lined with a solid cedar tube carved from a log {{convert|1.7|m}} in diameter. The water from this well was probably for the exclusive use of the emperor and empress. The site was reburied and the wall was reconstructed with new materials as an outdoor exhibit.

=== Office of the Imperial Household ===
In this section to the east of the imperial domicile, is what is thought to have been the {{nihongo|{{ill|Ministry of the Imperial Household|en|Ministry of the Imperial Household|qid=Q8193428|lt=Office of the Imperial Household|1=Ministry of the Imperial Household}}|宮内省|Kunai-shō}}. It was surrounded by an earthen wall, 90 metres in length to the north and south and 50 metres wide from east to west. Six buildings stood in this compound. The main one was roofed with tiles, the others with cypress bark.

The building were reconstructed in accordance with the findings of the archaeological excavations, following the Nara period construction techniques.

=== East Palace Garden ===
[[File:Heijyokyo Tointeien Plaza.jpg|thumb|The East Palace Garden]]
Archaeological excavations uncovered remains of a large garden in the southeast corner of the palace in 1967. This was named "East Palace Garden" (Tōin Teien) because the neighbouring area is considered to be the site of the East Palace.

Within the area measuring {{convert|100|by|80|m|ft}}. Several buildings were located around a curvilinear pond. In the vicinity of the site, [[:en:Empress Shōtoku|Empress Shōtoku]] had the "Jewelled Hall of the East Palace" constructed, in which banquets were held.

The excavations revealed that the garden was originally built in the Chinese style of the early Nara period, and modified in a Japanese style of the late Nara period. The garden was reconstructed in 1998.

== Heijō-kyō Suzaku-ōji==
The {{nihongo|Heijō-kyō Suzaku-ōji|平城京朱雀大路跡||}}, the central street of Heijō-kyō, was located between Nijō-ōji Minami and Sanjō-ōji in modern Nara city. In 1984 the 220 meter stretch from the Heijō-kyō ruins to Ōmiya-dōri to the south, was designated as a [[Monuments of Japan|National Historic Site]].&lt;ref name="Bunka1"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://kunishitei.bunka.go.jp/heritage/detail/401/2043 |title=平城京朱雀大路跡 |language=Japanese |publisher=[[Agency for Cultural Affairs]] |access-date=August 20, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Suzaku-ōji, which stretches 3.7 kilometer from north to south, from the Rajōmon Gate, the main entrance to Heijō-kyō in the south, to Suzakumon Gate, the main gate on the south side of the palace complex, was designed not only to function as a road, but also to accommodate the passage of foreign envoys, and its size and the surrounding streetscape were designed to be spectacular. Excavations conducted since 1974 have clarified the route of the street, and it has been revealed that the width is about 74 meters between the centers of the east-and-west side gutters, and that the distance between the east and west embankments in Sanjō isabout 85 meters. The remains of a previous 23 meter wide were also discovered below the {{ill|Nara period|en|Nara period|qid=Q189178|lt=Nara period|1=Nara period}} road. In 2010, a portion of the Heijō-kyō Suzaku-ōji, measuring 70 meters wide and 210 meters long, was restored from the south side of Suzakumon Gate.&lt;ref name="Shiseki"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Isomura |first1=Yukio |last2=Sakai |first2=Hideya |title=(国指定史跡事典) National Historic Site Encyclopedia |date=2012 |publisher=学生社 |isbn=4311750404}}{{in lang|ja}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Museum ==
The Nara National Research Institute for Cultural Properties has conducted research and investigation of the site on a continual basis since 1959. The Nara Palace Site Museum exhibits the results of the excavations. It consists of galleries for the palace and its administrative offices, artifacts, archaeological science, and special exhibitions.

== Transport ==
It takes 15 or 20 minutes to walk from {{ill|Yamato-Saidaiji Station|en|Yamato-Saidaiji Station|qid=Q489786|lt=Yamato-Saidaiji Station|1=Yamato-Saidaiji Station}} to Heijō Palace. And between May and August in 2010, the free shuttle bus runs between Yamato-Saidaiji Station, {{ill|Nara Station|en|Nara Station|qid=Q1150978|lt=JR Nara Station|1=Nara Station}} and Heijō Palace every 10 or 15 minutes.

==See also==
* {{ill|Kyūseki Teien|en|Kyūseki Teien|qid=Q11482303|lt=Kyūseki Teien|1=Kyūseki Teien}}, a garden located at Sakyo Sanjo Nibo constructed around the same time
* {{ill|Heian Palace|en|Heian Palace|qid=Q304501|lt=Heian Palace|1=Heian Palace}}
* {{ill|List of Special Places of Scenic Beauty, Special Historic Sites and Special Natural Monuments|en|List of Special Places of Scenic Beauty, Special Historic Sites and Special Natural Monuments|qid=Q20982902|lt=List of Special Places of Scenic Beauty, Special Historic Sites and Special Natural Monuments|1=List of Special Places of Scenic Beauty, Special Historic Sites and Special Natural Monuments}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name="Hashimoto_1954"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Hashimoto | first1 = Yoshinori  | date= 1954 | title = Kodai kyūto no dairi kōzō | script-title = ja:古代宮都の内裏構造 | trans-title = Inner structure of the ancient palace | language = ja | publisher = Yoshikawa Kōbunkan | publication-date = 2011 |isbn = 978-4642024815  | lccn = 2011528219 | oclc = 763044145 | ol = OL25180282M | df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="narashikanko"&gt;{{cite web |url = https://narashikanko.or.jp/en/spot/world_heritage/heijokyuseki/ |title = Heijo Palace Site | date= n.d. | website = Nara City Tourism Association | language = en  | access-date = 2020-11-24 |url-status = live | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20200819212343/https://narashikanko.or.jp/en/spot/world_heritage/heijokyuseki/ | archive-date = 2020-08-19 | df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Takenaka_01"&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://www.takenaka.co.jp/solution/purpose/traditional/service08/index.html  | title = Heijōkyūato suzakumon 1300-nen no toki o koe, yomigaetta tenpyō no iyō remasu | trans-title = Heijo Palace Remains Suzakumon: The majesty of Tenpei revived after 1300.| script-title = ja:平城宮跡 朱雀門 1300th year の時を越え、蘇った天平の威容 れます。  | website = {{ill|Takenaka Corporation|en|Takenaka Corporation|qid=Q3116531|lt=Takenaka Corporation|1=Takenaka Corporation}} | language = ja | access-date=2013-11-21 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131224103806/http://www.takenaka.co.jp/solution/purpose/traditional/service08/index.html | archive-date = 2013-12-24 |url-status = dead  | via = {{ill|Wayback Machine|en|Wayback Machine|qid=Q648266|lt=Wayback Machine|1=Wayback Machine}} | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Takenaka_02"&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://www.takenaka.co.jp/solution/purpose/traditional/service09/index.html  | title = Heijōkyūato dai ichi-ji Taikyokuden seiden fukugen kōji: "Suzakumon" no kansei kara 12-nen, futatabi Takenaka no te ni yori, tenpyō bunka no iki o atsumeta kyūden kenchiku "Taikyokuden seiden" ga kansei. | trans-title = Heijo Palace Remains 1st Daigokuden Main Hall Restoration work: Twelve years after the completion of "Suzakumon", Takenaka completed the palace architecture "Taigokuden Main Hall", which is a collection of the best of Tenpyo culture. | script-title = ja:平城宮跡第 一 次大極殿正殿復原工事: 『朱雀門』の完成から12nd year 、再び竹中の手により、天平文化の粋を集めた宮殿建築『大極殿正殿』が完成。 | website = {{ill|Takenaka Corporation|en|Takenaka Corporation|qid=Q3116531|lt=Takenaka Corporation|1=Takenaka Corporation}} | language = ja | access-date=2020-11-24 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160423052036/http://www.takenaka.co.jp/solution/purpose/traditional/service09/index.html | archive-date = 2016-04-23 |url-status = dead  | via = {{ill|Wayback Machine|en|Wayback Machine|qid=Q648266|lt=Wayback Machine|1=Wayback Machine}} | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="1300_Festival"&gt;{{Cite web | url  =http://osamu.blog.eonet.jp/weblog/2010/11/1300-b62a.html | title = Narasento 1300-nen-sai Heijōkyō fea | date = 2010-11-03  | language = ja |script-title = ja:平城遷都1300th year 祭 平城京フェア | trans-title = Heijo Relocation 1300 Year Festival Heijokyo Fair  | access-date = 2020-11-24 | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140502165832/http://osamu.blog.eonet.jp/weblog/2010/11/1300-b62a.html |archive-date=2014-05-02 | df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="nmzk"&gt;{{cite web | url = https://nmzk.blog.ss-blog.jp/2010-06-07 | title = Nara e ikimashita 6 heijōkyūato no kengaku 3 | author = nmzk's | date = 2010-06-07  | language = ja |script-title = ja:奈良へ行きました ６ 平城宮跡の見学 ３ | trans-title = I went to Nara 6 Visiting the Heijo Palace site 3 | access-date = 2020-11-24 | url-status = live |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20201124164840/https://nmzk.blog.ss-blog.jp/2010-06-07 |archive-date = 2020-11-24 | df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
{{commons Category-inline}}
* [http://www.nabunken.go.jp/heijo/museum/index.html Nara Palace Site Museum]{{in lang|ja}}
* [https://visitnara.jp/venues/A00497/ Heijokyu Imperial Palace, from The Official Nara Travel Guide] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210221221241/https://www.visitnara.jp/venues/A00497/ |date=2021-02-21 }}
* [https://whc.unesco.org/sites/870.htm Official UNESCO page]
* [https://archive.today/20121206034238/http://www2.gol.com/users/stever/nara.htm Geomancy and Imperial Position in Nara]
* [http://sitereports.nabunken.go.jp/en/search?all=%E5%B9%B3%E5%9F%8E%E5%AE%AE%E8%B7%A1&amp;include_file=exclude. Excavation report] The Comprehensive Database of Archaeological Site Reports in Japan.

{{coord|34|41|28|N|135|47|44|E|region:JP_type:landmark|display=title}}
{{Imperial Palaces Japan}}
{{World Heritage Nara}}



[[en:Heijō Palace]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[af:Heijō Paleis]]
[[ca:Palau Heijō]]
{{Commons category|Heijō Palace}}
[[cs:Palác Heidžó]]
[[el:Ανάκτορο Χεϊτζό]]
[[es:Palacio Heijō]]
[[fa:کاخ هیجو]]
[[fr:Palais Heijō]]
[[hr:Carska palača u Nari]]
[[id:Istana Heijō]]
[[it:Palazzo Heijō]]
[[ja:平城宮]]
[[ko:헤이조궁]]
[[pt:Palácio Heijō]]
[[sh:Carska palača u Nari]]
[[sl:Palača Heidžo]]
[[tr:Heijō Sarayı]]
[[wuu:平城宫]]
[[zh:平城宫]]
[[zh-yue:平城宮]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
&lt;!--zhwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q211585}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in the 8th century]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Nara, Nara]]
[[Category:Former palaces in Japan]]
[[Category:Historic Sites of Japan]]
[[Category:History of Nara Prefecture]]
[[Category:Imperial residences in Japan]]
[[Category:Kansai Science City]]
[[Category:Museums in Nara Prefecture]]
[[Category:Nara period]]
[[Category:Places of Scenic Beauty]]
[[Category:Special Historic Sites]]
[[Category:Special Places of Scenic Beauty]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Nara Prefecture]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>c0417ojgce2cekpyua4rhqyo10p723z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
