<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sōkaisō Mondō</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>192485</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3756561</id>
      <timestamp>2026-05-19T19:25:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yenistardom</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>滄海窓問答</comment>
      <origin>3756561</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="88964" sha1="6qog88mh13itdm0v2tslwethjgak1gd" xml:space="preserve">'''''Sōkaisō mondō''''' (滄海窓問答) was compiled by Sasaki Tetsutarō (佐佐木哲太朗) in 1898. It is written in Literary Chinese (hence the lack of Japanese ''[[w:en:Kana|kana]]'' in the text). It contains 98 questions and answers on Soejima Taneomi's explanations of spiritual studies of [[w:en:Honda Chikaatsu|Honda Chikaatsu]] ([[w:ja:本田親徳|本田親徳]]). ''Sōkaisō mondō'' (滄海窓問答) can also be found at the end of  ([[commons:Category:幽冥秘録神仙霊典|幽冥秘録神仙霊典]], ''Yūmei Hiroku Shinsen Reiten''), which was published by [[w:en:Shintō Tenkōkyo|Shintō Tenkōkyo]] founder Tomokiyo Yoshisane ([[w:ja:友清歓真|友清歓真]]) in 1920. This version is based on Tomokiyo's 1920 edition. The text consists of nearly 100 questions from [[w:en:Soejima Taneomi|Soejima Taneomi]], along with answers from Honda Chikaatsu, about the nature of the divine, the formation of the spirit and the soul, and so on.

==Interlinear translation==
(Google Gemini 3.1 Pro Extended translation; please check for errors and improvements) 

滄海問答

*Canghai Wenda (Sōkai's Dialogues)

未定草

*Unfinished Draft

門人石舟道士輯

*Compiled by the Disciple, Daoist Sekishū

---

問	一念將動神能知之者何

*'''Question''': When a single thought is about to move, how is it that the spirits (kami) can know it?

曰	不謂善必先知之不善必先知之乎

*'''Answer''': Is it not said that "when good is about to happen, they foreknow it; when evil is about to happen, they foreknow it"?

問	以奇魂知之乎

*'''Question''': Do they know it by means of the ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul)?

曰	奇魂知奇魂和魂知和魂荒幸二魂知荒幸二魂

*'''Answer''': The ''Kushi-mitama'' knows the ''Kushi-mitama'', the ''Nigi-mitama'' (Harmonious Soul) knows the ''Nigi-mitama'', and the two souls ''Ara-mitama'' (Rough Soul) and ''Saki-mitama'' (Fortunate Soul) know the ''Ara-mitama'' and ''Saki-mitama''.

問	和魂而知他魂者何

*'''Question''': How does the ''Nigi-mitama'' know the other souls?

曰	以和魂有餘而知他魂不足以和魂不足知他魂有餘

*'''Answer''': Through the excess of the ''Nigi-mitama'' it knows the deficiency of the other souls; through the deficiency of the ''Nigi-mitama'' it knows the excess of the other souls.

問	善知不善者何

*'''Question''': How does good know what is not good?

曰	以全魂而知四魂有餘不足有餘不足者即不善

*'''Answer''': Through the complete soul, it knows the excess or deficiency of the four souls. Excess and deficiency are precisely what is not good.

問	有餘亦爲不善乎

*'''Question''': Is excess also considered not good?

曰	過猶不及

*'''Answer''': To go beyond is as wrong as to fall short.

問	各魂各用得嘗聞教未知合兩魂之用一言而可幾

*'''Question''': I have previously received teachings on the individual functions of each soul, but I do not yet know how the combined functions of two souls might be expressed in a single phrase.

曰	寬柔而教不報無道南方之强是合奇荒二魂之用者

*'''Answer''': "To teach with broad gentleness and not to exact revenge upon the unreasonable, which is the strength of the South"—this combines the functions of the ''Kushi-mitama'' and the ''Ara-mitama''.

問	寬柔者豈非和魂之用乎

*'''Question''': Is not "broad gentleness" a function of the ''Nigi-mitama''?

曰	夫教無道者智之巧寬柔者其形容也和魂者不與無道和

*'''Answer''': Teaching the unreasonable is the ingenuity of Wisdom, and broad gentleness is its outward appearance. The ''Nigi-mitama'' does not harmonize with the unreasonable.

問	神何衣何食何宅

*'''Question''': What do the spirits wear, what do they eat, and where do they dwell?

曰	衣道食道宅道如人衣於道食於道宅於道則亦猶神耳

*'''Answer''': They wear the Way, eat the Way, and dwell in the Way. If a person were to wear the Way, eat the Way, and dwell in the Way, they would be just like a spirit.

民見治于君々見養于民百官立其中間而行其義可以悟君權民權所判而百官所注意亦可定焉故百官偏頗于君則爲侫姦傾側于民則爲亂賊以審判之理言之或人或獸或禽或魚虫是正則也有居人與獸之間者有居獸與禽之間者有居禽與魚虫之間者是變則也若人惡性者蓋居人與獸之間者獸善性者亦然是所謂人面獸心與獸面人心之辨也

The people are governed by the lord, and the lord is nourished by the people; the myriad officials stand between them to practice righteousness. Through this, one can understand the distinction between sovereign rights and civil rights, and the proper focus of the officials can be established. Therefore, if officials are overly biased toward the lord, they become flattering sycophants; if they tilt completely toward the people, they become rebellious traitors. Speaking from the principle of judgment, whether human, beast, bird, or fish and insect, these follow the standard rules. There are those who dwell between humans and beasts, those who dwell between beasts and birds, and those who dwell between birds and fishes/insects; these follow anomalous rules. If a human has an evil nature, they exist between humans and beasts, and a beast with a good nature is the same. This is the distinction between "a human face with a beast's heart" and "a beast's face with a human heart."

樂若無用然使千百人一時同心志者唯樂爲然周人禮樂並稱爲和性情莫及樂也和者親和也

Music may seem useless, yet to make thousands of people unify their hearts and wills simultaneously, only music can achieve this. The people of Zhou praised Rites and Music equally; for harmonizing nature and emotion, nothing matches music. This harmony is an intimate harmony.

擊柝警夜金鼓喇吧指揮三軍亦皆與樂同用所以一其心志也

Striking the watchman's clapper to warn the night, or using gongs, drums, and trumpets to command the armies, are all used in the same manner as music, serving to unify their hearts and wills.

靈威亦猶樂也有聲響于此誰不愕然者誰不敬畏者按孔子迅雷風烈必變有以也

Spiritual majesty is also like music. If a great sound echoes here, who would not be startled? Who would not be in awe? Consider that Confucius would change his countenance at sudden claps of thunder or fierce winds; there is a reason for this.

問	役小角役使鬼魅何術

*'''Question''': By what art did En no Ozuno control and command ghosts and demons?

曰	人有魔性者能與魔魅感如役小角是也前所謂人面獸心者即魔性也

*'''Answer''': A person who possesses a demonic nature can resonate with demons and spirits, as was the case with En no Ozuno. What was previously called "a human face with a beast's heart" is exactly this demonic nature.

問	伊勢神宮其他神社等有不由人火而燒亡者如何

*'''Question''': How is it that the Grand Shrine of Ise and other shrines are sometimes destroyed by fires not caused by humans?

曰	神怒所有激發生火警猶凡人慣恚滿面發赤不意生火而生火也固與魔魅好事出火異矣

*'''Answer''': The anger of the gods causes a sudden sparking of fire, just as an ordinary person, filled with rage, flushes red in the face, involuntarily generating heat. This is fundamentally different from demons mischievously starting fires.

同之一神也而其所嗣各不同其功用者祭人本意所有各不同也即神人相感之理也故在人應慎勿思不祥言不祥行也則神人相感不啻無不祥[禮內則胎教／之條可思]至于顯許多功用矣

It is the same single deity, yet their manifestations and functions differ because the fundamental intentions of the worshippers differ. This is the principle of mutual resonance between gods and humans. Therefore, humans must be careful not to think inauspicious thoughts, speak inauspicious words, or perform inauspicious deeds. Then, the mutual resonance between gods and humans will not only prevent the inauspicious [one may consider the section on prenatal education in the "Neize" chapter of the ''Book of Rites''], but will also manifest many beneficial functions.

在廟堂上思安民則必獲安民矣提三軍衆思勝敵則必獲勝敵矣有神人相感者然

If one is in the imperial court and thinks of bringing peace to the people, they will surely achieve peace for the people. If one leads the armies and the multitudes think of defeating the enemy, they will surely defeat the enemy. This is so because of the mutual resonance between gods and humans.

靈光靈動靈聲靈香靈味靈觸是謂靈威凡是等事神非好事爲之神意所透徹自顯此靈威

Spiritual light, spiritual movement, spiritual sound, spiritual scent, spiritual taste, and spiritual touch—these are called spiritual majesty. In all these matters, it is not that the gods do them mischievously; rather, where the divine will penetrates deeply, this spiritual majesty naturally manifests.

問	古人言望雲氣知吉凶有理乎

*'''Question''': The ancients said that by observing the clouds and vapors, one can know good and bad fortune. Is there reason in this?

曰	無此理也大概皆托神異圖名利者但如北魏崔浩明劉基固旣推擴事理而察知其吉凶而托之於天文地理者蓋神妙其說也凡治亂興廢決於行道義與否也

*'''Answer''': There is no such reason. Generally, these are just people feigning divine anomalies to scheme for fame and profit. However, figures like Cui Hao of the Northern Wei and Liu Ji of the Ming had already deduced the principles of affairs to perceive good and bad fortune, and then merely attributed them to astronomy and geography to mystify their explanations. Ultimately, order and chaos, rise and fall, are determined by whether or not moral principles are practiced.

夫易說貞凶天地間有此理乎若說貞凶則將說不貞吉平舜事瞽叟孝道也文王囚羌里忠道也可以爲凶乎凶在彼而不在己

The ''Book of Changes'' speaks of "uprightness leading to misfortune." Can such a principle exist between heaven and earth? If uprightness leads to misfortune, would they say being un-upright is auspicious? Shun serving Gu Sou was the path of filial piety; King Wen being imprisoned in Youli was the path of loyalty. Can these be considered inauspicious? The misfortune lies with the others, not with oneself.

樂器猶筆也筆工之作筆其製一般也而有書道德仁義有書雜話小說由其書之者不同也雖二絃琴使陶淵明彈之則不可謂無神祇守護

A musical instrument is like a brush. When a brush maker makes brushes, the design is the same, yet some are used to write of the Dao, Virtue, Benevolence, and Righteousness, while others are used to write idle chatter and fiction; this is due to the difference in the writers. Even a simple two-stringed zither, if played by Tao Yuanming, could not be said to lack the protection of the gods.

有同一異事于此不問其爲神異爲魔異先問其本主有德無德則其爲顧祥爲妖孽不辨可知猶富家翁有二子一喜勤儉一好游蕩而翁各與之萬金則一益勤儉爲富一盒游蕩至亡其身也

If the same anomalous event occurs, do not ask whether it is a divine anomaly or a demonic anomaly; first ask whether its primary owner possesses virtue or lacks virtue. Then, whether it is an auspicious omen or a monstrous calamity will be known without need for debate. It is like a rich old man who has two sons: one loves diligence and thrift, the other loves debauchery. If the old man gives them each ten thousand pieces of gold, the first will become even more diligent and wealthy, while the second will squander it entirely until he destroys himself.

樂之不可無吉凶軍賓嘉皆爲然

Music cannot exist without the context of auspiciousness, inauspiciousness, military matters, welcoming guests, or joyous occasions; all are thus.

歌辭與聲律相稱是正樂不相稱者所謂鄭聲也

When the lyrics and the musical pitch are in harmony, it is proper music. When they do not harmonize, it is what is called the "Sounds of Zheng" (decadent music).

樂器則古法可矣凡在後世須要言古人所不言行古人所不行發明古人所不發明今則專精樂器其所造雖工智不足稱也

For musical instruments, the ancient methods are sufficient. Generally, in later generations, it is essential to speak what the ancients did not speak, to do what the ancients did not do, and to invent what the ancients did not invent. But today, people only specialize in perfecting musical instruments; though their craftsmanship is skilled, their wisdom is not worth praising.

樂唯在交際上用之者今若自鳴琴猶自鳴鐘蓋屬玩物者不可謂之樂器也夫樂者人與人相對手舞足蹈足以和性情也故日在交際上用之

Music is solely meant to be used in social interaction. Today, a self-playing piano is like a chiming clock—it belongs to the category of playthings and cannot be called a musical instrument. Music is when people face one another, their hands dancing and feet tapping, sufficiently harmonizing their natures and emotions. Therefore it is said to be used in social interaction.

人生而其靈始顯然其父母交感之時既備得魂體力之三者不然及其生何種子能突然引天地之靈乎唯其在胎內其魂與母氏接續耳而其實母胎包羅之猶天地包羅人也

When a human is born, their spirit first becomes manifest. Yet, at the moment of their parents' intercourse, they are already endowed with the three elements: soul, body, and vital force. If this were not so, by what seed could they suddenly draw down the spirit of heaven and earth upon being born? It is just that while in the womb, their soul is continuously connected with the mother. In truth, the mother's womb encompasses the child just as heaven and earth encompass humanity.

問	元宋邦昌者釋奠孔廟俄然風起殿上吹拔殿中鎮樽時人皆以爲孔子威靈未知如何

*'''Question''': During the Yuan dynasty, when Song Bangchang was performing a sacrifice at the Temple of Confucius, a sudden wind rose in the hall and blew away the sacrificial vessels inside. People of the time all considered this to be Confucius's spiritual majesty. I do not know how this is?

曰	是爲回應凡孔子所述作諸書皆其威靈至今有感服天下人心蓋在道義上不可不如此說語日子不語怪力亂神其生平如此况死後乎唯自他論之謂其威靈所然亦未爲不可

*'''Answer''': This was a response. All the books written by Confucius are his spiritual majesty; to this day they possess the power to move and subdue the hearts of people worldwide. From the perspective of moral principles, one must explain it this way. The ''Analects'' say, "The Master did not speak of anomalies, feats of strength, rebellions, or spirits." His life was like this, how much more so after his death? However, if judging from the perspective of others, it is not entirely unacceptable to attribute it to his spiritual majesty.

孔子溫良恭謙讓適所以盛其威靈孔子不謂鬼神之爲德其盛矣若夫反之者其平生發露無復餘薀何威靈之有

Confucius was gentle, upright, courteous, temperate, and yielding; this is exactly what magnified his spiritual majesty. Confucius did not say that the virtue of ghosts and spirits was abundant. As for those who are the opposite, their entire lives are exposed with nothing left in reserve—what spiritual majesty could they possess?

孔子平生實能認識神祇威靈故其所慎齋戰疾

Confucius, in his lifetime, truly could recognize the spiritual majesty of the deities, which is why the things he exercised the greatest caution over were fasting, war, and sickness.

怪力亂神二事也亂神後世所謂瀋祠之類左傳石言是其一

Anomalous strength and chaotic spirits are two different things. "Chaotic spirits" refer to what later generations call illicit shrines and the like; the "speaking stone" in the ''Zuo Zhuan'' is one example.

夫以實事論者道義上正則譬風謂之風光謂之光色謂之色聲謂之聲之類然非其時非其所非其物而顯其異者不可不謂之威靈也凡自祭法言之威靈也

Discussing it based on actual events: if it follows the standard of natural laws, then wind is called wind, light is called light, form is called form, and sound is called sound. But when anomalies manifest outside their proper time, place, or natural state, they must be called spiritual majesty. Generally, from the perspective of sacrificial rites, it is called spiritual majesty.

同一異事而賢人君子視之謂之祥瑞亂臣賊子視之謂之妖孽由道義上判之謂之異事

Regarding the very same anomalous event, sages and noblemen see it and call it an auspicious sign; rebellious ministers and traitors see it and call it a monstrous calamity. Judged from the standpoint of moral principles, it is simply called an anomaly.

問	祭法者如何

*'''Question''': What of the sacrificial rites?

曰	禮記祭法日山林川谷丘陵能出雲爲風雨見怪物皆日神々者猶靈威也神威也夫能以誠祭神必有靈益祭必受福禮明教也日祭無益豈非殷紂罪狀之一乎

*'''Answer''': The ''Book of Rites'', in the "Law of Sacrifices," says: "Mountains, forests, rivers, valleys, hills, and mounds, which can produce clouds and make wind and rain, and manifest anomalous things, are all called deities." "Deity" here implies spiritual majesty and divine power. If one can sacrifice to the spirits with sincerity, there will definitely be spiritual benefit. "Sacrifice inevitably brings blessings" is the clear teaching of the rites. To claim that sacrifices bring no benefit—was this not one of the crimes of King Zhou of Shang?

夫不脩農政而祈年穀豊饒固見其無靈念也人事神事並舉而無靈益者未之有也

To neglect agricultural administration while praying for an abundant harvest is a clear sign of lacking true spiritual mindfulness. There has never been a case where human effort and divine service were conducted together without yielding spiritual benefit.

孔子明道盡義又能熟知祭法是孔子之所以爲聖人

Confucius illuminated the Way, exhausted righteousness, and was deeply versed in the sacrificial rites; this is what made Confucius a sage.

問	孔子謂非其鬼而祭謟也又釋奠孔子母乃不可乎

*'''Question''': Confucius said, "To sacrifice to a spirit which does not belong to you is flattery." Is it then inappropriate to perform sacrifices to Confucius?

曰	國家祭聖賢忠孝貞烈之靈欲使天下後世儀刑之也非非其鬼而祭之類也唯在人民不爲其孫子者不可自爲祭主耳孔子所云爾者謂祭無主墓之類也

*'''Answer''': The state sacrifices to the spirits of sages, worthies, the loyal, the filial, and the fiercely chaste to make them models for the world and future generations. This is not the same as "sacrificing to a spirit that does not belong to you." It is only that common people who are not his descendants cannot set themselves up as the chief mourner/officiant. What Confucius referred to was the practice of offering sacrifices to untended graves and the like.

問	敬鬼神而遠之何謂也

*'''Question''': What does it mean to "respect spiritual beings but keep them at a distance"?

曰	遠之猶謂不擾避席下階敬之至義之盡也有一貴人于此正色端坐衣履顧類之匹夫能與之並坐乎意應人間無此法也蓋孔子能擴充人間法者也孔子所謂未能事人安能事鬼者無他亦謂推人及鬼耳若將推鬼及人其必陷巫頭流

*'''Answer''': "Keeping them at a distance" means not disturbing them, yielding one's seat, and stepping down from the hall; it is the utmost respect and the exhaustion of righteousness. Suppose there is a nobleman sitting here with a solemn expression and formal attire; could a commoner in ragged clothes sit beside him? Such a practice surely does not exist in the human world. Confucius was one who could extend the laws of the human world. When Confucius said, "While you cannot serve men, how can you serve spirits?", he simply meant projecting human principles onto spirits. If one projects spiritual matters onto humans, they will inevitably fall into the way of shamans and sorcerers.

問	今世間喪者有嫌火潔穢之事如何

*'''Question''': In the present world, mourners avoid using fire from the same hearth to avoid pollution. What about this?

曰	是非人情也厚其生而薄其死以人骸爲穢夫以人骸爲穢而食禽獸虫魚死物而不爲穢何其謬也夫禽獸虫魚死物猶供之於鬼神而爲禮乎

*'''Answer''': This goes against human feelings. It values life but treats death lightly, viewing human remains as impure. To consider human remains impure, while eating the dead bodies of beasts, birds, insects, and fish without considering them impure—how absurd! Can the dead bodies of beasts, birds, insects, and fish still be offered to gods and spirits as a proper rite?

神不食祭物然祭物其必享之享者歡也非食之謂也夫人以誠敬祭之而不饗之者頑鬼也頑鬼者在草葬者也

The spirits do not physically eat the sacrificial offerings, yet they must "enjoy" them. To "enjoy" means to take pleasure in them, not to eat them. If people sacrifice with sincere respect and the spirit does not enjoy it, it is an obstinate ghost. An obstinate ghost is one buried carelessly in the wild.

豊臣秀吉之裁禍亂漢高祖之定國佛拿勃列翁之踐帝位本皆微賤而能如此者唯在一立志耳如高祖見禽其父而不屈秀吉自質其母而不厭拿勃列翁流竄一孤嶋而能奮者其勇决亦可知矣

Toyotomi Hideyoshi quelling chaos, Han Gaozu pacifying the nation, and Napoleon ascending the imperial throne—they were all originally of humble origins, and were able to achieve these things simply through a firm resolve. Gaozu saw his father captured yet did not yield; Hideyoshi offered his mother as a hostage without hesitation; Napoleon was exiled to a lonely island yet still rose up. Their resolute courage can be understood from this.

歆羨他人不及自爲之勝

Admiring others is not as good as taking action oneself.

無其所期而琢磨靈魂蓋亦爲難能矣

To refine one's soul without having a clear expectation or goal is indeed a difficult feat.

問	造語法亦自有四魂之別乎

*'''Question''': In the formation of words, is there also a distinction based on the four souls?

曰	聲以心爲主故其造語無細大見四魂之別

*'''Answer''': Sounds are governed by the heart/mind; therefore, in word formation, regardless of magnitude, the distinction of the four souls is evident.

問	大物忌神名義如何

*'''Question''': What is the meaning of the name "Omonoimi-no-kami" (Deity of Great Abstinence/Offerings)?

曰	物忌謂膳部等諸供物也

*'''Answer''': "Monoimi" (Offerings) refers to provisions and various sacrificial items.

問	既有神憑之道其所以質道義辨是非者不復須用太占法而可如何

*'''Question''': Since there is the path of divine possession to question moral principles and distinguish right from wrong, is there no longer a need to use the grand divination method (''Futomani'')? How is this?

曰	神憑自神太占自人故神憑無弗的中太占自非聰明睿智不能中之

*'''Answer''': Divine possession originates from the gods, while grand divination originates from humans. Therefore, divine possession never misses the mark, whereas grand divination cannot be accurate unless performed by someone with acute intelligence and profound wisdom.

問	墓祭禮乎

*'''Question''': Is sacrificing at a tomb in accordance with the rites?

曰	祭斯靈格如之何其爲非禮唯以其禮爲在地中不可

*'''Answer''': Sacrificing to this spiritual presence—how could it be against the rites? It is only improper to assume that the object of the rite is confined within the earth.

夫人盡禮而祭之而神不歡之是神不神終不能神也

If a person exhausts the rites to sacrifice to them, and the spirit does not rejoice, then the spirit is not acting as a spirit, and ultimately cannot be divine.

神與人言神事其聲洞轍一神界百神成聽夫言神事而不能聽者非神也

When a god speaks to a human about divine matters, the voice resonates thoroughly; if one divine realm hears it, a hundred gods all listen. Those who speak of divine matters but cannot hear are not gods.

夫以神爲人以人爲神是謂亂名語日必也正名乎

To treat gods as humans, or to treat humans as gods, is called confusing names. As the ''Analects'' say, "What is necessary is to rectify names."

アワハサャマナカクラ是韵例也マノミモム或タテチトッ是同聲例也聲以爲語々有聲通世以爲韻通非也

A-wa-ha-sa-ya-ma-na-ka-ku-ra are examples of rhymes. Ma-no-mi-mo-mu or ta-te-chi-to-tsu are examples of identical initial consonants. Sounds form words, and words have phonetic resonance. The world thinks this is rhyming, but it is not.

彦火々出見尊火出体之義後世國學者以火爲稻穗之義誤矣火進命火明命之名悉非稻穗之義觀其產時之行事可見蓋以火爲祥瑞而命名也忍穗根命之名義大靈根也瓊々杵尊之名義和也以和一字爲人民主凡人君臨人民不可不以和爲先其他諸魂蓋從其後也夫忍穗根爲大靈根是以元素鍛鍊爲体其不飲食推名義可知助字之津者接續辭其義不同」靈魂以鍛鍊琢磨爲貴

*Hikohohodemi-no-Mikoto'' means the manifestation of fire. Later Kokugaku (National Learning) scholars mistakenly took "fire" (''ho'') to mean "rice ears" (''ho''). The names ''Hososuseri-no-Mikoto'' and ''Hoakari-no-Mikoto'' absolutely do not mean rice ears; looking at the events during their births, this is evident. They were named taking fire as an auspicious sign. The name ''Oshihomimi-no-Mikoto'' means "Great Spiritual Root." The name ''Ninigi-no-Mikoto'' means "Harmony." Using the single character for "harmony" designates the ruler of the people. Generally, when a ruler presides over the people, they must place harmony first, and the other souls must follow after. ''Oshihomimi'' represents the Great Spiritual Root, utilizing elemental refinement as its form; its lack of eating or drinking can be deduced from its name. The auxiliary character ''tsu'' is a connective particle with a different meaning. The soul values refinement and polishing above all.

力者道体之義也体力者第二義也夫有道力而能發体力也未有体力能發道力也是有御中主神道力而後有天地萬物也

"Force" means the substance of the Way. Physical strength is a secondary meaning. Only when there is the force of the Way can physical strength be generated; physical strength has never been able to generate the force of the Way. Thus, it was the force of the Way of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami'' that existed first, and only afterward did heaven, earth, and all things come into being.

大地球自有地道大陽國自有大陽道月國自有月道眾星國自有衆星道而悉皆莫不本於天御中主大道矣

The great earth has its own earthly Way, the realm of the Sun has its own solar Way, the realm of the Moon has its own lunar Way, and the realm of the Myriad Stars has its own stellar Way. Yet, none of these fail to be rooted in the Great Way of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi''.

問	高津神者何

*'''Question''': What are the ''Takatsu-kami'' (High Deities)?

曰	世人所謂天狗者人神之而非神也夫天狗者混鳥獸之稱也然是語對高津鳥而言之則專指獸類也

*'''Answer''': What people of the world call ''Tengu''. People deify them, but they are not gods. ''Tengu'' is a mixed term for birds and beasts. However, when this term is contrasted with "Takatsu-tori" (High Birds), it specifically refers to beasts.

凡言道不言神言神不言道何則神道不二也

Generally, if one speaks of the Way, one does not need to speak of the gods; if one speaks of the gods, one does not need to speak of the Way. Why? Because gods and the Way are not two separate things.

問	世俗所言天狗者如何

*'''Question''': What about what the common people call ''Tengu''?

曰	夫有肉体而變幻爲奇異者自体上言之謂之天狗自道義上言之謂之魔

*'''Answer''': Those who have physical bodies but transform into bizarre illusions are called ''Tengu'' from the perspective of their physical form, but from the perspective of moral principles, they are called demons.

又曰	夫天狗等之現体物譬猶器械屬諸忠臣之手則誅斬亂賊也

*'''He also said''': These physical entities like ''Tengu'' are like tools; if they fall into the hands of loyal ministers, they will execute rebels and traitors.

又曰	夫天狗之爲行未必有惡事但至其思想不能盡脫惡意是所以稱魔物也

*'''He also said''': The actions of ''Tengu'' are not necessarily evil deeds, but when it comes to their thoughts, they cannot entirely rid themselves of evil intentions. That is why they are called demonic entities.

問	神亦可見乎

*'''Question''': Can the gods be seen?

曰	可見焉雄略帝之見一言主神其君臣皆見之也是其證神雖幽体現々亦易

*'''Answer''': They can be seen. Emperor Yūryaku saw the deity ''Hitokotonushi'', and both the sovereign and his ministers saw him. This is the proof. Although the gods are ethereal bodies, manifesting is quite easy for them.

莫貴於道義也荷能執持道義則雖不遇於時猶遺芳後世況遇者平日夫登神界者之土產惟道義而已矣

Nothing is more precious than moral principles. If one can hold fast to moral principles, even if unrecognized in their time, they will leave a fragrant legacy for later generations—how much more so for those who do meet their time! The only "souvenir" one brings when ascending to the divine realm is moral principle, nothing else.

敢問	伊勢神靈乎

*'''Question''': May I venture to ask, is the deity at Ise a divine spirit?

曰	直視天照皇大日靈貴神而可矣所憑伊勢神鏡之靈是自有限界者雖然一滴之水々則水神鏡之靈不可謂非天照皇也

*'''Answer''': You may regard it directly as ''Amaterasu-Ōmikami'' (the Great Sun Goddess). The spirit residing in the divine mirror at Ise naturally has its limits. Nevertheless, just as a single drop of water is still water, the spirit of the divine mirror cannot be said to not be ''Amaterasu''.

問	他日朝廷有復古之事則伊勢神宮如何而可

*'''Question''': In the future, if the Imperial Court undergoes a restoration of antiquity, what should be done regarding the Grand Shrine of Ise?

曰	先不復伊勢神宮於朝廷則當無復古之名夫神鏡之職權止於受天子崇拜是古誼也故日見之看見吾玉璽瓊々杵尊鎮魂之玉也

*'''Answer''': If the Grand Shrine of Ise is not first restored to the Imperial Court, there can be no true name of "restoration of antiquity." The authority of the divine mirror rests in receiving the veneration of the Emperor; this is the ancient principle. Therefore it is said, "Seeing this is like seeing me." The Imperial Seal is the jewel that pacifies the soul of ''Ninigi-no-Mikoto''.

天帝惟一故大陽亦惟一神界亦惟一

The Heavenly Emperor is unique, therefore the Great Sun is also unique, and the divine realm is also unique.

此地上賞罰之事皆大國主神責任也不然有害審判故於大神宮有如神罰者非天照皇神所爲有爲之者而爲之也

All matters of reward and punishment on this earth are the responsibility of ''Ōkuninushi-no-Kami''. If this were not so, it would harm fair judgment. Therefore, if there appears to be divine punishment at the Grand Shrine, it is not the doing of ''Amaterasu-Ōmikami''; there are those appointed to do it who carry it out.

問	死物不變性乎

*'''Question''': Do dead things not change their nature?

曰	死物亦變性故世之火葬者是拒絕神政之造化也况欲不朽者臣子之至情而忍之是逆道也

*'''Answer''': Dead things also change their nature. Therefore, the practice of cremation in the world is a rejection of the creation of divine administration. Moreover, desiring the body not to decay is the utmost affection of a subject or child; to bear destroying it is contrary to the Way.

問	素盞雄神與大國主神二神而一神一神而二神如何

*'''Question''': ''Susanoo-no-Kami'' and ''Ōkuninushi-no-Kami''—are they two gods as one god, or one god as two gods? How is this?

曰	二神也夫素盞雄神者指零圍氣名之大國主者指大地球名之也

*'''Answer''': They are two gods. ''Susanoo-no-Kami'' refers to the atmosphere; ''Ōkuninushi'' refers to the Great Earth.

又曰	大地球者雰圍氣所凝結也故古書說效親子非無謂也不能明視其動物植物自與石体宜

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth is the condensation of the atmosphere. Therefore, ancient books describe them in the relation of parent and child; this is not without reason. If you cannot see this clearly, consider that its animals and plants naturally correspond appropriately with its rocky body.

問	月球如何

*'''Question''': What about the Moon?

曰	月球石体故近寒

*'''Answer''': The Moon is a rocky body, hence it approaches coldness.

問	星球如何

*'''Question''': What about the Stars?

又曰	月球石体也雖有水氣不足成河海蒸發氣稀薄有零圍氣此界之人

*'''He also said''': The Moon is a rocky body. Although it has moisture, it is insufficient to form rivers and seas. Its evaporative vapors are thin, and its atmosphere contains people of that realm...

曰	各星球各異其体質而球体是爲同耳其動物植物皆與其体質宜

*'''Answer''': Each star differs in its physical substance, though they are identical in being spherical bodies. Their animals and plants are all suited to their physical substance.

問	幾萬年之後地球滅盡之說如何

*'''Question''': What of the theory that the earth will be entirely destroyed after tens of thousands of years?

上帝不爲魔誘食禁菓樹故上帝不罪汝等且呼名醫來供驚悸昏倒之用

God was not tempted by the devil to eat from the forbidden tree. Therefore, God does not punish you all, but summons famous physicians to treat those who collapse in terror.

是上帝豫言者也夫不死之上帝决不造死之物矣

This is the prophecy of God. The immortal God absolutely does not create mortal things.

靈魂者上帝所造故永々不死形骸者以雰圍氣所假造故死夫靈魂者第一造化而形骸者第二造化也今人知重形骸而不知重靈魂惑之甚也

The soul is created by God, hence it is eternally immortal. The physical body is temporarily formed from the atmosphere, hence it dies. The soul is the primary creation, while the physical body is the secondary creation. Today's people know to value the physical body but do not know to value the soul; their delusion is extreme.

問	無故拔樹壞屋者世謂之天狗之術未知禽獸之飛行空中者所爲乎

*'''Question''': Uprooting trees and destroying houses without cause is called the art of the ''Tengu'' by the world. Is it the doing of beasts and birds flying in the air?

曰	勿問飛走也有神力副焉雖螻蟻之徵可仆大厦屋有道義副焉則雖匹夫之賤可覆惡政府况有衆道者之在乎

*'''Answer''': Do not ask about flying or running creatures. If divine power assists them, even a creature as small as an ant can topple a great mansion. If moral principle assists them, even a lowly commoner can overthrow an evil government. How much more so if there is an assembly of followers of the Way!

惡人之魂經幾千萬年之久而後神歸之於元素而其間分析之苦痛拷掠不足以爲譬而後真死

The soul of a wicked person will pass through tens of millions of years before God returns it to its elements. The pain of dissolution during that time cannot be compared to any torture, and only after that does true death occur.

(此間△△△△大概)

*(In this section, text is omitted)

問	教者何

*'''Question''': What is a teacher/teaching?

曰	教者立於幽顯之間者

*'''Answer''': A teacher is one who stands between the hidden (spiritual) and the manifest (physical) worlds.

問	聖人者何

*'''Question''': What is a sage?

曰	四靈平均無過不及謂之聖々無等差[國訓聖/日靈知]

*'''Answer''': When the four spiritual souls are perfectly balanced, with neither excess nor deficiency, this is called a sage. Among sages, there are no gradations. [In the Japanese reading, "sage" (''hijiri'') means "spiritual knowledge" (''hi-shiri'').]

問	賢人者何

*'''Question''': What is a worthy man?

曰	四靈不平均有過不及謂之賢々有等差

*'''Answer''': When the four spiritual souls are imbalanced, having excess and deficiency, this is called a worthy man. Among worthies, there are gradations.

又曰	大賢與聖人邇小賢與凡人遐

*'''He also said''': Great worthies are close to sages; minor worthies are far from ordinary men.

問	聖人言行若各異其質者何

*'''Question''': Why do the words and deeds of the sages seem to differ in their substance?

曰	若各異其質者鵠不同也賢人者同鶴而不命中也

*'''Answer''': The reason they seem to differ in substance is that their targets (bullseyes) were different. Worthy men share the same target but fail to hit the center.

蓋謂見鴿而過之見鴿而不及之也

This means seeing the target and either shooting past it or falling short of it.

問	有地震雷震大風水而生民罹其災如何

*'''Question''': When there are earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods, and the people suffer their disasters, what of this?

曰	地震雷震大風水亦地政不可易之道也

*'''Answer''': Earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods are also the unalterable ways of Earth's administration.

又曰	夫天錫生民以靈魂使其知避禍就利而其罹災自取之也且雖無地震雷震大風水未有不死之人也

*'''He also said''': Heaven endows the people with souls so they may know how to avoid disaster and seek advantage. When they suffer disasters, they bring it upon themselves. Furthermore, even without earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods, there has never been an immortal human.

問	雰圍氣內亦有別神乎

*'''Question''': Are there distinct deities within the atmosphere?

曰	自有四魂存焉夫從人間視之大地球者根也而從神界視之零圍氣者根也

*'''Answer''': Naturally, the four souls exist within it. From the human perspective, the great Earth is the root, but from the perspective of the divine realm, the atmosphere is the root.

又曰	夫無大地球則無有雰圍氣無雰圍氣則無有大地球故若風雨雲雷政令出於一未會有二

*'''He also said''': Without the great Earth, there would be no atmosphere; without the atmosphere, there would be no great Earth. Therefore, things like wind, rain, clouds, and thunder all issue from a single source of command; there have never been two.

問	神告死生乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods inform us of life and death?

曰	告之生而不告之死或告之凶者以欲之生也

*'''Answer''': They inform us of life, but do not inform us of death. Sometimes they inform us of misfortune because they desire us to live.

問	神有幽明乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods have a distinction between hidden and manifest (dark and light)?

曰	唯人有幽明也神無幽明是以無內外遠近無曲直無長短

*'''Answer''': Only humans have hidden and manifest. Gods have no hidden or manifest, therefore they have no inside or outside, no far or near, no crooked or straight, no long or short.

又曰	神之子地官守也非所以爲体也人則不然体其体

*'''He also said''': The Earth is merely an office and post for the children of the gods; it is not what constitutes their body. Humans are not like this; they embody their physical forms.

又曰	大地体者資養於幽冥故不騫不崩人則不然資養於大地体故有死有病

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth body is nourished by the hidden realms, therefore it does not fail and does not collapse. Humans are not like this; they are nourished by the Great Earth body, therefore they suffer death and illness.

又曰	大地体者不騫不崩故不須有子人則死病故生子生孫

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth body does not fail and does not collapse, therefore it does not need to have offspring. Humans die and fall ill, therefore they beget children and grandchildren.

問	人之無後者爲不幸乎

*'''Question''': Is a person without descendants considered unfortunate?

曰	然雖然與姦賊之有後不如忠義之無後夫義名與天地存焉雖無有子猶有子也姦賊反之諺曰天下之至寶曰道其此之謂乎

*'''Answer''': Yes. However, having descendants as a traitor is not as good as having no descendants as a loyal and righteous person. The name of righteousness endures alongside heaven and earth; even without children, it is as if one has children. For a traitor, the opposite is true. The proverb says: "The greatest treasure under heaven is the Way." Does this not refer to this exactly?

問	卜筮如何

*'''Question''': What of divination by tortoiseshell and yarrow stalks?

曰	天地必先知之鬼神必先知之而後動乎龜著顯乎四体也

*'''Answer''': Heaven and Earth must foreknow it, and gods and spirits must foreknow it. Only then does it stir the tortoiseshell and yarrow stalks and manifest upon the four limbs.

問	神氣有問乎 ''(間)

*'''Question''': Are there gaps within divine energy?

曰	神氣無立錐之間故靈魂受授不勞迎接

*'''Answer''': Divine energy has not even the space to stand an awl. Therefore, the giving and receiving of souls requires no effort to welcome or receive them.

又曰	神氣者靈魂之與体力抱合者

*'''He also said''': Divine energy is what embraces and unites the soul and physical strength.

又曰	人之靈魂者神氣之精美者

*'''He also said''': The human soul is the most refined and beautiful part of divine energy.

問	神始造人祖亦猶兒乎

*'''Question''': When God first created the human ancestors, were they also like children?

曰	兒也

*'''Answer''': They were children.

曰	人魂之保護日月關焉乎 ''(問)

*'''Question''': Are the sun and moon involved in the protection of human souls?

曰	日月保護殊其体耳矣人魂則天帝爲主而地帝宰之也然是其生時之事死後則其最上魂專歸於天帝所轄無不至無不止

*'''Answer''': The sun and moon exclusively protect physical bodies. As for human souls, the Heavenly Emperor is their master, and the Earthly Emperor governs them. However, this applies to their time of life. After death, the highest soul returns exclusively to the jurisdiction of the Heavenly Emperor, reaching everywhere and unhindered anywhere.

問	剛柔流三体其元素幾何

*'''Question''': How many elements are there for the three states of matter: solid (rigid), yielding (soft), and fluid?

曰	元素之數五十其爲現体之用者二十五而天帝實合造化不造化而爲之故曰天帝所呼吸非現体所呼吸

*'''Answer''': The number of elements is fifty. Twenty-five of them are used for manifest bodies. The Heavenly Emperor truly combines the created and the uncreated to govern them. Therefore it is said: that which the Heavenly Emperor breathes is not what the manifest body breathes.

問	天帝有古稱乎

*'''Question''': Does the Heavenly Emperor have an ancient name?

曰	天御中主是也曰神皇產靈高皇產靈指其造化心也

*'''Answer''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi'' is the one. ''Kamimusuhi'' and ''Takamimusubi'' refer to His creative mind.

又曰	中也者無所不有天之爲大無非中也分子之爲微無非中也指示一處定爲中者受造者之論其体有限量之故也

*'''He also said''': "Center" (''Mina-ka'') means there is nothing it does not contain. The greatness of Heaven is nothing but the Center; the microscopic nature of molecules is nothing but the Center. Pointing to one spot and designating it the "center" is the logic of created beings, because their bodies have limits.

又曰	天御中主造化太陽其造化心即其中主也造化大地其造化心即其中主也造化太陰其造化心即其中主也

*'''He also said''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi'' created the Sun; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it. He created the Great Earth; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it. He created the Moon; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it.

又曰	人之靈性日中可悟其自出也

*'''He also said''': The spiritual nature of humanity is called the "Center"; from this, one can awaken to its origin.

問	天帝所賦錫靈魂未知何從而取之乎

*'''Question''': Regarding the souls bestowed by the Heavenly Emperor, from where does He draw them?

曰	天帝自分其靈魂而賦錫之也夫分而不减其本量是靈魂之所以爲靈魂也

*'''Answer''': The Heavenly Emperor divides His own spiritual soul and bestows it. To divide it without diminishing its original volume is exactly what makes a spiritual soul a spiritual soul.

問	八力之在人身中其支持靈魂者與支持体格者各別乎

*'''Question''': Regarding the eight forces within the human body, are those that support the soul and those that support the physical frame distinct from one another?

曰	其支持靈魂者亦自支持体格

*'''Answer''': That which supports the soul naturally also supports the physical frame.

問	靈魂驚悸則若八力先失而汗流油出者如何

*'''Question''': When the soul is terrified, it seems as if the eight forces are lost first, and sweat flows like oil. Why is this?

曰	八力雖支持靈魂々々實能鼓動八力々々々々而增其强盛則靈魂亦益强盛也

*'''Answer''': Although the eight forces support the soul, the soul is actually capable of stimulating the eight forces. If the forces increase their robustness, the soul also grows increasingly robust.

問	人之死靈魂與八力俱去乎

*'''Question''': When a person dies, do the soul and the eight forces depart together?

曰	八力去而人始死也

*'''Answer''': The eight forces depart, and only then does the person die.

問	四魂之用夫唯果故能進乎唯察故能巧乎唯育故能盆乎唯交故能平乎 ''(盆 is likely a typo for 益 - benefit)

*'''Question''': Regarding the functions of the four souls: Is it solely because of decisiveness that one can advance? Solely because of observation that one can be skillful? Solely because of nurturing that one can benefit? Solely because of interacting that one can be peaceful?

曰	是用中之用所當然也亦唯進故能果也唯巧故能察也唯益故能育也唯平故能交也

*'''Answer''': This is the natural course of utilizing their functions. It is also solely because of advancing that one can be decisive; solely because of skill that one can observe; solely because of benefit that one can nurture; and solely because of peace that one can interact.

問	我儕所見太陽外別又有太陽乎

*'''Question''': Outside the sun that we see, is there another sun?

曰	天帝既造一太陽足以照各現体也

*'''Answer''': The Heavenly Emperor has already created one sun; it is sufficient to illuminate all manifest bodies.

問	人魂何用或在零圍氣內或在零圍氣以外

*'''Question''': To what end does the human soul reside either within the atmosphere or outside the atmosphere?

曰	上德者自得在界圍氣外然其有用而自居雰圍氣內者其位不得不屬天神

*'''Answer''': Those of supreme virtue naturally attain a place outside the atmosphere. However, those who have a purpose and voluntarily remain within the atmosphere hold a status that cannot help but belong to the heavenly gods.

問	良知良能者如何

*'''Question''': What of innate knowledge and innate ability?

曰	善善惡惡是所謂良知良能

*'''Answer''': Loving the good and hating the evil—this is what is called innate knowledge and innate ability.

夫人既有現体則不得現世之禮不奉事于神祇是顯齋之所以興而其日用常行起居動靜之際神常照鑑之則亦不得爲之思是謂之幽齋也

Since people have manifest bodies, they cannot abandon the rites of the manifest world nor cease serving the gods; this is why the "manifest purification" (external rites) arose. But in the midst of daily affairs, normal actions, rising, resting, moving, and staying still, the gods constantly illuminate and reflect upon them, so one must not harbor improper thoughts; this is called "hidden purification" (internal rites).

問	神有名乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods have names?

曰	神界無名而有名對現人也

*'''Answer''': In the divine realm there are no names. They have names only in relation to manifest humans.

問	道即善乎

*'''Question''': Is the Way the same as the Good?

曰	道所宜履之名善純美之名

*'''Answer''': The Way is the name for what ought to be walked; the Good is the name for pure beauty.

又曰	道猶指南車也循奉而不失其心之事也

*'''He also said''': The Way is like a south-pointing chariot. It is a matter of following and revering it without losing its core principle.

又曰	道猶經也善猶緯也

*'''He also said''': The Way is like the warp (vertical threads); the Good is like the weft (horizontal threads).

又曰	有人于此謂盡吾道則將問之日天道乎地道平抑汝之道乎且夫汝道亦有類焉公道乎私道乎自門以外公道而戶庭之事私道也如何

*'''He also said''': If someone here says, "I have exhausted my way," I would ask him: "Is it the Way of Heaven? The Way of Earth? Or is it merely your way? Moreover, your way also has categories. Is it the public way or the private way? Beyond the gate is the public way, while matters of the inner courtyard are the private way. Which is it?"

問	兵吉凶如何

*'''Question''': What of the auspiciousness or inauspiciousness of weapons (the military)?

曰	兵吉器而凶器

*'''Answer''': Weapons are both instruments of good fortune and instruments of evil fortune.

問	丹後峰山大野村伊藤常八妻美與再生說如何

*'''Question''': What about the story of the reincarnation of Miyo, the wife of Itō Tsunehachi from Ōno Village, Mineyama, Tango Province?

曰	再生無理而有理天地神祇無不為也

*'''Answer''': Reincarnation contradicts natural logic, yet it possesses a logic. There is nothing that the gods of heaven and earth cannot do.

問	再生者是無本魂乎

*'''Question''': Does a reincarnated person lack their original soul?

曰	或無本魂或有本魂

*'''Answer''': Sometimes they lack their original soul, and sometimes they possess their original soul.

問	大阪鐵道有火球大三丈變爲一血頭出舌是何怪

*'''Question''': On the Osaka railway, there was a fireball three ''zhang'' (thirty feet) in size that turned into a bloody head sticking out its tongue. What kind of monster is this?

曰	天降之孽也非怪也天者神也之者指賊也賊者何慢神害民者夫賊者猶病也孽者猶藥也以藥治病天職也復何疑

*'''Answer''': It is a calamity sent down by Heaven; it is not a monster. "Heaven" means the gods. "Sent down to" points to the traitors. Who are the traitors? Those who disrespect the gods and harm the people. The traitors are like a disease, and the calamity is like the medicine. Curing a disease with medicine is the duty of Heaven; what is there to doubt?

問	作詩之要

*'''Question''': What is the essence of writing poetry?

曰	華外實內是作詩之要

*'''Answer''': Radiance on the outside, substance on the inside—this is the essence of writing poetry.

道與神一孔子之言不離道則孔子之言不離神也道也者不可須臾離則神也者不可須臾離也

The Way and the gods are one. If the words of Confucius do not depart from the Way, then the words of Confucius do not depart from the gods. "The Way cannot be left for a single moment," which means the gods cannot be left for a single moment.

又曰	聲者心之形字者聲之書

*'''He also said''': Sound is the form of the mind; characters are the writing of the sound.

問	神也者何

*'''Question''': What is a god/spirit?

曰	天地精靈氣謂之神也

*'''Answer''': The refined, spiritual pneuma of heaven and earth is called a god.

問	何謂精靈氣

*'''Question''': What is the refined, spiritual pneuma?

曰	四精神也

*'''Answer''': It is the four spiritual souls.

問	何謂四精神

*'''Question''': What are the four spiritual souls?

曰	幸魂和魂奇魂荒魂是也

*'''Answer''': They are the ''Saki-mitama'' (Fortunate Soul), ''Nigi-mitama'' (Harmonious Soul), ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul), and ''Ara-mitama'' (Rough Soul).

問	何謂幸和荒奇

*'''Question''': What is meant by Fortunate, Harmonious, Rough, and Wondrous?

曰	幸魂者仁德是也和魂者禮德是也荒魂者義德是也奇魂者智德是也

*'''Answer''': The ''Saki-mitama'' is the virtue of Benevolence. The ''Nigi-mitama'' is the virtue of Propriety. The ''Ara-mitama'' is the virtue of Righteousness. The ''Kushi-mitama'' is the virtue of Wisdom.

問	四神形象如何

*'''Question''': What are the forms and images of the four gods (souls)?

曰	元素是神故能神而通也若有定形象眞能大不能小入又能小不能大造小入大造隨時而有變而化也

*'''Answer''': Elements are gods, therefore they can be divine and penetrating. If they had fixed forms or images, they might be capable of being large but incapable of becoming small to enter things, or capable of being small but incapable of becoming large to create things. Making small, entering things, or creating large things—they change and transform according to the times.

問	然則或以爲一神或以爲多神皆非乎

*'''Question''': In that case, is it wrong to consider them as a single god, or wrong to consider them as many gods?

曰	或以爲一神以道不相爭或以爲多神以四魂

*'''Answer''': Some consider them one god, because the Way does not conflict with itself. Some consider them many gods, based on the four souls.

問	以四魂則其爲八百萬神不可乎

*'''Question''': Based on the four souls, is it not possible for them to become the eight million gods?

曰	四魂分配爲八百萬神無不可也乘數雖陞無量無數無不可也

*'''Answer''': There is nothing wrong with the four souls being distributed to become the eight million gods. Even if multiplied infinitely to countless numbers, there is nothing wrong with it.

敢問	其詳

*'''Question''': I venture to ask for details.

曰	在日爲日神在月爲月神在星爲星神在地爲地神此類推而敷衍恰無量無數也且汝精神亦四魂四神

*'''Answer''': In the sun they are the sun god, in the moon they are the moon god, in the stars they are the star god, on earth they are the earth god. Deducing and expanding from this, they are truly infinite and countless. Furthermore, your own spirit also consists of the four souls and the four gods.

問	四魂如何係著

*'''Question''': How are the four souls attached/connected?

曰	古人曰心者神明之舍夫心臟四竅豈不四魂之所在乎雖是漢字心爲四畫德字直字懷字自字俱从四魂字魄字思字皆从田田者心臟之象也試驗之乎人在胎內而其機械先成者心腦次之諸体格又次之陰部爲最後腦司体格運營而心主精神夫心病而精神不去也腦患而精神先失以是侔乎死人腦爲腦可哀也且子又試驗心意動平懼者心悸而後頭岑々憂者心作凝結而肢体無力勇者心不動而全身緊張懣者心塞而口爲吃々懼憂屬愛勇懣屬勇而腦不關也思恥之屬智而相爲耳熱謙下之屬禮而辭色和易又心臟作用四魂在心臟明矣

*'''Answer''': The ancients said, "The heart is the dwelling place of the divine illumination." Do not the four chambers of the heart represent the location of the four souls? Even looking at Chinese characters, "heart" (心) has four strokes. Characters like virtue (德), straightness (直), bosom (懷), and self (自) all relate to the four souls. Characters like soul (魄) and thought (思) all derive from the "field" (田) radical; "field" is a representation of the heart. Test this: when a person is in the womb, the first mechanism to form is the heart, followed by the brain, then the various limbs and bodily frames, and the private parts last. The brain governs the operation of the physical frame, while the heart rules the spirit. If the heart is diseased, the spirit does not depart; but if the brain suffers, the spirit is lost first. In this respect, the brain of a dead person remains a brain; how pitiable! Furthermore, you can test how the mind and intentions move. For one who is terrified, the heart palpitates, and only then does the head feel heavy. For one who is sorrowful, the heart feels frozen solid, and the limbs lose their strength. For one who is courageous, the heart remains unmoving, and the entire body tenses. For one who is frustrated, the heart feels blocked, and the mouth stutters. Fear and sorrow belong to Affection (Love); courage and frustration belong to Bravery; and the brain is not involved. Thinking and shame belong to Wisdom, mutually causing the ears to burn; humility and submissiveness belong to Propriety, rendering words and expressions gentle. Thus, it is clear that the functions of the heart demonstrate that the four souls reside within the heart.

問	神者何

*'''Question''': What is a god/spirit?

曰	元素是故人死而後歸元素亦神

*'''Answer''': Elements. Therefore, when a person dies and returns to the elements, they are also a spirit.

問	元素者何豈亦形氣乎然則精氣與形氣奚擇

*'''Question''': What are the elements? Are they also physical pneuma? If so, how does one choose between spiritual pneuma and physical pneuma?

曰	元素有二種類汝肉体與汝精神是資

*'''Answer''': There are two kinds of elements. Your fleshly body and your spirit are endowed by them.

問	精神元素一魂乎

*'''Question''': Is the spiritual element a single soul?

曰	非一魂何以知之日心臟四房是實容四魂所謂幸魂之仁也荒魂之義也奇魂之智也和魂之禮也而信者天之所屬故云誠者天之道也誠信也天以仁義禮智配人承以有之雖然人不可獨信有時乎父爲子廋子爲父廋春秋諱國惡而天不可隱味是以聰明睿智爲不可掩而又有時乎動於人故云誠之者人之道也天道人道所分判如

*'''Answer''': It is not a single soul. How do we know this? We say the four chambers of the heart actually contain the four souls: what is called the Benevolence of the ''Saki-mitama'', the Righteousness of the ''Ara-mitama'', the Wisdom of the ''Kushi-mitama'', and the Propriety of the ''Nigi-mitama''. "Trust/Sincerity" (Xin) belongs to Heaven. Therefore it is said, "Sincerity is the Way of Heaven." Sincerity is Trust. Heaven equips humans with Benevolence, Righteousness, Propriety, and Wisdom, and people inherit and possess them. However, humans cannot be exclusively trusting/sincere. Sometimes, a father covers up for his son, and a son covers up for his father. The ''Spring and Autumn Annals'' concealed the faults of the state. But Heaven cannot conceal or obscure anything; therefore its acute intelligence and profound wisdom cannot be hidden. Yet, sometimes it stirs within humans; hence it is said, "To become sincere is the Way of Man." This is how the Way of Heaven and the Way of Man are distinguished.

問	然則四魂外信亦一元素

*'''Question''': If so, then besides the four souls, is Trust/Sincerity also an element?

曰	其然雖然予試檢之元素在天互相駢列互相不雄長然則信獨屬之天道不欲復賜於人間是信獨尊矣故予謂信者仁義禮智之相約諾所以爲道々即四中中者無偏倚之謂無傍邊之謂無過不及之謂堯舜所執中其人道之中歟

*'''Answer''': That is so. Nevertheless, let me examine it: the elements exist in Heaven, arrayed side by side, none lording over the others. If Trust belongs exclusively to the Heavenly Way and is not meant to be bestowed upon the human realm, then Trust would be uniquely supreme. Therefore, I say that Trust is the mutual promise and alignment of Benevolence, Righteousness, Propriety, and Wisdom. It is what constitutes the Way. The Way is precisely the Center of the four. "Center" means having no bias, no siding, no excess, and no deficiency. The "Center" held fast by Yao and Shun—is this not the Center of the Human Way?

問	魂以顆論何

*'''Question''': Why is the soul discussed in terms of granules/particles?

曰	四魂元素說其色相耳其實元素者粒々顆々其數無邊無量無涯幾億兆萬有旬各自稱神稱中同色相感而做同感異色相合而爲同抱亦看一神也上代稱之爲天之御中主神々德及人實是人中夫天造大物其神合抱稱之造小物其神小分稱之神自由自在也人有体未能自由是莫之憾榮養原身有妻有子又有君父有朋友交際之道百年化而歸元素未晚也矣

*'''Answer''': Describing the elements of the four souls is merely discussing their appearances. In reality, the elements are myriad granules and particles; their number is boundless, measureless, limitless, numbering in the hundreds of millions, trillions, and tens of thousands. Each particle calls itself a god, calls itself the Center. Those of the same kind resonate together, creating a unified feeling; those of different kinds join together, forming a unified embrace, which is also seen as one god. Antiquity called this ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami''. Its divine virtue reaches humanity and is truly the Center of humanity. When Heaven creates large things, the gods combine and embrace to match the scale; when it creates small things, the gods minutely divide to match the scale. The gods are completely free and unhindered. Humans have physical bodies and cannot yet be free; there is no regret in this. Nourishing the original body, having a wife and children, having a lord and a father, having friends and the ways of social interaction—after a hundred years, transforming and returning to the elements will not be too late!

問	魂與神氣有以異乎

*'''Question''': Is there a difference between the soul and divine energy?

曰	魂者人之精神磅礴而爲魂者神氣則漫漶而充敷胎內者

*'''Answer''': The soul is the human spirit, majestic and concentrated into a soul; divine energy is diffuse, filling and spreading within the womb.

又曰	天地之精神是爲神是自一元体之磅礴突然人不能得而見其体則亦岐爲小分子狀是神之自由者所謂思則得也

*'''He also said''': The spirit of heaven and earth is the god. It emerges majestically from a single primal entity. Suddenly, if humans cannot perceive its body, it branches into small molecular forms. This is the freedom of the gods, as it is said, "Seek, and you shall find."

又曰	力者俗所謂魂氣也魂氣者力之異名也又俗所謂精神者則精神力而與靈魂大異也

*'''He also said''': "Force" is what the vulgar call soul-energy. Soul-energy is another name for force. Also, what the vulgar call "spirit" is actually spiritual force, which is vastly different from the soul itself.

問	然則禽獸者如何

*'''Question''': In that case, what about birds and beasts?

曰	禽獸者不足爲魂也罔神經之故也

*'''Answer''': Birds and beasts are insufficient to form a true soul, because they lack spiritual nervous systems.

問	然則其蝒動者何且狐魅之爲妖非智慧而何如何 ''(蝒 is a typo for 蠕, wriggling)

*'''Question''': In that case, what of crawling creatures? Moreover, when fox spirits and demons act as monsters, if not out of wisdom, then what is it?

曰	是神氣之所爲蓋神氣者天之未爲魂者雖無靈力亦自有靈狀狐魅得靈狀而自鍛鍊者也聊感奇魂之神氣者是大惡魔

*'''Answer''': This is the work of divine energy. Divine energy is Heaven's substance before it becomes a soul. Although it lacks spiritual force, it naturally possesses a spiritual form. Fox spirits and demons acquire this spiritual form and refine it themselves. Those who slightly resonate with the divine energy of the ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul) become great arch-demons.

問	人之始生錫靈魂幾点子乎

*'''Question''': When a human is first born, how many particles (points) of the soul are bestowed upon them?

曰	凡人之始生先錫之愛一点子而初出胎而錫奇魂勇魂親魂各一点子也

*'''Answer''': Generally, when a human is first conceived, they are first bestowed one particle of Love. The moment they emerge from the womb, they are bestowed one particle each of the Wondrous Soul (Wisdom), Courageous Soul (Bravery), and Kinship Soul.

問	然則終身是而止乎

*'''Question''': Then does it stop at this for their entire life?

曰	隨長而降之各不同

*'''Answer''': As they grow, more are sent down to them, differing for each individual.

問	如是則造物者不公平乎

*'''Question''': If this is so, is the Creator not unfair?

曰	天[此天者/地球天]之爲政決無不公平善者獨能受賞者耳矣

*'''Answer''': Heaven's [this Heaven means the Heaven of the Earth] governance is absolutely never unfair; it is merely that only the good are able to receive the rewards.

問	神道

*'''Question''': [What is] the Divine Way (Shinto)?

曰	汝知人道乎

*'''Answer''': Do you know the Human Way?

問	知之人道也者五倫也

*'''Question''': I know it. The Human Way consists of the Five Human Relationships.

曰	然則告神道也夫神亦有五倫焉凡盈於天地之間者是氣々分爲二精神元素與休養元素是也体養元素也者四十九種類而底一爲太極太極也者精神元素也精神元素亦四種類四種類相合爲一以善一以道一以中一極斯立太極也四十九加一五十也五十之數瀰々綸々無空隙也乎於是乎造物者即精神元素相謂曰吾智足以經輪吾仁足以愛被吾勇足以決進吾禮足以守成(下略)

*'''Answer''': Then I will tell you the Divine Way. The gods also have five relationships. All that fills the space between heaven and earth is pneuma (Qi). Pneuma divides into two: the spiritual elements and the nurturing elements. The physically nurturing elements comprise forty-nine types, and the underlying one is the Supreme Ultimate (''Taiji''). The Supreme Ultimate is the spiritual element. The spiritual element also consists of four types. The four types combine to form one. With Good as one, the Way as one, and the Center as one, the Ultimate is thus established as the Supreme Ultimate. Forty-nine plus one makes fifty. The number fifty fills and permeates everything, leaving no empty space. Thereupon, the Creator, which is the spiritual elements, spoke to themselves saying: "My Wisdom is sufficient to manage and organize; My Benevolence is sufficient to cover with love; My Bravery is sufficient to advance decisively; My Propriety is sufficient to preserve and maintain." (The rest is omitted).

問	幾

*'''Question''': [What of] the subtle beginnings (''ji'')?

曰	知幾者其神乎其知神之所爲乎賢矣仲舒

*'''Answer''': "He who knows the subtle beginnings is indeed divine!" Did he know the workings of the gods? How worthy was Dong Zhongshu!

問	易傳誰作

*'''Question''': Who wrote the commentaries on the ''Book of Changes'' (''Yizhuan'')?

曰	五行說仲舒爲之則易傳說五行非仲舒而何

*'''Answer''': Dong Zhongshu created the theory of the Five Phases (''Wuxing''). Since the ''Yizhuan'' explains the Five Phases, if it was not Dong Zhongshu who wrote it, then who else?

問	人會愀然日天途不可知乎

*'''Question''': People sometimes sigh mournfully and say, "The ways of Heaven cannot be known." Is this true?

曰	我亦天也天之分身也我而自知是知天也

*'''Answer''': I am also Heaven; I am an offshoot of Heaven. For me to know myself is to know Heaven.

問	智

*'''Question''': [What of] Wisdom?

曰	知所知是智

*'''Answer''': Knowing what one knows is wisdom.

問	大智

*'''Question''': [What of] Great Wisdom?

曰	不知所不知是大智

*'''Answer''': Not pretending to know what one does not know is Great Wisdom.

問	慾如何

*'''Question''': What of desire?

曰	慾者欲从心也心欲也仲尼欲明明德於天下也可見大有慾者是善矣

*'''Answer''': Desire (慾) is wishing (欲) coming from the heart (心). It is the wishing of the heart. Confucius desired to manifest luminous virtue to the world. It can be seen that having great desire is a good thing.

敢問	天亦有慾乎

*'''Question''': May I venture to ask, does Heaven also have desires?

曰	有矣天欲造化物之日善也

*'''Answer''': It does. Heaven desires that its created things become daily more good.

先生甞日余所父所師者天也天外有父者第二父也天外有師者第二師也夫父師者身之所憑學之所由也身本於天而成於父母學亦本於天而就於師者故余精神然矣

The Master once said: "That which I treat as a father and treat as a teacher is Heaven. Any father outside of Heaven is a secondary father; any teacher outside of Heaven is a secondary teacher. Fathers and teachers are what the body relies on and where learning originates. The body originates from Heaven but is formed through the parents; learning also originates from Heaven but is accomplished through the teacher. Therefore, my spirit is as it is."

問	中者何

*'''Question''': What is the "Center" (''Zhong'')?

曰	中者衷也天之所以衷其大無外其小無內也且主忠信之忠从中心則孔子之一也者中之謂也堯日以允執中終義之所在也古之帝王學士莫弗以中稱說者可見人所以衷者中也在而中也在人而中也一之謂歟天地一中蓋吾執一中以從事也

*'''Answer''': "Center" means inner core. Heaven's inner core is so great it has no outside, so small it has no inside. Moreover, the "Loyalty" (忠) in "hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary" is formed from the characters "center" (中) and "heart" (心). Thus, Confucius's "One" refers to the Center. When Yao said, "Sincerely hold fast to the Center," it indicates where ultimate righteousness lies. The ancient emperors and scholars never failed to praise and explain the Center. It can be seen that human's inner core is the Center. The center of presence, the center in humans—is this not what is called the "One"? Heaven and Earth share one Center, and I hold fast to this one Center to conduct my affairs.

又曰	執中之法審心之所先起而可有善而無惡也人之良知良能於是乎在矣

*'''He also said''': The method of holding fast to the Center is to examine what first arises in the mind, ensuring it contains good and lacks evil. Human innate knowledge and innate ability reside precisely herein.

又曰	人之体氣不一少年之日利於長進長進之害燥急故頓失中之義老年之時老練矣老鍊之蔽屈退故又輙失中之義學者宜念々在於中則中之所命者未有失焉者也

*'''He also said''': People's physical energy is not uniform. In the days of youth, they are prone to rapid growth and advancement, but the harm of this advancement is rashness and impatience; thus they suddenly lose the principle of the Center. In old age, they become experienced, but the flaw of experience is shrinking back and retreating; thus they again frequently lose the principle of the Center. Scholars ought to keep their thoughts constantly upon the Center, for those who follow the mandates of the Center have never erred.

又曰	中者有形者也文中子序說得矣而匪有象者又尤得也察於中而能不才者未之有也文中子門人陸續輩出而皆賢執中之功效也孔子門人即啓之鏞矣休矣

*'''He also said''': The Center is something that possesses form. The preface by Wenzhongzi grasped this, yet realizing it possesses no physical image grasps it even more deeply. There has never been one who examines the Center yet remains untalented. Wenzhongzi's disciples emerged one after another and were all worthies; this was the efficacy of holding fast to the Center. Confucius's disciples were the very bells that heralded this. How excellent!

又曰	顧諟天之明命者尤執中之謂也

*'''He also said''': "To carefully attend to Heaven's luminous mandate" refers precisely to holding fast to the Center.

又曰	允執厥中我國所謂天御中主神之中是也

*'''He also said''': "Sincerely holding fast to the Center"—this Center is what in our country is called the "Mina-ka" (Center) of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami''.

又曰	一以貫之即中之謂也忠即中也

*'''He also said''': "One thread running through it all" simply means the Center. Loyalty is the Center.

又曰	凡忠恕忠信之類皆以中字爲主

*'''He also said''': Generally, terms like "loyalty and empathy" or "loyalty and trustworthiness" all take the character "Center" (Zhong) as their root.

又曰	中庸云忠恕達道不遠此言非也

*'''He also said''': The ''Doctrine of the Mean'' says, "Loyalty and empathy are not far from the Way." This statement is incorrect.

又曰	主忠信無友不如已者如忠信如丘之如不如已者即不主忠信者也以反及義釋者非也

*'''He also said''': "Hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary, and have no friends who are not like yourself." "Like" means like loyalty and trustworthiness, as in "like Qiu" (Confucius's name). "Not like yourself" means those who do not hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary. To interpret this as meaning "inferior to yourself" is incorrect.

又曰	書云惟皇上帝降衷于下民若有恒性衷中也忠也若順也乃奉載天意而弗誤之謂也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' says, "The great Supreme Lord bestowed the inner core (''Zhong'') upon the lower people, to accord with their constant nature." "Inner core" is the Center; it is Loyalty. "Accord with" means to comply. This means respectfully bearing the will of Heaven without error.

又曰	洪範云于汝極錫汝保極保極者中之道也錫極者若有恒惟也

*'''He also said''': The "Great Plan" says, "To your ultimate standard, He gives the preservation of the ultimate." Preserving the ultimate is the Way of the Center. Bestowing the ultimate refers to the constant nature.

又曰	酒誥云作稽中德中德即保極也

*'''He also said''': The "Announcement about Drunkenness" says, "To investigate the central virtue." The central virtue is precisely preserving the ultimate.

又曰	中庸之中亦降衷于下民之衷庸若有恒性之恒故中與庸者聖者遺傳也

*'''He also said''': The "Zhong" (Center) in the ''Doctrine of the Mean'' is the same "inner core" bestowed upon the lower people; "Yong" (Constant/Mean) is the "constant" of the constant nature. Therefore, the concepts of Center and Mean are the legacy of the sages.

又曰	論語云天之曆數在爾躬天即我國所謂高天原是也

*'''He also said''': The ''Analects'' say, "The heavenly succession rests in your person." "Heaven" here is what in our country is called ''Takamagahara'' (the High Plain of Heaven).

又曰	書云威有一德孔子云一以貫之一即我國神代文字之——也積與縱之異制也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' says, "Majesty possesses one virtue." Confucius says, "One thread running through it all." The "One" is equivalent to the character "——" in our country's Age of the Gods script. It is just a different system of stacking or placing vertically.

又曰	子云獲罪乎天無所禱也道也者一也天地人所以一也故屬之天也所謂神者也

*'''He also said''': The Master said, "He who offends against Heaven has none to whom he can pray." The Way is One. It is that by which Heaven, Earth, and Humanity become one. Therefore it belongs to Heaven. It is what is called God.

又曰	道者神之所爲天所以爲天之實也

*'''He also said''': The Way is the doing of the gods; it is the substance of what makes Heaven, Heaven.

又曰	身也者父母之遺体也父母亦其父母之遺体也推言之天地爲父母

*'''He also said''': The body is the inherited form from one's parents. The parents are also the inherited forms from their parents. By extension, Heaven and Earth are the ultimate parents.

又曰	中神也我國所謂伊那々伎爾伎寸免留加美中也指頭爲加美亦中也是所謂魂神者也

*'''He also said''': The Center is a god. It is the "Center" in what our country calls ''Inanagi'', ''Ninigi'', and ''Sumeru-kami''. Pointing to the head as "Kami" (god/upper) also means the Center. This is what is called the soul-god.

中庸云知恥近乎勇亦誤曰知即智也

The ''Doctrine of the Mean'' says, "To know shame is close to courage." This is also an error. "Knowing" (Zhi) is precisely Wisdom (Zhi).

又曰	易云立人之道曰仁與義非也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Changes'' says, "The Way established for humanity is called benevolence and righteousness." This is incorrect.

我國所謂鎮魂則求未全錫於我者也蓋求放心之義亦同焉

What our country calls "pacifying the soul" (''Chinkon'') means seeking that which has not yet been fully bestowed upon us. The meaning of "seeking the lost mind" is also the same as this.

又曰	中神也誠亦神也道亦神也而神固一神也

*'''He also said''': The Center is a god; Sincerity is also a god; the Way is also a god. Yet the god is inherently a single god.

又曰	夫鬼神皆有形而非必無形然爲其有形亦充於天地之間故惟不能定爲形容也

*'''He also said''': Ghosts and spirits all have forms, and are not necessarily formless. However, because their forms fill the space between heaven and earth, they simply cannot be fixed into a specific shape or appearance.

問	明德如何

*'''Question''': What of luminous virtue?

曰	明德即靈魂屬於心也

*'''Answer''': Luminous virtue is the soul belonging to the heart.

又曰	夫人主魂不主体故孔子云朝聞道夕死可矣又云守死善道雖然魂依体栖宿者故体與力亦不可不養也而養魂以魂養力以力養体以体或食肉或食穀々與肉質也体亦質也以質實之物養質實之体是以体養体之理也昔陶侃朝運百甓於齋外暮運於齋內是以力養力之理也多聞道義之精神以養道義之精神是以魂養魂之理也此三者乃天地乃原则也不可不知矣

*'''He also said''': A person takes the soul as primary, not the body. Therefore Confucius said, "If one hears the Way in the morning, one may die in the evening without regret." He also said, "Hold fast to death to perfect the Way." Nevertheless, because the soul relies on the body as its dwelling, the body and its forces must also be nourished. One nourishes the soul with the soul, nourishes force with force, and nourishes the body with the body. Whether eating meat or eating grains—grains and meat are matter. The body is also matter. To nourish a material body with material objects is the principle of nourishing the body with the body. In the past, Tao Kan would move a hundred bricks outside his study in the morning, and move them back inside in the evening; this is the principle of nourishing force with force. To widely hear the spirit of moral principles in order to nourish the spirit of moral principles is the principle of nourishing the soul with the soul. These three are the fundamental principles of heaven and earth, and one must not fail to know them.

曰	我愛吾者私愛也而離其形骸而愛者正愛也離其道義而愛者邪愛也

*'''He said''': Loving myself is private love. But loving detached from the physical body is correct love. Loving detached from moral principles is wicked love.

又曰	神自神人顧自人祖不可混合

*'''He also said''': Gods are from gods, and human ancestors are from humans. They must not be conflated.

又曰	人在地上各異其國各異其邑則亦各異其言語各異其音聲是各人祖之意各異之所致若以人祖系之於神則神意不二敎其言語音聲亦應不二淺學輩以人祖爲一祖日人々言語音聲本皆一般是皆遁辭耳

*'''He also said''': Since people on earth reside in different countries and different towns, their languages and sounds also differ. This is caused by the differing intentions of their respective human ancestors. If one traces human ancestors back to the gods, the divine will is undivided; their teachings, languages, and sounds should also be undivided. Shallow scholars claim that human ancestors stem from a single ancestor, and that human languages and sounds were originally all the same; these are nothing but evasive words.

又曰	氣海無波凶賊隱身何許耳

*'''He also said''': If the sea of pneuma has no waves, where can the evil traitors hide themselves?

又曰	上代各地有大蛇因溫暖勢強也

*'''He also said''': In ancient times, there were giant serpents in various regions, due to the strength of the warm climate.

又曰	人祖之始降大地非南方而在北方蓋天帝之造大地以其初含温素過當南方熾烈不可生息而北方温熱漸適生息也故知人類之始降非南方而在北方矣

*'''He also said''': When human ancestors first descended to the earth, it was not in the South but in the North. This is because when the Heavenly Emperor created the earth, it initially contained an excess of warmth. The South was fiercely hot and incapable of sustaining life, whereas the warmth of the North gradually became suitable for life. Thus, we know that humanity's initial descent was not in the South but in the North.

又曰	書北方日幽都蓋以北方今雖幽味然實人祖之所始降而昔時嘗爲都會之地也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' calls the North the "Dark Capital" (''Youdu''). This is because, although the North is now dark and obscure, it was actually where the human ancestors first descended, and in ancient times it was a metropolitan region.

又曰	國語北方曰子々者根也乃萬物之所根始也

*'''He also said''': In the national language, the North is associated with the earthly branch ''Zi'' (Rat). ''Zi'' means root. It is the root and origin of all things.

問	中者一氣乎

*'''Question''': Is the Center a single pneuma (''Qi'')?

曰	亦有五氣故國書云五魂是五魂者爲精神之元素也

*'''Answer''': There are also five pneumas. Therefore, the national texts speak of the Five Souls. These Five Souls are the spiritual elements.

問	元素之神如何

*'''Question''': What of the gods of the elements?

問	五神之用如何

*'''Question''': What are the functions of the Five Gods?

曰	天御中主神高皇產靈神神皇產靈神甘葦芽彥舅神天常立神此五神者實爲精神元素故稱爲別天神也

*'''Answer''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami'', ''Takamimusubi-no-Kami'', ''Kamimusuhi-no-Kami'', ''Umashiashikabihikoji-no-Kami'', and ''Amenotokotachi-no-Kami''. These five gods are truly the spiritual elements, hence they are called the Separate Heavenly Deities (''Kotoamatsukami'').

曰	國書所云和魂幸魂奇魂荒魂而其一魂未聞揚言之者但說和魂禮也幸魂仁也奇魂智也荒魂義也若語一魂則一魂爲一中也中之爲用大矣蓋中猶道也以道乎四魂道猶一魂也是實五元素之稱號所以興其實爲四魂亦未不可心臟四竅職此之由

*'''He said''': The national texts mention the ''Nigi-mitama'', ''Saki-mitama'', ''Kushi-mitama'', and ''Ara-mitama'', but we rarely hear the fifth soul spoken of aloud. They merely explain that the ''Nigi-mitama'' is Propriety, the ''Saki-mitama'' is Benevolence, the ''Kushi-mitama'' is Wisdom, and the ''Ara-mitama'' is Righteousness. If we speak of the one remaining soul, it is the One Center. The function of the Center is immense! The Center is like the Way. To apply the Way to the four souls—the Way itself is like the one soul. This is the origin of the title of the Five Elements. Yet, in reality, referring to them as four souls is also acceptable. This is the reason the heart has four chambers.

問	思之思之不已鬼神佑之有是理乎

*'''Question''': "Think on it, think on it ceaselessly, and the ghosts and spirits will aid you." Does this principle hold true?

曰	有之人雖未掌等於鬼神苟思一善者則一善成應焉善者天之心也爲一巧思則一巧思成感焉巧思也天之才也

*'''Answer''': It does. Although a human may not yet equal the ghosts and spirits, if they earnestly think upon a single good, that single good will successfully elicit a response. The Good is the heart of Heaven. If they hold a single ingenious thought, that ingenious thought will successfully evoke resonance. Ingenuity is the talent of Heaven.

又曰	神也者中心也

*'''He also said''': Gods are the central core.

又曰	靈也者中與神之謂也故也與神須臾不可離者乃道之本義

*'''He also said''': "Spirit" (''Ling'') is a term for the Center and the Gods. Therefore, that "it and the gods cannot be separated for a single moment" is the fundamental meaning of the Way.

又曰	道先天地成後天地顯

*'''He also said''': The Way was formed before heaven and earth, and became manifest after heaven and earth.

又曰	靈也者神力之總稱故剖判以來萬物之離合聚散亦係于力德

*'''He also said''': "Spirit" is the collective name for divine force. Therefore, since the separation of heaven and earth, the merging, separating, gathering, and dispersing of all things are also tied to this virtuous force.

又曰	在彼不來在此不去神心中々

*'''He also said''': Being there it does not come, being here it does not go; the gods are precisely in the center of the heart.

又神魂者無光之光也矣故上屆天心下達地中無不普照可謂無量無礙光也

And the divine soul is the light without light. Therefore, reaching up to the heart of heaven and reaching down into the earth, there is nothing it does not universally illuminate. It can be called boundless, unhindered light.

又曰	四魂互爲經緯而直在其中故云五魂

*'''He also said''': The four souls serve mutually as warp and weft, while the straight line exists in the center; therefore they are called the five souls.

問	中與上帝異乎

*'''Question''': Is the Center different from the Supreme Lord (''Shangdi'')?

曰	中也者在心中之稱也而上帝也在頭上之謂也且人脚下亦有神易所謂感胖而西醫扶氏經驗書載脚下言語之病皆證脚下有神也

*'''Answer''': "Center" is the term for that which resides within the heart, whereas "Supreme Lord" is the term for that which resides above the head. Moreover, humans also have gods beneath their feet. The ''Book of Changes'' mentions "moving the big toe," and the experiential records of the Western physician Hufeland mention a disease involving speech emanating from beneath the feet, all of which proves that there are gods beneath the feet.

問	祈必益乎

*'''Question''': Does prayer definitely bring benefit?

曰	祈必益故孔子亦云吾戰必勝祭必受福是也

*'''Answer''': Prayer definitely brings benefit. Therefore, Confucius also said, "When I fight, I must win; when I sacrifice, I must receive blessings." This is what it means.

門人佐々木哲太郎輯錄於千駄谷口副島邸

*Compiled and recorded by the disciple Sasaki Tetsutarō at the Soejima residence in Sendagaya.

維時明治三十一年十二月七日抄錄終

*In this time, the thirty-first year of Meiji [1898], the 7th day of the 12th month, the copying of the record was completed.

(蒼海語錄畢)

*(End of the Sayings of Sōkai)

[[Category:Honda Chikaatsu]]</text>
      <sha1>6qog88mh13itdm0v2tslwethjgak1gd</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3756563</id>
      <parentid>3756561</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-19T19:29:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yenistardom</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <origin>3756563</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="88966" sha1="bk46pubjbgj2514t4gcdllwoi0uehv3" xml:space="preserve">'''''Sōkaisō mondō''''' (滄海窓問答) was compiled by Sasaki Tetsutarō (佐佐木哲太朗) in 1898. It is written in Literary Chinese (hence the lack of Japanese ''[[w:en:Kana|kana]]'' in the text). It contains 98 questions and answers on Soejima Taneomi's explanations of spiritual studies of [[w:en:Honda Chikaatsu|Honda Chikaatsu]] ([[w:ja:本田親徳|本田親徳]]). ''Sōkaisō mondō'' (滄海窓問答) can also be found at the end of  ([[commons:Category:幽冥秘録神仙霊典|幽冥秘録神仙霊典]], ''Yūmei Hiroku Shinsen Reiten''), which was published by [[w:en:Shintō Tenkōkyo|Shintō Tenkōkyo]] founder Tomokiyo Yoshisane ([[w:ja:友清歓真|友清歓真]]) in 1920. This version is based on Tomokiyo's 1920 edition. The text consists of nearly 100 questions from [[w:en:Soejima Taneomi|Soejima Taneomi]], along with answers from Honda Chikaatsu, about the nature of the divine, the formation of the spirit and the soul, and so on.

==Interlinear translation==
(Google Gemini 3.1 Pro Extended translation; please check for errors and improvements) 

滄海問答

*Canghai Wenda (Sōkai's Dialogues)

未定草

*Unfinished Draft

門人石舟道士輯

*Compiled by the Disciple, Daoist Sekishū

---

問	一念將動神能知之者何

*'''Question''': When a single thought is about to move, how is it that the spirits (kami) can know it?

曰	不謂善必先知之不善必先知之乎

*'''Answer''': Is it not said that "when good is about to happen, they foreknow it; when evil is about to happen, they foreknow it"?

問	以奇魂知之乎

*'''Question''': Do they know it by means of the ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul)?

曰	奇魂知奇魂和魂知和魂荒幸二魂知荒幸二魂

*'''Answer''': The ''Kushi-mitama'' knows the ''Kushi-mitama'', the ''Nigi-mitama'' (Harmonious Soul) knows the ''Nigi-mitama'', and the two souls ''Ara-mitama'' (Rough Soul) and ''Saki-mitama'' (Fortunate Soul) know the ''Ara-mitama'' and ''Saki-mitama''.

問	和魂而知他魂者何

*'''Question''': How does the ''Nigi-mitama'' know the other souls?

曰	以和魂有餘而知他魂不足以和魂不足知他魂有餘

*'''Answer''': Through the excess of the ''Nigi-mitama'' it knows the deficiency of the other souls; through the deficiency of the ''Nigi-mitama'' it knows the excess of the other souls.

問	善知不善者何

*'''Question''': How does good know what is not good?

曰	以全魂而知四魂有餘不足有餘不足者即不善

*'''Answer''': Through the complete soul, it knows the excess or deficiency of the four souls. Excess and deficiency are precisely what is not good.

問	有餘亦爲不善乎

*'''Question''': Is excess also considered not good?

曰	過猶不及

*'''Answer''': To go beyond is as wrong as to fall short.

問	各魂各用得嘗聞教未知合兩魂之用一言而可幾

*'''Question''': I have previously received teachings on the individual functions of each soul, but I do not yet know how the combined functions of two souls might be expressed in a single phrase.

曰	寬柔而教不報無道南方之强是合奇荒二魂之用者

*'''Answer''': "To teach with broad gentleness and not to exact revenge upon the unreasonable, which is the strength of the South"—this combines the functions of the ''Kushi-mitama'' and the ''Ara-mitama''.

問	寬柔者豈非和魂之用乎

*'''Question''': Is not "broad gentleness" a function of the ''Nigi-mitama''?

曰	夫教無道者智之巧寬柔者其形容也和魂者不與無道和

*'''Answer''': Teaching the unreasonable is the ingenuity of Wisdom, and broad gentleness is its outward appearance. The ''Nigi-mitama'' does not harmonize with the unreasonable.

問	神何衣何食何宅

*'''Question''': What do the spirits wear, what do they eat, and where do they dwell?

曰	衣道食道宅道如人衣於道食於道宅於道則亦猶神耳

*'''Answer''': They wear the Way, eat the Way, and dwell in the Way. If a person were to wear the Way, eat the Way, and dwell in the Way, they would be just like a spirit.

民見治于君々見養于民百官立其中間而行其義可以悟君權民權所判而百官所注意亦可定焉故百官偏頗于君則爲侫姦傾側于民則爲亂賊以審判之理言之或人或獸或禽或魚虫是正則也有居人與獸之間者有居獸與禽之間者有居禽與魚虫之間者是變則也若人惡性者蓋居人與獸之間者獸善性者亦然是所謂人面獸心與獸面人心之辨也

The people are governed by the lord, and the lord is nourished by the people; the myriad officials stand between them to practice righteousness. Through this, one can understand the distinction between sovereign rights and civil rights, and the proper focus of the officials can be established. Therefore, if officials are overly biased toward the lord, they become flattering sycophants; if they tilt completely toward the people, they become rebellious traitors. Speaking from the principle of judgment, whether human, beast, bird, or fish and insect, these follow the standard rules. There are those who dwell between humans and beasts, those who dwell between beasts and birds, and those who dwell between birds and fishes/insects; these follow anomalous rules. If a human has an evil nature, they exist between humans and beasts, and a beast with a good nature is the same. This is the distinction between "a human face with a beast's heart" and "a beast's face with a human heart."

樂若無用然使千百人一時同心志者唯樂爲然周人禮樂並稱爲和性情莫及樂也和者親和也

Music may seem useless, yet to make thousands of people unify their hearts and wills simultaneously, only music can achieve this. The people of Zhou praised Rites and Music equally; for harmonizing nature and emotion, nothing matches music. This harmony is an intimate harmony.

擊柝警夜金鼓喇吧指揮三軍亦皆與樂同用所以一其心志也

Striking the watchman's clapper to warn the night, or using gongs, drums, and trumpets to command the armies, are all used in the same manner as music, serving to unify their hearts and wills.

靈威亦猶樂也有聲響于此誰不愕然者誰不敬畏者按孔子迅雷風烈必變有以也

Spiritual majesty is also like music. If a great sound echoes here, who would not be startled? Who would not be in awe? Consider that Confucius would change his countenance at sudden claps of thunder or fierce winds; there is a reason for this.

問	役小角役使鬼魅何術

*'''Question''': By what art did En no Ozuno control and command ghosts and demons?

曰	人有魔性者能與魔魅感如役小角是也前所謂人面獸心者即魔性也

*'''Answer''': A person who possesses a demonic nature can resonate with demons and spirits, as was the case with En no Ozuno. What was previously called "a human face with a beast's heart" is exactly this demonic nature.

問	伊勢神宮其他神社等有不由人火而燒亡者如何

*'''Question''': How is it that the Grand Shrine of Ise and other shrines are sometimes destroyed by fires not caused by humans?

曰	神怒所有激發生火警猶凡人慣恚滿面發赤不意生火而生火也固與魔魅好事出火異矣

*'''Answer''': The anger of the gods causes a sudden sparking of fire, just as an ordinary person, filled with rage, flushes red in the face, involuntarily generating heat. This is fundamentally different from demons mischievously starting fires.

同之一神也而其所嗣各不同其功用者祭人本意所有各不同也即神人相感之理也故在人應慎勿思不祥言不祥行也則神人相感不啻無不祥[禮內則胎教／之條可思]至于顯許多功用矣

It is the same single deity, yet their manifestations and functions differ because the fundamental intentions of the worshippers differ. This is the principle of mutual resonance between gods and humans. Therefore, humans must be careful not to think inauspicious thoughts, speak inauspicious words, or perform inauspicious deeds. Then, the mutual resonance between gods and humans will not only prevent the inauspicious [one may consider the section on prenatal education in the "Neize" chapter of the ''Book of Rites''], but will also manifest many beneficial functions.

在廟堂上思安民則必獲安民矣提三軍衆思勝敵則必獲勝敵矣有神人相感者然

If one is in the imperial court and thinks of bringing peace to the people, they will surely achieve peace for the people. If one leads the armies and the multitudes think of defeating the enemy, they will surely defeat the enemy. This is so because of the mutual resonance between gods and humans.

靈光靈動靈聲靈香靈味靈觸是謂靈威凡是等事神非好事爲之神意所透徹自顯此靈威

Spiritual light, spiritual movement, spiritual sound, spiritual scent, spiritual taste, and spiritual touch—these are called spiritual majesty. In all these matters, it is not that the gods do them mischievously; rather, where the divine will penetrates deeply, this spiritual majesty naturally manifests.

問	古人言望雲氣知吉凶有理乎

*'''Question''': The ancients said that by observing the clouds and vapors, one can know good and bad fortune. Is there reason in this?

曰	無此理也大概皆托神異圖名利者但如北魏崔浩明劉基固旣推擴事理而察知其吉凶而托之於天文地理者蓋神妙其說也凡治亂興廢決於行道義與否也

*'''Answer''': There is no such reason. Generally, these are just people feigning divine anomalies to scheme for fame and profit. However, figures like Cui Hao of the Northern Wei and Liu Ji of the Ming had already deduced the principles of affairs to perceive good and bad fortune, and then merely attributed them to astronomy and geography to mystify their explanations. Ultimately, order and chaos, rise and fall, are determined by whether or not moral principles are practiced.

夫易說貞凶天地間有此理乎若說貞凶則將說不貞吉平舜事瞽叟孝道也文王囚羌里忠道也可以爲凶乎凶在彼而不在己

The ''Book of Changes'' speaks of "uprightness leading to misfortune." Can such a principle exist between heaven and earth? If uprightness leads to misfortune, would they say being un-upright is auspicious? Shun serving Gu Sou was the path of filial piety; King Wen being imprisoned in Youli was the path of loyalty. Can these be considered inauspicious? The misfortune lies with the others, not with oneself.

樂器猶筆也筆工之作筆其製一般也而有書道德仁義有書雜話小說由其書之者不同也雖二絃琴使陶淵明彈之則不可謂無神祇守護

A musical instrument is like a brush. When a brush maker makes brushes, the design is the same, yet some are used to write of the Dao, Virtue, Benevolence, and Righteousness, while others are used to write idle chatter and fiction; this is due to the difference in the writers. Even a simple two-stringed zither, if played by Tao Yuanming, could not be said to lack the protection of the gods.

有同一異事于此不問其爲神異爲魔異先問其本主有德無德則其爲顧祥爲妖孽不辨可知猶富家翁有二子一喜勤儉一好游蕩而翁各與之萬金則一益勤儉爲富一盒游蕩至亡其身也

If the same anomalous event occurs, do not ask whether it is a divine anomaly or a demonic anomaly; first ask whether its primary owner possesses virtue or lacks virtue. Then, whether it is an auspicious omen or a monstrous calamity will be known without need for debate. It is like a rich old man who has two sons: one loves diligence and thrift, the other loves debauchery. If the old man gives them each ten thousand pieces of gold, the first will become even more diligent and wealthy, while the second will squander it entirely until he destroys himself.

樂之不可無吉凶軍賓嘉皆爲然

Music cannot exist without the context of auspiciousness, inauspiciousness, military matters, welcoming guests, or joyous occasions; all are thus.

歌辭與聲律相稱是正樂不相稱者所謂鄭聲也

When the lyrics and the musical pitch are in harmony, it is proper music. When they do not harmonize, it is what is called the "Sounds of Zheng" (decadent music).

樂器則古法可矣凡在後世須要言古人所不言行古人所不行發明古人所不發明今則專精樂器其所造雖工智不足稱也

For musical instruments, the ancient methods are sufficient. Generally, in later generations, it is essential to speak what the ancients did not speak, to do what the ancients did not do, and to invent what the ancients did not invent. But today, people only specialize in perfecting musical instruments; though their craftsmanship is skilled, their wisdom is not worth praising.

樂唯在交際上用之者今若自鳴琴猶自鳴鐘蓋屬玩物者不可謂之樂器也夫樂者人與人相對手舞足蹈足以和性情也故日在交際上用之

Music is solely meant to be used in social interaction. Today, a self-playing piano is like a chiming clock—it belongs to the category of playthings and cannot be called a musical instrument. Music is when people face one another, their hands dancing and feet tapping, sufficiently harmonizing their natures and emotions. Therefore it is said to be used in social interaction.

人生而其靈始顯然其父母交感之時既備得魂體力之三者不然及其生何種子能突然引天地之靈乎唯其在胎內其魂與母氏接續耳而其實母胎包羅之猶天地包羅人也

When a human is born, their spirit first becomes manifest. Yet, at the moment of their parents' intercourse, they are already endowed with the three elements: soul, body, and vital force. If this were not so, by what seed could they suddenly draw down the spirit of heaven and earth upon being born? It is just that while in the womb, their soul is continuously connected with the mother. In truth, the mother's womb encompasses the child just as heaven and earth encompass humanity.

問	元宋邦昌者釋奠孔廟俄然風起殿上吹拔殿中鎮樽時人皆以爲孔子威靈未知如何

*'''Question''': During the Yuan dynasty, when Song Bangchang was performing a sacrifice at the Temple of Confucius, a sudden wind rose in the hall and blew away the sacrificial vessels inside. People of the time all considered this to be Confucius's spiritual majesty. I do not know how this is?

曰	是爲回應凡孔子所述作諸書皆其威靈至今有感服天下人心蓋在道義上不可不如此說語日子不語怪力亂神其生平如此况死後乎唯自他論之謂其威靈所然亦未爲不可

*'''Answer''': This was a response. All the books written by Confucius are his spiritual majesty; to this day they possess the power to move and subdue the hearts of people worldwide. From the perspective of moral principles, one must explain it this way. The ''Analects'' say, "The Master did not speak of anomalies, feats of strength, rebellions, or spirits." His life was like this, how much more so after his death? However, if judging from the perspective of others, it is not entirely unacceptable to attribute it to his spiritual majesty.

孔子溫良恭謙讓適所以盛其威靈孔子不謂鬼神之爲德其盛矣若夫反之者其平生發露無復餘薀何威靈之有

Confucius was gentle, upright, courteous, temperate, and yielding; this is exactly what magnified his spiritual majesty. Confucius did not say that the virtue of ghosts and spirits was abundant. As for those who are the opposite, their entire lives are exposed with nothing left in reserve—what spiritual majesty could they possess?

孔子平生實能認識神祇威靈故其所慎齋戰疾

Confucius, in his lifetime, truly could recognize the spiritual majesty of the deities, which is why the things he exercised the greatest caution over were fasting, war, and sickness.

怪力亂神二事也亂神後世所謂瀋祠之類左傳石言是其一

Anomalous strength and chaotic spirits are two different things. "Chaotic spirits" refer to what later generations call illicit shrines and the like; the "speaking stone" in the ''Zuo Zhuan'' is one example.

夫以實事論者道義上正則譬風謂之風光謂之光色謂之色聲謂之聲之類然非其時非其所非其物而顯其異者不可不謂之威靈也凡自祭法言之威靈也

Discussing it based on actual events: if it follows the standard of natural laws, then wind is called wind, light is called light, form is called form, and sound is called sound. But when anomalies manifest outside their proper time, place, or natural state, they must be called spiritual majesty. Generally, from the perspective of sacrificial rites, it is called spiritual majesty.

同一異事而賢人君子視之謂之祥瑞亂臣賊子視之謂之妖孽由道義上判之謂之異事

Regarding the very same anomalous event, sages and noblemen see it and call it an auspicious sign; rebellious ministers and traitors see it and call it a monstrous calamity. Judged from the standpoint of moral principles, it is simply called an anomaly.

問	祭法者如何

*'''Question''': What of the sacrificial rites?

曰	禮記祭法日山林川谷丘陵能出雲爲風雨見怪物皆日神々者猶靈威也神威也夫能以誠祭神必有靈益祭必受福禮明教也日祭無益豈非殷紂罪狀之一乎

*'''Answer''': The ''Book of Rites'', in the "Law of Sacrifices," says: "Mountains, forests, rivers, valleys, hills, and mounds, which can produce clouds and make wind and rain, and manifest anomalous things, are all called deities." "Deity" here implies spiritual majesty and divine power. If one can sacrifice to the spirits with sincerity, there will definitely be spiritual benefit. "Sacrifice inevitably brings blessings" is the clear teaching of the rites. To claim that sacrifices bring no benefit—was this not one of the crimes of King Zhou of Shang?

夫不脩農政而祈年穀豊饒固見其無靈念也人事神事並舉而無靈益者未之有也

To neglect agricultural administration while praying for an abundant harvest is a clear sign of lacking true spiritual mindfulness. There has never been a case where human effort and divine service were conducted together without yielding spiritual benefit.

孔子明道盡義又能熟知祭法是孔子之所以爲聖人

Confucius illuminated the Way, exhausted righteousness, and was deeply versed in the sacrificial rites; this is what made Confucius a sage.

問	孔子謂非其鬼而祭謟也又釋奠孔子母乃不可乎

*'''Question''': Confucius said, "To sacrifice to a spirit which does not belong to you is flattery." Is it then inappropriate to perform sacrifices to Confucius?

曰	國家祭聖賢忠孝貞烈之靈欲使天下後世儀刑之也非非其鬼而祭之類也唯在人民不爲其孫子者不可自爲祭主耳孔子所云爾者謂祭無主墓之類也

*'''Answer''': The state sacrifices to the spirits of sages, worthies, the loyal, the filial, and the fiercely chaste to make them models for the world and future generations. This is not the same as "sacrificing to a spirit that does not belong to you." It is only that common people who are not his descendants cannot set themselves up as the chief mourner/officiant. What Confucius referred to was the practice of offering sacrifices to untended graves and the like.

問	敬鬼神而遠之何謂也

*'''Question''': What does it mean to "respect spiritual beings but keep them at a distance"?

曰	遠之猶謂不擾避席下階敬之至義之盡也有一貴人于此正色端坐衣履顧類之匹夫能與之並坐乎意應人間無此法也蓋孔子能擴充人間法者也孔子所謂未能事人安能事鬼者無他亦謂推人及鬼耳若將推鬼及人其必陷巫頭流

*'''Answer''': "Keeping them at a distance" means not disturbing them, yielding one's seat, and stepping down from the hall; it is the utmost respect and the exhaustion of righteousness. Suppose there is a nobleman sitting here with a solemn expression and formal attire; could a commoner in ragged clothes sit beside him? Such a practice surely does not exist in the human world. Confucius was one who could extend the laws of the human world. When Confucius said, "While you cannot serve men, how can you serve spirits?", he simply meant projecting human principles onto spirits. If one projects spiritual matters onto humans, they will inevitably fall into the way of shamans and sorcerers.

問	今世間喪者有嫌火潔穢之事如何

*'''Question''': In the present world, mourners avoid using fire from the same hearth to avoid pollution. What about this?

曰	是非人情也厚其生而薄其死以人骸爲穢夫以人骸爲穢而食禽獸虫魚死物而不爲穢何其謬也夫禽獸虫魚死物猶供之於鬼神而爲禮乎

*'''Answer''': This goes against human feelings. It values life but treats death lightly, viewing human remains as impure. To consider human remains impure, while eating the dead bodies of beasts, birds, insects, and fish without considering them impure—how absurd! Can the dead bodies of beasts, birds, insects, and fish still be offered to gods and spirits as a proper rite?

神不食祭物然祭物其必享之享者歡也非食之謂也夫人以誠敬祭之而不饗之者頑鬼也頑鬼者在草葬者也

The spirits do not physically eat the sacrificial offerings, yet they must "enjoy" them. To "enjoy" means to take pleasure in them, not to eat them. If people sacrifice with sincere respect and the spirit does not enjoy it, it is an obstinate ghost. An obstinate ghost is one buried carelessly in the wild.

豊臣秀吉之裁禍亂漢高祖之定國佛拿勃列翁之踐帝位本皆微賤而能如此者唯在一立志耳如高祖見禽其父而不屈秀吉自質其母而不厭拿勃列翁流竄一孤嶋而能奮者其勇决亦可知矣

Toyotomi Hideyoshi quelling chaos, Han Gaozu pacifying the nation, and Napoleon ascending the imperial throne—they were all originally of humble origins, and were able to achieve these things simply through a firm resolve. Gaozu saw his father captured yet did not yield; Hideyoshi offered his mother as a hostage without hesitation; Napoleon was exiled to a lonely island yet still rose up. Their resolute courage can be understood from this.

歆羨他人不及自爲之勝

Admiring others is not as good as taking action oneself.

無其所期而琢磨靈魂蓋亦爲難能矣

To refine one's soul without having a clear expectation or goal is indeed a difficult feat.

問	造語法亦自有四魂之別乎

*'''Question''': In the formation of words, is there also a distinction based on the four souls?

曰	聲以心爲主故其造語無細大見四魂之別

*'''Answer''': Sounds are governed by the heart/mind; therefore, in word formation, regardless of magnitude, the distinction of the four souls is evident.

問	大物忌神名義如何

*'''Question''': What is the meaning of the name "Omonoimi-no-kami" (Deity of Great Abstinence/Offerings)?

曰	物忌謂膳部等諸供物也

*'''Answer''': "Monoimi" (Offerings) refers to provisions and various sacrificial items.

問	既有神憑之道其所以質道義辨是非者不復須用太占法而可如何

*'''Question''': Since there is the path of divine possession to question moral principles and distinguish right from wrong, is there no longer a need to use the grand divination method (''Futomani'')? How is this?

曰	神憑自神太占自人故神憑無弗的中太占自非聰明睿智不能中之

*'''Answer''': Divine possession originates from the gods, while grand divination originates from humans. Therefore, divine possession never misses the mark, whereas grand divination cannot be accurate unless performed by someone with acute intelligence and profound wisdom.

問	墓祭禮乎

*'''Question''': Is sacrificing at a tomb in accordance with the rites?

曰	祭斯靈格如之何其爲非禮唯以其禮爲在地中不可

*'''Answer''': Sacrificing to this spiritual presence—how could it be against the rites? It is only improper to assume that the object of the rite is confined within the earth.

夫人盡禮而祭之而神不歡之是神不神終不能神也

If a person exhausts the rites to sacrifice to them, and the spirit does not rejoice, then the spirit is not acting as a spirit, and ultimately cannot be divine.

神與人言神事其聲洞轍一神界百神成聽夫言神事而不能聽者非神也

When a god speaks to a human about divine matters, the voice resonates thoroughly; if one divine realm hears it, a hundred gods all listen. Those who speak of divine matters but cannot hear are not gods.

夫以神爲人以人爲神是謂亂名語日必也正名乎

To treat gods as humans, or to treat humans as gods, is called confusing names. As the ''Analects'' say, "What is necessary is to rectify names."

アワハサャマナカクラ是韵例也マノミモム或タテチトッ是同聲例也聲以爲語々有聲通世以爲韻通非也

A-wa-ha-sa-ya-ma-na-ka-ku-ra are examples of rhymes. Ma-no-mi-mo-mu or ta-te-chi-to-tsu are examples of identical initial consonants. Sounds form words, and words have phonetic resonance. The world thinks this is rhyming, but it is not.

彦火々出見尊火出体之義後世國學者以火爲稻穗之義誤矣火進命火明命之名悉非稻穗之義觀其產時之行事可見蓋以火爲祥瑞而命名也忍穗根命之名義大靈根也瓊々杵尊之名義和也以和一字爲人民主凡人君臨人民不可不以和爲先其他諸魂蓋從其後也夫忍穗根爲大靈根是以元素鍛鍊爲体其不飲食推名義可知助字之津者接續辭其義不同」靈魂以鍛鍊琢磨爲貴

*''Hikohohodemi-no-Mikoto'' means the manifestation of fire. Later Kokugaku (National Learning) scholars mistakenly took "fire" (''ho'') to mean "rice ears" (''ho''). The names ''Hososuseri-no-Mikoto'' and ''Hoakari-no-Mikoto'' absolutely do not mean rice ears; looking at the events during their births, this is evident. They were named taking fire as an auspicious sign. The name ''Oshihomimi-no-Mikoto'' means "Great Spiritual Root." The name ''Ninigi-no-Mikoto'' means "Harmony." Using the single character for "harmony" designates the ruler of the people. Generally, when a ruler presides over the people, they must place harmony first, and the other souls must follow after. ''Oshihomimi'' represents the Great Spiritual Root, utilizing elemental refinement as its form; its lack of eating or drinking can be deduced from its name. The auxiliary character ''tsu'' is a connective particle with a different meaning. The soul values refinement and polishing above all.

力者道体之義也体力者第二義也夫有道力而能發体力也未有体力能發道力也是有御中主神道力而後有天地萬物也

"Force" means the substance of the Way. Physical strength is a secondary meaning. Only when there is the force of the Way can physical strength be generated; physical strength has never been able to generate the force of the Way. Thus, it was the force of the Way of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami'' that existed first, and only afterward did heaven, earth, and all things come into being.

大地球自有地道大陽國自有大陽道月國自有月道眾星國自有衆星道而悉皆莫不本於天御中主大道矣

The great earth has its own earthly Way, the realm of the Sun has its own solar Way, the realm of the Moon has its own lunar Way, and the realm of the Myriad Stars has its own stellar Way. Yet, none of these fail to be rooted in the Great Way of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi''.

問	高津神者何

*'''Question''': What are the ''Takatsu-kami'' (High Deities)?

曰	世人所謂天狗者人神之而非神也夫天狗者混鳥獸之稱也然是語對高津鳥而言之則專指獸類也

*'''Answer''': What people of the world call ''Tengu''. People deify them, but they are not gods. ''Tengu'' is a mixed term for birds and beasts. However, when this term is contrasted with "Takatsu-tori" (High Birds), it specifically refers to beasts.

凡言道不言神言神不言道何則神道不二也

Generally, if one speaks of the Way, one does not need to speak of the gods; if one speaks of the gods, one does not need to speak of the Way. Why? Because gods and the Way are not two separate things.

問	世俗所言天狗者如何

*'''Question''': What about what the common people call ''Tengu''?

曰	夫有肉体而變幻爲奇異者自体上言之謂之天狗自道義上言之謂之魔

*'''Answer''': Those who have physical bodies but transform into bizarre illusions are called ''Tengu'' from the perspective of their physical form, but from the perspective of moral principles, they are called demons.

又曰	夫天狗等之現体物譬猶器械屬諸忠臣之手則誅斬亂賊也

*'''He also said''': These physical entities like ''Tengu'' are like tools; if they fall into the hands of loyal ministers, they will execute rebels and traitors.

又曰	夫天狗之爲行未必有惡事但至其思想不能盡脫惡意是所以稱魔物也

*'''He also said''': The actions of ''Tengu'' are not necessarily evil deeds, but when it comes to their thoughts, they cannot entirely rid themselves of evil intentions. That is why they are called demonic entities.

問	神亦可見乎

*'''Question''': Can the gods be seen?

曰	可見焉雄略帝之見一言主神其君臣皆見之也是其證神雖幽体現々亦易

*'''Answer''': They can be seen. Emperor Yūryaku saw the deity ''Hitokotonushi'', and both the sovereign and his ministers saw him. This is the proof. Although the gods are ethereal bodies, manifesting is quite easy for them.

莫貴於道義也荷能執持道義則雖不遇於時猶遺芳後世況遇者平日夫登神界者之土產惟道義而已矣

Nothing is more precious than moral principles. If one can hold fast to moral principles, even if unrecognized in their time, they will leave a fragrant legacy for later generations—how much more so for those who do meet their time! The only "souvenir" one brings when ascending to the divine realm is moral principle, nothing else.

敢問	伊勢神靈乎

*'''Question''': May I venture to ask, is the deity at Ise a divine spirit?

曰	直視天照皇大日靈貴神而可矣所憑伊勢神鏡之靈是自有限界者雖然一滴之水々則水神鏡之靈不可謂非天照皇也

*'''Answer''': You may regard it directly as ''Amaterasu-Ōmikami'' (the Great Sun Goddess). The spirit residing in the divine mirror at Ise naturally has its limits. Nevertheless, just as a single drop of water is still water, the spirit of the divine mirror cannot be said to not be ''Amaterasu''.

問	他日朝廷有復古之事則伊勢神宮如何而可

*'''Question''': In the future, if the Imperial Court undergoes a restoration of antiquity, what should be done regarding the Grand Shrine of Ise?

曰	先不復伊勢神宮於朝廷則當無復古之名夫神鏡之職權止於受天子崇拜是古誼也故日見之看見吾玉璽瓊々杵尊鎮魂之玉也

*'''Answer''': If the Grand Shrine of Ise is not first restored to the Imperial Court, there can be no true name of "restoration of antiquity." The authority of the divine mirror rests in receiving the veneration of the Emperor; this is the ancient principle. Therefore it is said, "Seeing this is like seeing me." The Imperial Seal is the jewel that pacifies the soul of ''Ninigi-no-Mikoto''.

天帝惟一故大陽亦惟一神界亦惟一

The Heavenly Emperor is unique, therefore the Great Sun is also unique, and the divine realm is also unique.

此地上賞罰之事皆大國主神責任也不然有害審判故於大神宮有如神罰者非天照皇神所爲有爲之者而爲之也

All matters of reward and punishment on this earth are the responsibility of ''Ōkuninushi-no-Kami''. If this were not so, it would harm fair judgment. Therefore, if there appears to be divine punishment at the Grand Shrine, it is not the doing of ''Amaterasu-Ōmikami''; there are those appointed to do it who carry it out.

問	死物不變性乎

*'''Question''': Do dead things not change their nature?

曰	死物亦變性故世之火葬者是拒絕神政之造化也况欲不朽者臣子之至情而忍之是逆道也

*'''Answer''': Dead things also change their nature. Therefore, the practice of cremation in the world is a rejection of the creation of divine administration. Moreover, desiring the body not to decay is the utmost affection of a subject or child; to bear destroying it is contrary to the Way.

問	素盞雄神與大國主神二神而一神一神而二神如何

*'''Question''': ''Susanoo-no-Kami'' and ''Ōkuninushi-no-Kami''—are they two gods as one god, or one god as two gods? How is this?

曰	二神也夫素盞雄神者指零圍氣名之大國主者指大地球名之也

*'''Answer''': They are two gods. ''Susanoo-no-Kami'' refers to the atmosphere; ''Ōkuninushi'' refers to the Great Earth.

又曰	大地球者雰圍氣所凝結也故古書說效親子非無謂也不能明視其動物植物自與石体宜

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth is the condensation of the atmosphere. Therefore, ancient books describe them in the relation of parent and child; this is not without reason. If you cannot see this clearly, consider that its animals and plants naturally correspond appropriately with its rocky body.

問	月球如何

*'''Question''': What about the Moon?

曰	月球石体故近寒

*'''Answer''': The Moon is a rocky body, hence it approaches coldness.

問	星球如何

*'''Question''': What about the Stars?

又曰	月球石体也雖有水氣不足成河海蒸發氣稀薄有零圍氣此界之人

*'''He also said''': The Moon is a rocky body. Although it has moisture, it is insufficient to form rivers and seas. Its evaporative vapors are thin, and its atmosphere contains people of that realm...

曰	各星球各異其体質而球体是爲同耳其動物植物皆與其体質宜

*'''Answer''': Each star differs in its physical substance, though they are identical in being spherical bodies. Their animals and plants are all suited to their physical substance.

問	幾萬年之後地球滅盡之說如何

*'''Question''': What of the theory that the earth will be entirely destroyed after tens of thousands of years?

上帝不爲魔誘食禁菓樹故上帝不罪汝等且呼名醫來供驚悸昏倒之用

God was not tempted by the devil to eat from the forbidden tree. Therefore, God does not punish you all, but summons famous physicians to treat those who collapse in terror.

是上帝豫言者也夫不死之上帝决不造死之物矣

This is the prophecy of God. The immortal God absolutely does not create mortal things.

靈魂者上帝所造故永々不死形骸者以雰圍氣所假造故死夫靈魂者第一造化而形骸者第二造化也今人知重形骸而不知重靈魂惑之甚也

The soul is created by God, hence it is eternally immortal. The physical body is temporarily formed from the atmosphere, hence it dies. The soul is the primary creation, while the physical body is the secondary creation. Today's people know to value the physical body but do not know to value the soul; their delusion is extreme.

問	無故拔樹壞屋者世謂之天狗之術未知禽獸之飛行空中者所爲乎

*'''Question''': Uprooting trees and destroying houses without cause is called the art of the ''Tengu'' by the world. Is it the doing of beasts and birds flying in the air?

曰	勿問飛走也有神力副焉雖螻蟻之徵可仆大厦屋有道義副焉則雖匹夫之賤可覆惡政府况有衆道者之在乎

*'''Answer''': Do not ask about flying or running creatures. If divine power assists them, even a creature as small as an ant can topple a great mansion. If moral principle assists them, even a lowly commoner can overthrow an evil government. How much more so if there is an assembly of followers of the Way!

惡人之魂經幾千萬年之久而後神歸之於元素而其間分析之苦痛拷掠不足以爲譬而後真死

The soul of a wicked person will pass through tens of millions of years before God returns it to its elements. The pain of dissolution during that time cannot be compared to any torture, and only after that does true death occur.

(此間△△△△大概)

*(In this section, text is omitted)

問	教者何

*'''Question''': What is a teacher/teaching?

曰	教者立於幽顯之間者

*'''Answer''': A teacher is one who stands between the hidden (spiritual) and the manifest (physical) worlds.

問	聖人者何

*'''Question''': What is a sage?

曰	四靈平均無過不及謂之聖々無等差[國訓聖/日靈知]

*'''Answer''': When the four spiritual souls are perfectly balanced, with neither excess nor deficiency, this is called a sage. Among sages, there are no gradations. [In the Japanese reading, "sage" (''hijiri'') means "spiritual knowledge" (''hi-shiri'').]

問	賢人者何

*'''Question''': What is a worthy man?

曰	四靈不平均有過不及謂之賢々有等差

*'''Answer''': When the four spiritual souls are imbalanced, having excess and deficiency, this is called a worthy man. Among worthies, there are gradations.

又曰	大賢與聖人邇小賢與凡人遐

*'''He also said''': Great worthies are close to sages; minor worthies are far from ordinary men.

問	聖人言行若各異其質者何

*'''Question''': Why do the words and deeds of the sages seem to differ in their substance?

曰	若各異其質者鵠不同也賢人者同鶴而不命中也

*'''Answer''': The reason they seem to differ in substance is that their targets (bullseyes) were different. Worthy men share the same target but fail to hit the center.

蓋謂見鴿而過之見鴿而不及之也

This means seeing the target and either shooting past it or falling short of it.

問	有地震雷震大風水而生民罹其災如何

*'''Question''': When there are earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods, and the people suffer their disasters, what of this?

曰	地震雷震大風水亦地政不可易之道也

*'''Answer''': Earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods are also the unalterable ways of Earth's administration.

又曰	夫天錫生民以靈魂使其知避禍就利而其罹災自取之也且雖無地震雷震大風水未有不死之人也

*'''He also said''': Heaven endows the people with souls so they may know how to avoid disaster and seek advantage. When they suffer disasters, they bring it upon themselves. Furthermore, even without earthquakes, thunderstorms, great winds, and floods, there has never been an immortal human.

問	雰圍氣內亦有別神乎

*'''Question''': Are there distinct deities within the atmosphere?

曰	自有四魂存焉夫從人間視之大地球者根也而從神界視之零圍氣者根也

*'''Answer''': Naturally, the four souls exist within it. From the human perspective, the great Earth is the root, but from the perspective of the divine realm, the atmosphere is the root.

又曰	夫無大地球則無有雰圍氣無雰圍氣則無有大地球故若風雨雲雷政令出於一未會有二

*'''He also said''': Without the great Earth, there would be no atmosphere; without the atmosphere, there would be no great Earth. Therefore, things like wind, rain, clouds, and thunder all issue from a single source of command; there have never been two.

問	神告死生乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods inform us of life and death?

曰	告之生而不告之死或告之凶者以欲之生也

*'''Answer''': They inform us of life, but do not inform us of death. Sometimes they inform us of misfortune because they desire us to live.

問	神有幽明乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods have a distinction between hidden and manifest (dark and light)?

曰	唯人有幽明也神無幽明是以無內外遠近無曲直無長短

*'''Answer''': Only humans have hidden and manifest. Gods have no hidden or manifest, therefore they have no inside or outside, no far or near, no crooked or straight, no long or short.

又曰	神之子地官守也非所以爲体也人則不然体其体

*'''He also said''': The Earth is merely an office and post for the children of the gods; it is not what constitutes their body. Humans are not like this; they embody their physical forms.

又曰	大地体者資養於幽冥故不騫不崩人則不然資養於大地体故有死有病

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth body is nourished by the hidden realms, therefore it does not fail and does not collapse. Humans are not like this; they are nourished by the Great Earth body, therefore they suffer death and illness.

又曰	大地体者不騫不崩故不須有子人則死病故生子生孫

*'''He also said''': The Great Earth body does not fail and does not collapse, therefore it does not need to have offspring. Humans die and fall ill, therefore they beget children and grandchildren.

問	人之無後者爲不幸乎

*'''Question''': Is a person without descendants considered unfortunate?

曰	然雖然與姦賊之有後不如忠義之無後夫義名與天地存焉雖無有子猶有子也姦賊反之諺曰天下之至寶曰道其此之謂乎

*'''Answer''': Yes. However, having descendants as a traitor is not as good as having no descendants as a loyal and righteous person. The name of righteousness endures alongside heaven and earth; even without children, it is as if one has children. For a traitor, the opposite is true. The proverb says: "The greatest treasure under heaven is the Way." Does this not refer to this exactly?

問	卜筮如何

*'''Question''': What of divination by tortoiseshell and yarrow stalks?

曰	天地必先知之鬼神必先知之而後動乎龜著顯乎四体也

*'''Answer''': Heaven and Earth must foreknow it, and gods and spirits must foreknow it. Only then does it stir the tortoiseshell and yarrow stalks and manifest upon the four limbs.

問	神氣有問乎 ''(間)

*'''Question''': Are there gaps within divine energy?

曰	神氣無立錐之間故靈魂受授不勞迎接

*'''Answer''': Divine energy has not even the space to stand an awl. Therefore, the giving and receiving of souls requires no effort to welcome or receive them.

又曰	神氣者靈魂之與体力抱合者

*'''He also said''': Divine energy is what embraces and unites the soul and physical strength.

又曰	人之靈魂者神氣之精美者

*'''He also said''': The human soul is the most refined and beautiful part of divine energy.

問	神始造人祖亦猶兒乎

*'''Question''': When God first created the human ancestors, were they also like children?

曰	兒也

*'''Answer''': They were children.

曰	人魂之保護日月關焉乎 ''(問)

*'''Question''': Are the sun and moon involved in the protection of human souls?

曰	日月保護殊其体耳矣人魂則天帝爲主而地帝宰之也然是其生時之事死後則其最上魂專歸於天帝所轄無不至無不止

*'''Answer''': The sun and moon exclusively protect physical bodies. As for human souls, the Heavenly Emperor is their master, and the Earthly Emperor governs them. However, this applies to their time of life. After death, the highest soul returns exclusively to the jurisdiction of the Heavenly Emperor, reaching everywhere and unhindered anywhere.

問	剛柔流三体其元素幾何

*'''Question''': How many elements are there for the three states of matter: solid (rigid), yielding (soft), and fluid?

曰	元素之數五十其爲現体之用者二十五而天帝實合造化不造化而爲之故曰天帝所呼吸非現体所呼吸

*'''Answer''': The number of elements is fifty. Twenty-five of them are used for manifest bodies. The Heavenly Emperor truly combines the created and the uncreated to govern them. Therefore it is said: that which the Heavenly Emperor breathes is not what the manifest body breathes.

問	天帝有古稱乎

*'''Question''': Does the Heavenly Emperor have an ancient name?

曰	天御中主是也曰神皇產靈高皇產靈指其造化心也

*'''Answer''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi'' is the one. ''Kamimusuhi'' and ''Takamimusubi'' refer to His creative mind.

又曰	中也者無所不有天之爲大無非中也分子之爲微無非中也指示一處定爲中者受造者之論其体有限量之故也

*'''He also said''': "Center" (''Mina-ka'') means there is nothing it does not contain. The greatness of Heaven is nothing but the Center; the microscopic nature of molecules is nothing but the Center. Pointing to one spot and designating it the "center" is the logic of created beings, because their bodies have limits.

又曰	天御中主造化太陽其造化心即其中主也造化大地其造化心即其中主也造化太陰其造化心即其中主也

*'''He also said''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi'' created the Sun; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it. He created the Great Earth; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it. He created the Moon; His creative mind is precisely the Central Lord within it.

又曰	人之靈性日中可悟其自出也

*'''He also said''': The spiritual nature of humanity is called the "Center"; from this, one can awaken to its origin.

問	天帝所賦錫靈魂未知何從而取之乎

*'''Question''': Regarding the souls bestowed by the Heavenly Emperor, from where does He draw them?

曰	天帝自分其靈魂而賦錫之也夫分而不减其本量是靈魂之所以爲靈魂也

*'''Answer''': The Heavenly Emperor divides His own spiritual soul and bestows it. To divide it without diminishing its original volume is exactly what makes a spiritual soul a spiritual soul.

問	八力之在人身中其支持靈魂者與支持体格者各別乎

*'''Question''': Regarding the eight forces within the human body, are those that support the soul and those that support the physical frame distinct from one another?

曰	其支持靈魂者亦自支持体格

*'''Answer''': That which supports the soul naturally also supports the physical frame.

問	靈魂驚悸則若八力先失而汗流油出者如何

*'''Question''': When the soul is terrified, it seems as if the eight forces are lost first, and sweat flows like oil. Why is this?

曰	八力雖支持靈魂々々實能鼓動八力々々々々而增其强盛則靈魂亦益强盛也

*'''Answer''': Although the eight forces support the soul, the soul is actually capable of stimulating the eight forces. If the forces increase their robustness, the soul also grows increasingly robust.

問	人之死靈魂與八力俱去乎

*'''Question''': When a person dies, do the soul and the eight forces depart together?

曰	八力去而人始死也

*'''Answer''': The eight forces depart, and only then does the person die.

問	四魂之用夫唯果故能進乎唯察故能巧乎唯育故能盆乎唯交故能平乎 ''(盆 is likely a typo for 益 - benefit)

*'''Question''': Regarding the functions of the four souls: Is it solely because of decisiveness that one can advance? Solely because of observation that one can be skillful? Solely because of nurturing that one can benefit? Solely because of interacting that one can be peaceful?

曰	是用中之用所當然也亦唯進故能果也唯巧故能察也唯益故能育也唯平故能交也

*'''Answer''': This is the natural course of utilizing their functions. It is also solely because of advancing that one can be decisive; solely because of skill that one can observe; solely because of benefit that one can nurture; and solely because of peace that one can interact.

問	我儕所見太陽外別又有太陽乎

*'''Question''': Outside the sun that we see, is there another sun?

曰	天帝既造一太陽足以照各現体也

*'''Answer''': The Heavenly Emperor has already created one sun; it is sufficient to illuminate all manifest bodies.

問	人魂何用或在零圍氣內或在零圍氣以外

*'''Question''': To what end does the human soul reside either within the atmosphere or outside the atmosphere?

曰	上德者自得在界圍氣外然其有用而自居雰圍氣內者其位不得不屬天神

*'''Answer''': Those of supreme virtue naturally attain a place outside the atmosphere. However, those who have a purpose and voluntarily remain within the atmosphere hold a status that cannot help but belong to the heavenly gods.

問	良知良能者如何

*'''Question''': What of innate knowledge and innate ability?

曰	善善惡惡是所謂良知良能

*'''Answer''': Loving the good and hating the evil—this is what is called innate knowledge and innate ability.

夫人既有現体則不得現世之禮不奉事于神祇是顯齋之所以興而其日用常行起居動靜之際神常照鑑之則亦不得爲之思是謂之幽齋也

Since people have manifest bodies, they cannot abandon the rites of the manifest world nor cease serving the gods; this is why the "manifest purification" (external rites) arose. But in the midst of daily affairs, normal actions, rising, resting, moving, and staying still, the gods constantly illuminate and reflect upon them, so one must not harbor improper thoughts; this is called "hidden purification" (internal rites).

問	神有名乎

*'''Question''': Do the gods have names?

曰	神界無名而有名對現人也

*'''Answer''': In the divine realm there are no names. They have names only in relation to manifest humans.

問	道即善乎

*'''Question''': Is the Way the same as the Good?

曰	道所宜履之名善純美之名

*'''Answer''': The Way is the name for what ought to be walked; the Good is the name for pure beauty.

又曰	道猶指南車也循奉而不失其心之事也

*'''He also said''': The Way is like a south-pointing chariot. It is a matter of following and revering it without losing its core principle.

又曰	道猶經也善猶緯也

*'''He also said''': The Way is like the warp (vertical threads); the Good is like the weft (horizontal threads).

又曰	有人于此謂盡吾道則將問之日天道乎地道平抑汝之道乎且夫汝道亦有類焉公道乎私道乎自門以外公道而戶庭之事私道也如何

*'''He also said''': If someone here says, "I have exhausted my way," I would ask him: "Is it the Way of Heaven? The Way of Earth? Or is it merely your way? Moreover, your way also has categories. Is it the public way or the private way? Beyond the gate is the public way, while matters of the inner courtyard are the private way. Which is it?"

問	兵吉凶如何

*'''Question''': What of the auspiciousness or inauspiciousness of weapons (the military)?

曰	兵吉器而凶器

*'''Answer''': Weapons are both instruments of good fortune and instruments of evil fortune.

問	丹後峰山大野村伊藤常八妻美與再生說如何

*'''Question''': What about the story of the reincarnation of Miyo, the wife of Itō Tsunehachi from Ōno Village, Mineyama, Tango Province?

曰	再生無理而有理天地神祇無不為也

*'''Answer''': Reincarnation contradicts natural logic, yet it possesses a logic. There is nothing that the gods of heaven and earth cannot do.

問	再生者是無本魂乎

*'''Question''': Does a reincarnated person lack their original soul?

曰	或無本魂或有本魂

*'''Answer''': Sometimes they lack their original soul, and sometimes they possess their original soul.

問	大阪鐵道有火球大三丈變爲一血頭出舌是何怪

*'''Question''': On the Osaka railway, there was a fireball three ''zhang'' (thirty feet) in size that turned into a bloody head sticking out its tongue. What kind of monster is this?

曰	天降之孽也非怪也天者神也之者指賊也賊者何慢神害民者夫賊者猶病也孽者猶藥也以藥治病天職也復何疑

*'''Answer''': It is a calamity sent down by Heaven; it is not a monster. "Heaven" means the gods. "Sent down to" points to the traitors. Who are the traitors? Those who disrespect the gods and harm the people. The traitors are like a disease, and the calamity is like the medicine. Curing a disease with medicine is the duty of Heaven; what is there to doubt?

問	作詩之要

*'''Question''': What is the essence of writing poetry?

曰	華外實內是作詩之要

*'''Answer''': Radiance on the outside, substance on the inside—this is the essence of writing poetry.

道與神一孔子之言不離道則孔子之言不離神也道也者不可須臾離則神也者不可須臾離也

The Way and the gods are one. If the words of Confucius do not depart from the Way, then the words of Confucius do not depart from the gods. "The Way cannot be left for a single moment," which means the gods cannot be left for a single moment.

又曰	聲者心之形字者聲之書

*'''He also said''': Sound is the form of the mind; characters are the writing of the sound.

問	神也者何

*'''Question''': What is a god/spirit?

曰	天地精靈氣謂之神也

*'''Answer''': The refined, spiritual pneuma of heaven and earth is called a god.

問	何謂精靈氣

*'''Question''': What is the refined, spiritual pneuma?

曰	四精神也

*'''Answer''': It is the four spiritual souls.

問	何謂四精神

*'''Question''': What are the four spiritual souls?

曰	幸魂和魂奇魂荒魂是也

*'''Answer''': They are the ''Saki-mitama'' (Fortunate Soul), ''Nigi-mitama'' (Harmonious Soul), ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul), and ''Ara-mitama'' (Rough Soul).

問	何謂幸和荒奇

*'''Question''': What is meant by Fortunate, Harmonious, Rough, and Wondrous?

曰	幸魂者仁德是也和魂者禮德是也荒魂者義德是也奇魂者智德是也

*'''Answer''': The ''Saki-mitama'' is the virtue of Benevolence. The ''Nigi-mitama'' is the virtue of Propriety. The ''Ara-mitama'' is the virtue of Righteousness. The ''Kushi-mitama'' is the virtue of Wisdom.

問	四神形象如何

*'''Question''': What are the forms and images of the four gods (souls)?

曰	元素是神故能神而通也若有定形象眞能大不能小入又能小不能大造小入大造隨時而有變而化也

*'''Answer''': Elements are gods, therefore they can be divine and penetrating. If they had fixed forms or images, they might be capable of being large but incapable of becoming small to enter things, or capable of being small but incapable of becoming large to create things. Making small, entering things, or creating large things—they change and transform according to the times.

問	然則或以爲一神或以爲多神皆非乎

*'''Question''': In that case, is it wrong to consider them as a single god, or wrong to consider them as many gods?

曰	或以爲一神以道不相爭或以爲多神以四魂

*'''Answer''': Some consider them one god, because the Way does not conflict with itself. Some consider them many gods, based on the four souls.

問	以四魂則其爲八百萬神不可乎

*'''Question''': Based on the four souls, is it not possible for them to become the eight million gods?

曰	四魂分配爲八百萬神無不可也乘數雖陞無量無數無不可也

*'''Answer''': There is nothing wrong with the four souls being distributed to become the eight million gods. Even if multiplied infinitely to countless numbers, there is nothing wrong with it.

敢問	其詳

*'''Question''': I venture to ask for details.

曰	在日爲日神在月爲月神在星爲星神在地爲地神此類推而敷衍恰無量無數也且汝精神亦四魂四神

*'''Answer''': In the sun they are the sun god, in the moon they are the moon god, in the stars they are the star god, on earth they are the earth god. Deducing and expanding from this, they are truly infinite and countless. Furthermore, your own spirit also consists of the four souls and the four gods.

問	四魂如何係著

*'''Question''': How are the four souls attached/connected?

曰	古人曰心者神明之舍夫心臟四竅豈不四魂之所在乎雖是漢字心爲四畫德字直字懷字自字俱从四魂字魄字思字皆从田田者心臟之象也試驗之乎人在胎內而其機械先成者心腦次之諸体格又次之陰部爲最後腦司体格運營而心主精神夫心病而精神不去也腦患而精神先失以是侔乎死人腦爲腦可哀也且子又試驗心意動平懼者心悸而後頭岑々憂者心作凝結而肢体無力勇者心不動而全身緊張懣者心塞而口爲吃々懼憂屬愛勇懣屬勇而腦不關也思恥之屬智而相爲耳熱謙下之屬禮而辭色和易又心臟作用四魂在心臟明矣

*'''Answer''': The ancients said, "The heart is the dwelling place of the divine illumination." Do not the four chambers of the heart represent the location of the four souls? Even looking at Chinese characters, "heart" (心) has four strokes. Characters like virtue (德), straightness (直), bosom (懷), and self (自) all relate to the four souls. Characters like soul (魄) and thought (思) all derive from the "field" (田) radical; "field" is a representation of the heart. Test this: when a person is in the womb, the first mechanism to form is the heart, followed by the brain, then the various limbs and bodily frames, and the private parts last. The brain governs the operation of the physical frame, while the heart rules the spirit. If the heart is diseased, the spirit does not depart; but if the brain suffers, the spirit is lost first. In this respect, the brain of a dead person remains a brain; how pitiable! Furthermore, you can test how the mind and intentions move. For one who is terrified, the heart palpitates, and only then does the head feel heavy. For one who is sorrowful, the heart feels frozen solid, and the limbs lose their strength. For one who is courageous, the heart remains unmoving, and the entire body tenses. For one who is frustrated, the heart feels blocked, and the mouth stutters. Fear and sorrow belong to Affection (Love); courage and frustration belong to Bravery; and the brain is not involved. Thinking and shame belong to Wisdom, mutually causing the ears to burn; humility and submissiveness belong to Propriety, rendering words and expressions gentle. Thus, it is clear that the functions of the heart demonstrate that the four souls reside within the heart.

問	神者何

*'''Question''': What is a god/spirit?

曰	元素是故人死而後歸元素亦神

*'''Answer''': Elements. Therefore, when a person dies and returns to the elements, they are also a spirit.

問	元素者何豈亦形氣乎然則精氣與形氣奚擇

*'''Question''': What are the elements? Are they also physical pneuma? If so, how does one choose between spiritual pneuma and physical pneuma?

曰	元素有二種類汝肉体與汝精神是資

*'''Answer''': There are two kinds of elements. Your fleshly body and your spirit are endowed by them.

問	精神元素一魂乎

*'''Question''': Is the spiritual element a single soul?

曰	非一魂何以知之日心臟四房是實容四魂所謂幸魂之仁也荒魂之義也奇魂之智也和魂之禮也而信者天之所屬故云誠者天之道也誠信也天以仁義禮智配人承以有之雖然人不可獨信有時乎父爲子廋子爲父廋春秋諱國惡而天不可隱味是以聰明睿智爲不可掩而又有時乎動於人故云誠之者人之道也天道人道所分判如

*'''Answer''': It is not a single soul. How do we know this? We say the four chambers of the heart actually contain the four souls: what is called the Benevolence of the ''Saki-mitama'', the Righteousness of the ''Ara-mitama'', the Wisdom of the ''Kushi-mitama'', and the Propriety of the ''Nigi-mitama''. "Trust/Sincerity" (Xin) belongs to Heaven. Therefore it is said, "Sincerity is the Way of Heaven." Sincerity is Trust. Heaven equips humans with Benevolence, Righteousness, Propriety, and Wisdom, and people inherit and possess them. However, humans cannot be exclusively trusting/sincere. Sometimes, a father covers up for his son, and a son covers up for his father. The ''Spring and Autumn Annals'' concealed the faults of the state. But Heaven cannot conceal or obscure anything; therefore its acute intelligence and profound wisdom cannot be hidden. Yet, sometimes it stirs within humans; hence it is said, "To become sincere is the Way of Man." This is how the Way of Heaven and the Way of Man are distinguished.

問	然則四魂外信亦一元素

*'''Question''': If so, then besides the four souls, is Trust/Sincerity also an element?

曰	其然雖然予試檢之元素在天互相駢列互相不雄長然則信獨屬之天道不欲復賜於人間是信獨尊矣故予謂信者仁義禮智之相約諾所以爲道々即四中中者無偏倚之謂無傍邊之謂無過不及之謂堯舜所執中其人道之中歟

*'''Answer''': That is so. Nevertheless, let me examine it: the elements exist in Heaven, arrayed side by side, none lording over the others. If Trust belongs exclusively to the Heavenly Way and is not meant to be bestowed upon the human realm, then Trust would be uniquely supreme. Therefore, I say that Trust is the mutual promise and alignment of Benevolence, Righteousness, Propriety, and Wisdom. It is what constitutes the Way. The Way is precisely the Center of the four. "Center" means having no bias, no siding, no excess, and no deficiency. The "Center" held fast by Yao and Shun—is this not the Center of the Human Way?

問	魂以顆論何

*'''Question''': Why is the soul discussed in terms of granules/particles?

曰	四魂元素說其色相耳其實元素者粒々顆々其數無邊無量無涯幾億兆萬有旬各自稱神稱中同色相感而做同感異色相合而爲同抱亦看一神也上代稱之爲天之御中主神々德及人實是人中夫天造大物其神合抱稱之造小物其神小分稱之神自由自在也人有体未能自由是莫之憾榮養原身有妻有子又有君父有朋友交際之道百年化而歸元素未晚也矣

*'''Answer''': Describing the elements of the four souls is merely discussing their appearances. In reality, the elements are myriad granules and particles; their number is boundless, measureless, limitless, numbering in the hundreds of millions, trillions, and tens of thousands. Each particle calls itself a god, calls itself the Center. Those of the same kind resonate together, creating a unified feeling; those of different kinds join together, forming a unified embrace, which is also seen as one god. Antiquity called this ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami''. Its divine virtue reaches humanity and is truly the Center of humanity. When Heaven creates large things, the gods combine and embrace to match the scale; when it creates small things, the gods minutely divide to match the scale. The gods are completely free and unhindered. Humans have physical bodies and cannot yet be free; there is no regret in this. Nourishing the original body, having a wife and children, having a lord and a father, having friends and the ways of social interaction—after a hundred years, transforming and returning to the elements will not be too late!

問	魂與神氣有以異乎

*'''Question''': Is there a difference between the soul and divine energy?

曰	魂者人之精神磅礴而爲魂者神氣則漫漶而充敷胎內者

*'''Answer''': The soul is the human spirit, majestic and concentrated into a soul; divine energy is diffuse, filling and spreading within the womb.

又曰	天地之精神是爲神是自一元体之磅礴突然人不能得而見其体則亦岐爲小分子狀是神之自由者所謂思則得也

*'''He also said''': The spirit of heaven and earth is the god. It emerges majestically from a single primal entity. Suddenly, if humans cannot perceive its body, it branches into small molecular forms. This is the freedom of the gods, as it is said, "Seek, and you shall find."

又曰	力者俗所謂魂氣也魂氣者力之異名也又俗所謂精神者則精神力而與靈魂大異也

*'''He also said''': "Force" is what the vulgar call soul-energy. Soul-energy is another name for force. Also, what the vulgar call "spirit" is actually spiritual force, which is vastly different from the soul itself.

問	然則禽獸者如何

*'''Question''': In that case, what about birds and beasts?

曰	禽獸者不足爲魂也罔神經之故也

*'''Answer''': Birds and beasts are insufficient to form a true soul, because they lack spiritual nervous systems.

問	然則其蝒動者何且狐魅之爲妖非智慧而何如何 ''(蝒 is a typo for 蠕, wriggling)

*'''Question''': In that case, what of crawling creatures? Moreover, when fox spirits and demons act as monsters, if not out of wisdom, then what is it?

曰	是神氣之所爲蓋神氣者天之未爲魂者雖無靈力亦自有靈狀狐魅得靈狀而自鍛鍊者也聊感奇魂之神氣者是大惡魔

*'''Answer''': This is the work of divine energy. Divine energy is Heaven's substance before it becomes a soul. Although it lacks spiritual force, it naturally possesses a spiritual form. Fox spirits and demons acquire this spiritual form and refine it themselves. Those who slightly resonate with the divine energy of the ''Kushi-mitama'' (Wondrous Soul) become great arch-demons.

問	人之始生錫靈魂幾点子乎

*'''Question''': When a human is first born, how many particles (points) of the soul are bestowed upon them?

曰	凡人之始生先錫之愛一点子而初出胎而錫奇魂勇魂親魂各一点子也

*'''Answer''': Generally, when a human is first conceived, they are first bestowed one particle of Love. The moment they emerge from the womb, they are bestowed one particle each of the Wondrous Soul (Wisdom), Courageous Soul (Bravery), and Kinship Soul.

問	然則終身是而止乎

*'''Question''': Then does it stop at this for their entire life?

曰	隨長而降之各不同

*'''Answer''': As they grow, more are sent down to them, differing for each individual.

問	如是則造物者不公平乎

*'''Question''': If this is so, is the Creator not unfair?

曰	天[此天者/地球天]之爲政決無不公平善者獨能受賞者耳矣

*'''Answer''': Heaven's [this Heaven means the Heaven of the Earth] governance is absolutely never unfair; it is merely that only the good are able to receive the rewards.

問	神道

*'''Question''': [What is] the Divine Way (Shinto)?

曰	汝知人道乎

*'''Answer''': Do you know the Human Way?

問	知之人道也者五倫也

*'''Question''': I know it. The Human Way consists of the Five Human Relationships.

曰	然則告神道也夫神亦有五倫焉凡盈於天地之間者是氣々分爲二精神元素與休養元素是也体養元素也者四十九種類而底一爲太極太極也者精神元素也精神元素亦四種類四種類相合爲一以善一以道一以中一極斯立太極也四十九加一五十也五十之數瀰々綸々無空隙也乎於是乎造物者即精神元素相謂曰吾智足以經輪吾仁足以愛被吾勇足以決進吾禮足以守成(下略)

*'''Answer''': Then I will tell you the Divine Way. The gods also have five relationships. All that fills the space between heaven and earth is pneuma (Qi). Pneuma divides into two: the spiritual elements and the nurturing elements. The physically nurturing elements comprise forty-nine types, and the underlying one is the Supreme Ultimate (''Taiji''). The Supreme Ultimate is the spiritual element. The spiritual element also consists of four types. The four types combine to form one. With Good as one, the Way as one, and the Center as one, the Ultimate is thus established as the Supreme Ultimate. Forty-nine plus one makes fifty. The number fifty fills and permeates everything, leaving no empty space. Thereupon, the Creator, which is the spiritual elements, spoke to themselves saying: "My Wisdom is sufficient to manage and organize; My Benevolence is sufficient to cover with love; My Bravery is sufficient to advance decisively; My Propriety is sufficient to preserve and maintain." (The rest is omitted).

問	幾

*'''Question''': [What of] the subtle beginnings (''ji'')?

曰	知幾者其神乎其知神之所爲乎賢矣仲舒

*'''Answer''': "He who knows the subtle beginnings is indeed divine!" Did he know the workings of the gods? How worthy was Dong Zhongshu!

問	易傳誰作

*'''Question''': Who wrote the commentaries on the ''Book of Changes'' (''Yizhuan'')?

曰	五行說仲舒爲之則易傳說五行非仲舒而何

*'''Answer''': Dong Zhongshu created the theory of the Five Phases (''Wuxing''). Since the ''Yizhuan'' explains the Five Phases, if it was not Dong Zhongshu who wrote it, then who else?

問	人會愀然日天途不可知乎

*'''Question''': People sometimes sigh mournfully and say, "The ways of Heaven cannot be known." Is this true?

曰	我亦天也天之分身也我而自知是知天也

*'''Answer''': I am also Heaven; I am an offshoot of Heaven. For me to know myself is to know Heaven.

問	智

*'''Question''': [What of] Wisdom?

曰	知所知是智

*'''Answer''': Knowing what one knows is wisdom.

問	大智

*'''Question''': [What of] Great Wisdom?

曰	不知所不知是大智

*'''Answer''': Not pretending to know what one does not know is Great Wisdom.

問	慾如何

*'''Question''': What of desire?

曰	慾者欲从心也心欲也仲尼欲明明德於天下也可見大有慾者是善矣

*'''Answer''': Desire (慾) is wishing (欲) coming from the heart (心). It is the wishing of the heart. Confucius desired to manifest luminous virtue to the world. It can be seen that having great desire is a good thing.

敢問	天亦有慾乎

*'''Question''': May I venture to ask, does Heaven also have desires?

曰	有矣天欲造化物之日善也

*'''Answer''': It does. Heaven desires that its created things become daily more good.

先生甞日余所父所師者天也天外有父者第二父也天外有師者第二師也夫父師者身之所憑學之所由也身本於天而成於父母學亦本於天而就於師者故余精神然矣

The Master once said: "That which I treat as a father and treat as a teacher is Heaven. Any father outside of Heaven is a secondary father; any teacher outside of Heaven is a secondary teacher. Fathers and teachers are what the body relies on and where learning originates. The body originates from Heaven but is formed through the parents; learning also originates from Heaven but is accomplished through the teacher. Therefore, my spirit is as it is."

問	中者何

*'''Question''': What is the "Center" (''Zhong'')?

曰	中者衷也天之所以衷其大無外其小無內也且主忠信之忠从中心則孔子之一也者中之謂也堯日以允執中終義之所在也古之帝王學士莫弗以中稱說者可見人所以衷者中也在而中也在人而中也一之謂歟天地一中蓋吾執一中以從事也

*'''Answer''': "Center" means inner core. Heaven's inner core is so great it has no outside, so small it has no inside. Moreover, the "Loyalty" (忠) in "hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary" is formed from the characters "center" (中) and "heart" (心). Thus, Confucius's "One" refers to the Center. When Yao said, "Sincerely hold fast to the Center," it indicates where ultimate righteousness lies. The ancient emperors and scholars never failed to praise and explain the Center. It can be seen that human's inner core is the Center. The center of presence, the center in humans—is this not what is called the "One"? Heaven and Earth share one Center, and I hold fast to this one Center to conduct my affairs.

又曰	執中之法審心之所先起而可有善而無惡也人之良知良能於是乎在矣

*'''He also said''': The method of holding fast to the Center is to examine what first arises in the mind, ensuring it contains good and lacks evil. Human innate knowledge and innate ability reside precisely herein.

又曰	人之体氣不一少年之日利於長進長進之害燥急故頓失中之義老年之時老練矣老鍊之蔽屈退故又輙失中之義學者宜念々在於中則中之所命者未有失焉者也

*'''He also said''': People's physical energy is not uniform. In the days of youth, they are prone to rapid growth and advancement, but the harm of this advancement is rashness and impatience; thus they suddenly lose the principle of the Center. In old age, they become experienced, but the flaw of experience is shrinking back and retreating; thus they again frequently lose the principle of the Center. Scholars ought to keep their thoughts constantly upon the Center, for those who follow the mandates of the Center have never erred.

又曰	中者有形者也文中子序說得矣而匪有象者又尤得也察於中而能不才者未之有也文中子門人陸續輩出而皆賢執中之功效也孔子門人即啓之鏞矣休矣

*'''He also said''': The Center is something that possesses form. The preface by Wenzhongzi grasped this, yet realizing it possesses no physical image grasps it even more deeply. There has never been one who examines the Center yet remains untalented. Wenzhongzi's disciples emerged one after another and were all worthies; this was the efficacy of holding fast to the Center. Confucius's disciples were the very bells that heralded this. How excellent!

又曰	顧諟天之明命者尤執中之謂也

*'''He also said''': "To carefully attend to Heaven's luminous mandate" refers precisely to holding fast to the Center.

又曰	允執厥中我國所謂天御中主神之中是也

*'''He also said''': "Sincerely holding fast to the Center"—this Center is what in our country is called the "Mina-ka" (Center) of ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami''.

又曰	一以貫之即中之謂也忠即中也

*'''He also said''': "One thread running through it all" simply means the Center. Loyalty is the Center.

又曰	凡忠恕忠信之類皆以中字爲主

*'''He also said''': Generally, terms like "loyalty and empathy" or "loyalty and trustworthiness" all take the character "Center" (Zhong) as their root.

又曰	中庸云忠恕達道不遠此言非也

*'''He also said''': The ''Doctrine of the Mean'' says, "Loyalty and empathy are not far from the Way." This statement is incorrect.

又曰	主忠信無友不如已者如忠信如丘之如不如已者即不主忠信者也以反及義釋者非也

*'''He also said''': "Hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary, and have no friends who are not like yourself." "Like" means like loyalty and trustworthiness, as in "like Qiu" (Confucius's name). "Not like yourself" means those who do not hold loyalty and trustworthiness as primary. To interpret this as meaning "inferior to yourself" is incorrect.

又曰	書云惟皇上帝降衷于下民若有恒性衷中也忠也若順也乃奉載天意而弗誤之謂也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' says, "The great Supreme Lord bestowed the inner core (''Zhong'') upon the lower people, to accord with their constant nature." "Inner core" is the Center; it is Loyalty. "Accord with" means to comply. This means respectfully bearing the will of Heaven without error.

又曰	洪範云于汝極錫汝保極保極者中之道也錫極者若有恒惟也

*'''He also said''': The "Great Plan" says, "To your ultimate standard, He gives the preservation of the ultimate." Preserving the ultimate is the Way of the Center. Bestowing the ultimate refers to the constant nature.

又曰	酒誥云作稽中德中德即保極也

*'''He also said''': The "Announcement about Drunkenness" says, "To investigate the central virtue." The central virtue is precisely preserving the ultimate.

又曰	中庸之中亦降衷于下民之衷庸若有恒性之恒故中與庸者聖者遺傳也

*'''He also said''': The "Zhong" (Center) in the ''Doctrine of the Mean'' is the same "inner core" bestowed upon the lower people; "Yong" (Constant/Mean) is the "constant" of the constant nature. Therefore, the concepts of Center and Mean are the legacy of the sages.

又曰	論語云天之曆數在爾躬天即我國所謂高天原是也

*'''He also said''': The ''Analects'' say, "The heavenly succession rests in your person." "Heaven" here is what in our country is called ''Takamagahara'' (the High Plain of Heaven).

又曰	書云威有一德孔子云一以貫之一即我國神代文字之——也積與縱之異制也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' says, "Majesty possesses one virtue." Confucius says, "One thread running through it all." The "One" is equivalent to the character "——" in our country's Age of the Gods script. It is just a different system of stacking or placing vertically.

又曰	子云獲罪乎天無所禱也道也者一也天地人所以一也故屬之天也所謂神者也

*'''He also said''': The Master said, "He who offends against Heaven has none to whom he can pray." The Way is One. It is that by which Heaven, Earth, and Humanity become one. Therefore it belongs to Heaven. It is what is called God.

又曰	道者神之所爲天所以爲天之實也

*'''He also said''': The Way is the doing of the gods; it is the substance of what makes Heaven, Heaven.

又曰	身也者父母之遺体也父母亦其父母之遺体也推言之天地爲父母

*'''He also said''': The body is the inherited form from one's parents. The parents are also the inherited forms from their parents. By extension, Heaven and Earth are the ultimate parents.

又曰	中神也我國所謂伊那々伎爾伎寸免留加美中也指頭爲加美亦中也是所謂魂神者也

*'''He also said''': The Center is a god. It is the "Center" in what our country calls ''Inanagi'', ''Ninigi'', and ''Sumeru-kami''. Pointing to the head as "Kami" (god/upper) also means the Center. This is what is called the soul-god.

中庸云知恥近乎勇亦誤曰知即智也

The ''Doctrine of the Mean'' says, "To know shame is close to courage." This is also an error. "Knowing" (Zhi) is precisely Wisdom (Zhi).

又曰	易云立人之道曰仁與義非也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Changes'' says, "The Way established for humanity is called benevolence and righteousness." This is incorrect.

我國所謂鎮魂則求未全錫於我者也蓋求放心之義亦同焉

What our country calls "pacifying the soul" (''Chinkon'') means seeking that which has not yet been fully bestowed upon us. The meaning of "seeking the lost mind" is also the same as this.

又曰	中神也誠亦神也道亦神也而神固一神也

*'''He also said''': The Center is a god; Sincerity is also a god; the Way is also a god. Yet the god is inherently a single god.

又曰	夫鬼神皆有形而非必無形然爲其有形亦充於天地之間故惟不能定爲形容也

*'''He also said''': Ghosts and spirits all have forms, and are not necessarily formless. However, because their forms fill the space between heaven and earth, they simply cannot be fixed into a specific shape or appearance.

問	明德如何

*'''Question''': What of luminous virtue?

曰	明德即靈魂屬於心也

*'''Answer''': Luminous virtue is the soul belonging to the heart.

又曰	夫人主魂不主体故孔子云朝聞道夕死可矣又云守死善道雖然魂依体栖宿者故体與力亦不可不養也而養魂以魂養力以力養体以体或食肉或食穀々與肉質也体亦質也以質實之物養質實之体是以体養体之理也昔陶侃朝運百甓於齋外暮運於齋內是以力養力之理也多聞道義之精神以養道義之精神是以魂養魂之理也此三者乃天地乃原则也不可不知矣

*'''He also said''': A person takes the soul as primary, not the body. Therefore Confucius said, "If one hears the Way in the morning, one may die in the evening without regret." He also said, "Hold fast to death to perfect the Way." Nevertheless, because the soul relies on the body as its dwelling, the body and its forces must also be nourished. One nourishes the soul with the soul, nourishes force with force, and nourishes the body with the body. Whether eating meat or eating grains—grains and meat are matter. The body is also matter. To nourish a material body with material objects is the principle of nourishing the body with the body. In the past, Tao Kan would move a hundred bricks outside his study in the morning, and move them back inside in the evening; this is the principle of nourishing force with force. To widely hear the spirit of moral principles in order to nourish the spirit of moral principles is the principle of nourishing the soul with the soul. These three are the fundamental principles of heaven and earth, and one must not fail to know them.

曰	我愛吾者私愛也而離其形骸而愛者正愛也離其道義而愛者邪愛也

*'''He said''': Loving myself is private love. But loving detached from the physical body is correct love. Loving detached from moral principles is wicked love.

又曰	神自神人顧自人祖不可混合

*'''He also said''': Gods are from gods, and human ancestors are from humans. They must not be conflated.

又曰	人在地上各異其國各異其邑則亦各異其言語各異其音聲是各人祖之意各異之所致若以人祖系之於神則神意不二敎其言語音聲亦應不二淺學輩以人祖爲一祖日人々言語音聲本皆一般是皆遁辭耳

*'''He also said''': Since people on earth reside in different countries and different towns, their languages and sounds also differ. This is caused by the differing intentions of their respective human ancestors. If one traces human ancestors back to the gods, the divine will is undivided; their teachings, languages, and sounds should also be undivided. Shallow scholars claim that human ancestors stem from a single ancestor, and that human languages and sounds were originally all the same; these are nothing but evasive words.

又曰	氣海無波凶賊隱身何許耳

*'''He also said''': If the sea of pneuma has no waves, where can the evil traitors hide themselves?

又曰	上代各地有大蛇因溫暖勢強也

*'''He also said''': In ancient times, there were giant serpents in various regions, due to the strength of the warm climate.

又曰	人祖之始降大地非南方而在北方蓋天帝之造大地以其初含温素過當南方熾烈不可生息而北方温熱漸適生息也故知人類之始降非南方而在北方矣

*'''He also said''': When human ancestors first descended to the earth, it was not in the South but in the North. This is because when the Heavenly Emperor created the earth, it initially contained an excess of warmth. The South was fiercely hot and incapable of sustaining life, whereas the warmth of the North gradually became suitable for life. Thus, we know that humanity's initial descent was not in the South but in the North.

又曰	書北方日幽都蓋以北方今雖幽味然實人祖之所始降而昔時嘗爲都會之地也

*'''He also said''': The ''Book of Documents'' calls the North the "Dark Capital" (''Youdu''). This is because, although the North is now dark and obscure, it was actually where the human ancestors first descended, and in ancient times it was a metropolitan region.

又曰	國語北方曰子々者根也乃萬物之所根始也

*'''He also said''': In the national language, the North is associated with the earthly branch ''Zi'' (Rat). ''Zi'' means root. It is the root and origin of all things.

問	中者一氣乎

*'''Question''': Is the Center a single pneuma (''Qi'')?

曰	亦有五氣故國書云五魂是五魂者爲精神之元素也

*'''Answer''': There are also five pneumas. Therefore, the national texts speak of the Five Souls. These Five Souls are the spiritual elements.

問	元素之神如何

*'''Question''': What of the gods of the elements?

問	五神之用如何

*'''Question''': What are the functions of the Five Gods?

曰	天御中主神高皇產靈神神皇產靈神甘葦芽彥舅神天常立神此五神者實爲精神元素故稱爲別天神也

*'''Answer''': ''Ame-no-Minakanushi-no-Kami'', ''Takamimusubi-no-Kami'', ''Kamimusuhi-no-Kami'', ''Umashiashikabihikoji-no-Kami'', and ''Amenotokotachi-no-Kami''. These five gods are truly the spiritual elements, hence they are called the Separate Heavenly Deities (''Kotoamatsukami'').

曰	國書所云和魂幸魂奇魂荒魂而其一魂未聞揚言之者但說和魂禮也幸魂仁也奇魂智也荒魂義也若語一魂則一魂爲一中也中之爲用大矣蓋中猶道也以道乎四魂道猶一魂也是實五元素之稱號所以興其實爲四魂亦未不可心臟四竅職此之由

*'''He said''': The national texts mention the ''Nigi-mitama'', ''Saki-mitama'', ''Kushi-mitama'', and ''Ara-mitama'', but we rarely hear the fifth soul spoken of aloud. They merely explain that the ''Nigi-mitama'' is Propriety, the ''Saki-mitama'' is Benevolence, the ''Kushi-mitama'' is Wisdom, and the ''Ara-mitama'' is Righteousness. If we speak of the one remaining soul, it is the One Center. The function of the Center is immense! The Center is like the Way. To apply the Way to the four souls—the Way itself is like the one soul. This is the origin of the title of the Five Elements. Yet, in reality, referring to them as four souls is also acceptable. This is the reason the heart has four chambers.

問	思之思之不已鬼神佑之有是理乎

*'''Question''': "Think on it, think on it ceaselessly, and the ghosts and spirits will aid you." Does this principle hold true?

曰	有之人雖未掌等於鬼神苟思一善者則一善成應焉善者天之心也爲一巧思則一巧思成感焉巧思也天之才也

*'''Answer''': It does. Although a human may not yet equal the ghosts and spirits, if they earnestly think upon a single good, that single good will successfully elicit a response. The Good is the heart of Heaven. If they hold a single ingenious thought, that ingenious thought will successfully evoke resonance. Ingenuity is the talent of Heaven.

又曰	神也者中心也

*'''He also said''': Gods are the central core.

又曰	靈也者中與神之謂也故也與神須臾不可離者乃道之本義

*'''He also said''': "Spirit" (''Ling'') is a term for the Center and the Gods. Therefore, that "it and the gods cannot be separated for a single moment" is the fundamental meaning of the Way.

又曰	道先天地成後天地顯

*'''He also said''': The Way was formed before heaven and earth, and became manifest after heaven and earth.

又曰	靈也者神力之總稱故剖判以來萬物之離合聚散亦係于力德

*'''He also said''': "Spirit" is the collective name for divine force. Therefore, since the separation of heaven and earth, the merging, separating, gathering, and dispersing of all things are also tied to this virtuous force.

又曰	在彼不來在此不去神心中々

*'''He also said''': Being there it does not come, being here it does not go; the gods are precisely in the center of the heart.

又神魂者無光之光也矣故上屆天心下達地中無不普照可謂無量無礙光也

And the divine soul is the light without light. Therefore, reaching up to the heart of heaven and reaching down into the earth, there is nothing it does not universally illuminate. It can be called boundless, unhindered light.

又曰	四魂互爲經緯而直在其中故云五魂

*'''He also said''': The four souls serve mutually as warp and weft, while the straight line exists in the center; therefore they are called the five souls.

問	中與上帝異乎

*'''Question''': Is the Center different from the Supreme Lord (''Shangdi'')?

曰	中也者在心中之稱也而上帝也在頭上之謂也且人脚下亦有神易所謂感胖而西醫扶氏經驗書載脚下言語之病皆證脚下有神也

*'''Answer''': "Center" is the term for that which resides within the heart, whereas "Supreme Lord" is the term for that which resides above the head. Moreover, humans also have gods beneath their feet. The ''Book of Changes'' mentions "moving the big toe," and the experiential records of the Western physician Hufeland mention a disease involving speech emanating from beneath the feet, all of which proves that there are gods beneath the feet.

問	祈必益乎

*'''Question''': Does prayer definitely bring benefit?

曰	祈必益故孔子亦云吾戰必勝祭必受福是也

*'''Answer''': Prayer definitely brings benefit. Therefore, Confucius also said, "When I fight, I must win; when I sacrifice, I must receive blessings." This is what it means.

門人佐々木哲太郎輯錄於千駄谷口副島邸

*Compiled and recorded by the disciple Sasaki Tetsutarō at the Soejima residence in Sendagaya.

維時明治三十一年十二月七日抄錄終

*In this time, the thirty-first year of Meiji [1898], the 7th day of the 12th month, the copying of the record was completed.

(蒼海語錄畢)

*(End of the Sayings of Sōkai)

[[Category:Honda Chikaatsu]]</text>
      <sha1>bk46pubjbgj2514t4gcdllwoi0uehv3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
