<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shineidō （神衞道）</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>152537</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3503405</id>
      <timestamp>2026-03-17T02:29:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Motosada Kuribayashi</username>
        <id>744</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "[[Shineidō （神衞道）|Shineidō]] is a religious and philosophical system founded by [[Kimitake Watanabe]], developed upon the teachings of Supreme Commander Hayato Kanda. This tradition extends considerably beyond the mere framework of faith, distinguishing itself by integrating ethics, Eastern philosophy, and scientific thought into a unified whole — placing at its centre the cultivation of human instinct, social responsibility, and harmonious coexistence with..."</comment>
      <origin>3503405</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="17402" sha1="ezg3h2lqumhsqxvhtxtpn0j623kgqdu" xml:space="preserve">[[Shineidō （神衞道）|Shineidō]] is a religious and philosophical system founded by [[Kimitake Watanabe]], developed upon the teachings of Supreme Commander Hayato Kanda. This tradition extends considerably beyond the mere framework of faith, distinguishing itself by integrating ethics, Eastern philosophy, and scientific thought into a unified whole — placing at its centre the cultivation of human instinct, social responsibility, and harmonious coexistence with the natural world. Supreme Commander Hayato Kanda placed particular emphasis upon adherents attaining the Shineidō spirit not through elaborate doctrine or ceremonial formality, but through the conduct of their daily lives, thereby pursuing human flourishing in its truest sense. This approach makes plain that faith is not a matter of passive submission, but one that deepens through autonomous ethical practice.

Kimitake Watanabe's deification of the Supreme Commander stands as a significant element of Shineidō's devotional character; yet the doctrine is by no means reducible to mere veneration of a divine figure. Rather, adherents are encouraged to draw upon the insights of ethics, philosophy, and the natural sciences — approaching doctrine with an experimental and scholarly disposition, deepening their understanding through inward cultivation. Accordingly, whilst the degree of the Supreme Commander's deification varies amongst sects and organisations, the reverence afforded to him as the spiritual centre of the tradition is common to all, forming the foundation of its ideological coherence.

Of particular note is the emphasis placed upon forming ethical reason not from external authority or fixed dogma, but from within — grounded in personal experience, observation, and causal reasoning. The innate goodness of human instinct is taken as a given, and reason is understood as that which emerges naturally through the disciplined cultivation of those instincts. This philosophy prizes the process by which the individual arrives at ethical judgement autonomously, observing and analysing one's own actions and their consequences, thereby achieving moral maturity. In short, it is made explicit that ethics and reason are not norms imposed from without, but are generated through each person's independent cultivation and practice.

Shineidō situates human existence within the causal structure of the cosmos and nature, holding that the actions and ethics of the individual are to be understood through their interaction with society and the natural world. In this respect, Shineidō differs markedly from traditional religious ethics and the moral frameworks of monotheism, standing instead as a practical religious philosophy that recognises, at its very root, the interconnectedness of the individual with society and with nature.
----

== Overview ==
The foundational principles of Shineidō begin with a scientific definition of the human being — not as a mere individual, but as an inherently social creature. In the doctrinal interpretation of the Watanabe school, human thought and conduct are understood through the interplay between the instinctive dispositions resident within the individual and the reason cultivated by their proper discipline. As a social animal, the human being has evolved and adapted not in isolation, but through relationship with community and natural environment; it is upon this understanding that ethics and codes of conduct are formed.

The rationalism and monotheism of Western religion are held, from a scientific standpoint, to contain fundamental errors. In particular, the notion that morality and reason are prescribed by an external absolute authority or supernatural being is regarded as suppressing the independent thought of adherents, bearing with it the danger of intellectual paralysis and dependent faith. Nevertheless, the spirit of Shineidō holds the freedom of belief in high esteem; accordingly, a degree of latitude exists in the interpretations and practices of non-Watanabe schools, and diversity corresponding to the convictions of individual sects and adherents is fully acknowledged.

The central claim of Watanabe school doctrine is this: that, grounded in modern science, the proper cultivation of humanity's instincts constitutes the social good by which common flourishing may be built. "Cultivation of instinct," as understood here, refers not to any self-indulgent form of training, but to a process of developing instinct through physical discipline and ethical conduct, thereby sharpening the individual's capacity for judgement. Adherents consciously practise benevolence, righteousness, loyalty, filial piety, and propriety in the course of daily life; through the repetition of right conduct, they achieve the Shineidō attainment. It is this repetitive practice that is held to lead directly to the perfection of the Shineidō spirit — that is, to the individual's moral maturity and the realisation of social harmony.
----

== Foundational Doctrine ==
One of the cardinal ideas of Shineidō is the view that human instinct is, in its essence, good. Instinct comprises the innate behavioural tendencies with which one is born; ethics and reason are held to form naturally when these tendencies are properly cultivated. Errors of reason and moral deviation arise as consequences of the mistaken understanding or application of instinct — not, it is maintained, through the compulsion of external authority or doctrinal norms. This view, rooted in the doctrine of original human goodness, regards moral growth as a matter of autonomous self-cultivation.

Adherents repeatedly perform ethical actions of their own volition, observing and analysing their inner lives, thereby deepening their understanding of the interplay between instinct and reason. This process is conceived not merely as a means of individual flourishing, but as a vehicle for pursuing the common good of society and humanity at large. That is to say, Shineidō teaches that the cultivation of ethics constitutes at once the spiritual growth of the individual and an act that realises the broader social good.
----

== Causal Reasoning ==
In Shineidō, causal reasoning is not confined to abstract theory or philosophical speculation; it is the fundamental mode of thought underlying the ethical judgements of adherents in their daily lives. The principle that all actions and choices are to be understood within the chain of cause and effect demands that individual conduct be evaluated not as an isolated event, but with full regard for its consequences upon society, the natural environment, and humanity as a whole.

This may be regarded as the very foundation of ethical autonomy within Shineidō. Adherents continually observe and analyse how their actions affect those around them and what lies ahead, and select their conduct in light of those consequences. This process, free of dependence upon external authority or fixed norms, encourages judgement that arises from within — grounded in personal experience and reason. Causal reasoning thus functions not as "a framework for theoretical understanding of ethics," but as "a practical guide for daily life."

Furthermore, causal reasoning serves as an indispensable method for comprehending the mutual relationship between the individual and society. Every personal choice carries consequences of considerable breadth, bearing the potential either to contribute to social harmony and the health of the natural environment, or to imperil them. In Shineidō, adherents are required to recognise this chain of causation and, through the active selection of ethical conduct, to pursue simultaneously the flourishing of the individual and the good of society as a whole.
----

== Spiritual Cultivation ==
Ethical cultivation in Shineidō extends considerably beyond mere moral education or the observance of behavioural codes; it is the central practice through which the individual's instinct is refined. Adherents cultivate their instinct and nurture reason by consciously practising benevolence, righteousness, loyalty, filial piety, and propriety in the course of daily life. This discipline is conceived not as compulsion from without or as obedience to dogma, but as autonomous self-cultivation underpinned by causal reasoning.

=== The Virtues ===
Benevolence and righteousness cultivate the instinctive disposition towards harmony with others; loyalty fosters the sense of responsibility to fulfil one's convictions and duties with integrity. Filial piety strengthens the foundations of social relationship through respect for family and ancestors, whilst propriety deepens one's understanding of order and social norms within the community. These ethical practices at once sharpen the individual's capacity for judgement and refinement of action, and cultivate the ability to realise social harmony and coexistence with nature.

=== Awareness of Social and Natural Responsibility ===
Cultivation is conceived not merely as the ordering of the individual spirit, but as an act of conscious responsibility towards society and the natural environment. Adherents observe the effect of their conduct upon those around them and upon the environment, and select their actions accordingly. This process is intimately bound to the understanding of causal reasoning, reinforcing the scientific and philosophical foundations of Shineidō conduct.

=== Continuity of Practice and the Formation of Habit ===
Its effects cannot be obtained through isolated acts or fleeting reflection alone; adherents are called upon to render the cultivation of instinct and the nurturing of reason habitual, through repeated practice in daily life. Sustained discipline promotes the automatisation of ethical conduct, enabling one to make choices naturally in accordance with the Shineidō spirit — grounded in goodwill — even in circumstances of adversity or sudden demand for decision.
----

== Application to Contemporary Spiritual Difficulties, and Demonstrated Results ==
The ethical cultivation of Shineidō is held to be efficacious in addressing the spiritual and social difficulties prevalent in modern society. Indeed, amongst adherents who have sustained the discipline and social activities prescribed by the Watanabe school's doctrine, cases have been reported of recovery from depression, social withdrawal, school refusal, and prolonged unemployment — with successful reintegration into society and the rekindling of the will to learn. These outcomes demonstrate that ethical cultivation possesses practical efficacy in the real world, not merely through the adjustment of the individual's inner life, but through social engagement and causal understanding.
----

== The Shineidō Spirit ==
Adherents of Shineidō are known as ''Shineishi'' (神衞志士 — Shineidō aspirants). They hold strictly to the following precepts.

=== The Twenty-One Precepts of the Shineishi ===

# Devote thyself to sincerity.
# Hold family and friends in high esteem.
# Never forget the profound benevolence of the Supreme Commander.
# Never forget the benevolence of thy father and mother.
# Never forget the benevolence of thy teacher.
# Never forget the benevolence of others.
# Never treat the faith of another with contempt.
# Never despise the young.
# Never surrender thyself to anger.
# Never rejoice in the misfortune of another.
# Serve the good to the utmost of thy ability.
# Never pursue thine own good whilst disregarding that of others.
# Give thanks to those who sustain thy daily life.
# Let not propriety fall into disorder.
# Never pursue learning or the arts for the sake of reputation or gain.
# Conduct thyself at all times as though receiving a guest.
# Never boast of thy virtuous deeds nor seek to make them known to others.
# Never mock the differing capacities of others.
# Whatsoever thou knowest not, seek instruction from any person and learn.
# Forgive the errors of others.
# Should any transgress against faith and honour, meet them in open and honourable combat.

=== The Seven Precepts of the Shineidō Soldier ===

# The Shineidō soldier shall render loyal service and shall not shrink from death.
# The Shineidō soldier shall esteem frugality and guard against extravagance.
# The Shineidō soldier shall keep all matters of secrecy inviolate and shall never permit their disclosure.
# The Shineidō soldier shall refine his martial valour and strive for daily improvement.
# The Shineidō soldier shall hold honour and faith dear and shall never violate his sworn word.
# The Shineidō soldier shall recognise the enemy as a man of honour, and engage him with due respect, openly and with dignity.
# The Shineidō soldier shall act in concert with his comrades and shall never lose his composure.

=== Commentary ===
These are not mere religious precepts; they constitute a philosophy of what Aristotle termed ''phronesis'' — practical wisdom. Rather than abstract principle, they give primacy to sound judgement and right action in concrete circumstances.

The greatest strength of Shineidō lies in its practicality and its flexibility. The words — ''"Even one who has not mastered the doctrine, if he be of steadfast spirit and hold his soul aright, is already a man of the Shineidō"'' — express a refusal of dogmatism and place sincerity of spirit at the very highest station.
----

== Shineidō Organisations ==

=== The Shineidō Head Office ''(Shineidō Honchō)'' ===
The mainstream organisation, of which Kimitake Watanabe serves as Secretary-General. It venerates Hayato Kanda as a living deity, and as the majority of Shineidō soldiers belong to its ranks, it carries about it something of the atmosphere of a fraternity of warriors.

=== The National Shineidō Federation ''(Zenkoku Shineidō Renmei)'' ===
A contemporary Shineidō organisation to which many Shineishi who are not Shineidō soldiers belong. A broad diversity of adherents is to be found within its membership; it deifies Hayato Kanda as an absolute being, and stands in opposition to the Head Office on the matter of the degree of that deification.

=== The Shineidō Science League ''(Shineidō Kagaku Renmei)'' ===
An organisation that interprets Shineidō in a philosophical vein, expressing concern that the advance of science has led to the erosion of virtue and morality in religion, giving rise to a distorted individualism. Its aim is to root the Shineidō spirit within the foundations of learning and the arts.

There exist also independent Shineishi affiliated with none of these schools. This follows from Kimitake Watanabe's declaration that ''"Even one who has not mastered the doctrine, if he be of steadfast spirit and hold his soul aright, is already a man of the Shineidō"'' — from which it may be understood that any person who acts in the Shineidō manner and holds the will to believe is a Shineishi.
----

== Freedom of Belief ==
Whilst Shineidō is a religion, it is distinguished by an open disposition that acknowledges the faith of others. This reflects the spirit of the precept ''"Never treat the faith of another with contempt"'' from the Twenty-One Precepts of the Shineishi, and arises from the view that faith itself is an act that elevates the happiness of the individual. The founder Kimitake Watanabe places great importance upon the spiritual refinement attained through faith, and actively commends understanding and coexistence with other religions. Adherents who pursue their own happiness through their cultural background and inner inquiry are equally welcomed.

Yet this tolerance is not without its limits. Within Shineidō, voices persistently critical of monotheism — Christianity and Islam in particular — as "dangerous ideologies liable to engender slaughter and exclusion" remain considerable. Many Shineishi hold that the exclusivity and absolutism of monotheism have historically given rise to war and persecution, and regard this as contrary to the precepts ''"Never rejoice in the misfortune of another"'' and ''"Never pursue thine own good whilst disregarding that of others."'' This criticism has become a central point of debate, being seen as standing in opposition to the "philosophy of humanity" that Shineidō seeks to embody, and to the ideal of a harmonious communal society.

In practice, the majority of Shineidō adherents are of Japanese ethnicity, and those who follow Shintō constitute a considerable portion. The very name "Shineidō" carries the meaning of protecting that which is sacred, and the tradition holds a natural affinity with Shintō's veneration of nature and its belief in the myriad deities. Many Shineishi hold a dual identity — as Shintō practitioners and as Shineishi — venerating Hayato Kanda as a living deity whilst preserving their respect for Japan's traditional gods. In this regard, Shineidō may be regarded as a new religious movement rooted in the distinctively Japanese religious sensibility.

At the same time, there exist those who profess atheism whilst feeling an affinity with Shineidō. These individuals, whilst rejecting the concept of a creator deity, are drawn to the ethical norms and humanitarian values expressed in precepts such as ''"Devote thyself to sincerity"'' and ''"Serve the good to the utmost of thy ability,"'' and become Shineishi on that account.</text>
      <sha1>ezg3h2lqumhsqxvhtxtpn0j623kgqdu</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3559106</id>
      <parentid>3503405</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T19:57:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: categorize uncategorized page [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23359502324|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3559106</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="17435" sha1="d6qwcuwjzxswaq154yaewg1sst6gplz" xml:space="preserve">[[Shineidō （神衞道）|Shineidō]] is a religious and philosophical system founded by [[Kimitake Watanabe]], developed upon the teachings of Supreme Commander Hayato Kanda. This tradition extends considerably beyond the mere framework of faith, distinguishing itself by integrating ethics, Eastern philosophy, and scientific thought into a unified whole — placing at its centre the cultivation of human instinct, social responsibility, and harmonious coexistence with the natural world. Supreme Commander Hayato Kanda placed particular emphasis upon adherents attaining the Shineidō spirit not through elaborate doctrine or ceremonial formality, but through the conduct of their daily lives, thereby pursuing human flourishing in its truest sense. This approach makes plain that faith is not a matter of passive submission, but one that deepens through autonomous ethical practice.

Kimitake Watanabe's deification of the Supreme Commander stands as a significant element of Shineidō's devotional character; yet the doctrine is by no means reducible to mere veneration of a divine figure. Rather, adherents are encouraged to draw upon the insights of ethics, philosophy, and the natural sciences — approaching doctrine with an experimental and scholarly disposition, deepening their understanding through inward cultivation. Accordingly, whilst the degree of the Supreme Commander's deification varies amongst sects and organisations, the reverence afforded to him as the spiritual centre of the tradition is common to all, forming the foundation of its ideological coherence.

Of particular note is the emphasis placed upon forming ethical reason not from external authority or fixed dogma, but from within — grounded in personal experience, observation, and causal reasoning. The innate goodness of human instinct is taken as a given, and reason is understood as that which emerges naturally through the disciplined cultivation of those instincts. This philosophy prizes the process by which the individual arrives at ethical judgement autonomously, observing and analysing one's own actions and their consequences, thereby achieving moral maturity. In short, it is made explicit that ethics and reason are not norms imposed from without, but are generated through each person's independent cultivation and practice.

Shineidō situates human existence within the causal structure of the cosmos and nature, holding that the actions and ethics of the individual are to be understood through their interaction with society and the natural world. In this respect, Shineidō differs markedly from traditional religious ethics and the moral frameworks of monotheism, standing instead as a practical religious philosophy that recognises, at its very root, the interconnectedness of the individual with society and with nature.
----

== Overview ==
The foundational principles of Shineidō begin with a scientific definition of the human being — not as a mere individual, but as an inherently social creature. In the doctrinal interpretation of the Watanabe school, human thought and conduct are understood through the interplay between the instinctive dispositions resident within the individual and the reason cultivated by their proper discipline. As a social animal, the human being has evolved and adapted not in isolation, but through relationship with community and natural environment; it is upon this understanding that ethics and codes of conduct are formed.

The rationalism and monotheism of Western religion are held, from a scientific standpoint, to contain fundamental errors. In particular, the notion that morality and reason are prescribed by an external absolute authority or supernatural being is regarded as suppressing the independent thought of adherents, bearing with it the danger of intellectual paralysis and dependent faith. Nevertheless, the spirit of Shineidō holds the freedom of belief in high esteem; accordingly, a degree of latitude exists in the interpretations and practices of non-Watanabe schools, and diversity corresponding to the convictions of individual sects and adherents is fully acknowledged.

The central claim of Watanabe school doctrine is this: that, grounded in modern science, the proper cultivation of humanity's instincts constitutes the social good by which common flourishing may be built. "Cultivation of instinct," as understood here, refers not to any self-indulgent form of training, but to a process of developing instinct through physical discipline and ethical conduct, thereby sharpening the individual's capacity for judgement. Adherents consciously practise benevolence, righteousness, loyalty, filial piety, and propriety in the course of daily life; through the repetition of right conduct, they achieve the Shineidō attainment. It is this repetitive practice that is held to lead directly to the perfection of the Shineidō spirit — that is, to the individual's moral maturity and the realisation of social harmony.
----

== Foundational Doctrine ==
One of the cardinal ideas of Shineidō is the view that human instinct is, in its essence, good. Instinct comprises the innate behavioural tendencies with which one is born; ethics and reason are held to form naturally when these tendencies are properly cultivated. Errors of reason and moral deviation arise as consequences of the mistaken understanding or application of instinct — not, it is maintained, through the compulsion of external authority or doctrinal norms. This view, rooted in the doctrine of original human goodness, regards moral growth as a matter of autonomous self-cultivation.

Adherents repeatedly perform ethical actions of their own volition, observing and analysing their inner lives, thereby deepening their understanding of the interplay between instinct and reason. This process is conceived not merely as a means of individual flourishing, but as a vehicle for pursuing the common good of society and humanity at large. That is to say, Shineidō teaches that the cultivation of ethics constitutes at once the spiritual growth of the individual and an act that realises the broader social good.
----

== Causal Reasoning ==
In Shineidō, causal reasoning is not confined to abstract theory or philosophical speculation; it is the fundamental mode of thought underlying the ethical judgements of adherents in their daily lives. The principle that all actions and choices are to be understood within the chain of cause and effect demands that individual conduct be evaluated not as an isolated event, but with full regard for its consequences upon society, the natural environment, and humanity as a whole.

This may be regarded as the very foundation of ethical autonomy within Shineidō. Adherents continually observe and analyse how their actions affect those around them and what lies ahead, and select their conduct in light of those consequences. This process, free of dependence upon external authority or fixed norms, encourages judgement that arises from within — grounded in personal experience and reason. Causal reasoning thus functions not as "a framework for theoretical understanding of ethics," but as "a practical guide for daily life."

Furthermore, causal reasoning serves as an indispensable method for comprehending the mutual relationship between the individual and society. Every personal choice carries consequences of considerable breadth, bearing the potential either to contribute to social harmony and the health of the natural environment, or to imperil them. In Shineidō, adherents are required to recognise this chain of causation and, through the active selection of ethical conduct, to pursue simultaneously the flourishing of the individual and the good of society as a whole.
----

== Spiritual Cultivation ==
Ethical cultivation in Shineidō extends considerably beyond mere moral education or the observance of behavioural codes; it is the central practice through which the individual's instinct is refined. Adherents cultivate their instinct and nurture reason by consciously practising benevolence, righteousness, loyalty, filial piety, and propriety in the course of daily life. This discipline is conceived not as compulsion from without or as obedience to dogma, but as autonomous self-cultivation underpinned by causal reasoning.

=== The Virtues ===
Benevolence and righteousness cultivate the instinctive disposition towards harmony with others; loyalty fosters the sense of responsibility to fulfil one's convictions and duties with integrity. Filial piety strengthens the foundations of social relationship through respect for family and ancestors, whilst propriety deepens one's understanding of order and social norms within the community. These ethical practices at once sharpen the individual's capacity for judgement and refinement of action, and cultivate the ability to realise social harmony and coexistence with nature.

=== Awareness of Social and Natural Responsibility ===
Cultivation is conceived not merely as the ordering of the individual spirit, but as an act of conscious responsibility towards society and the natural environment. Adherents observe the effect of their conduct upon those around them and upon the environment, and select their actions accordingly. This process is intimately bound to the understanding of causal reasoning, reinforcing the scientific and philosophical foundations of Shineidō conduct.

=== Continuity of Practice and the Formation of Habit ===
Its effects cannot be obtained through isolated acts or fleeting reflection alone; adherents are called upon to render the cultivation of instinct and the nurturing of reason habitual, through repeated practice in daily life. Sustained discipline promotes the automatisation of ethical conduct, enabling one to make choices naturally in accordance with the Shineidō spirit — grounded in goodwill — even in circumstances of adversity or sudden demand for decision.
----

== Application to Contemporary Spiritual Difficulties, and Demonstrated Results ==
The ethical cultivation of Shineidō is held to be efficacious in addressing the spiritual and social difficulties prevalent in modern society. Indeed, amongst adherents who have sustained the discipline and social activities prescribed by the Watanabe school's doctrine, cases have been reported of recovery from depression, social withdrawal, school refusal, and prolonged unemployment — with successful reintegration into society and the rekindling of the will to learn. These outcomes demonstrate that ethical cultivation possesses practical efficacy in the real world, not merely through the adjustment of the individual's inner life, but through social engagement and causal understanding.
----

== The Shineidō Spirit ==
Adherents of Shineidō are known as ''Shineishi'' (神衞志士 — Shineidō aspirants). They hold strictly to the following precepts.

=== The Twenty-One Precepts of the Shineishi ===

# Devote thyself to sincerity.
# Hold family and friends in high esteem.
# Never forget the profound benevolence of the Supreme Commander.
# Never forget the benevolence of thy father and mother.
# Never forget the benevolence of thy teacher.
# Never forget the benevolence of others.
# Never treat the faith of another with contempt.
# Never despise the young.
# Never surrender thyself to anger.
# Never rejoice in the misfortune of another.
# Serve the good to the utmost of thy ability.
# Never pursue thine own good whilst disregarding that of others.
# Give thanks to those who sustain thy daily life.
# Let not propriety fall into disorder.
# Never pursue learning or the arts for the sake of reputation or gain.
# Conduct thyself at all times as though receiving a guest.
# Never boast of thy virtuous deeds nor seek to make them known to others.
# Never mock the differing capacities of others.
# Whatsoever thou knowest not, seek instruction from any person and learn.
# Forgive the errors of others.
# Should any transgress against faith and honour, meet them in open and honourable combat.

=== The Seven Precepts of the Shineidō Soldier ===

# The Shineidō soldier shall render loyal service and shall not shrink from death.
# The Shineidō soldier shall esteem frugality and guard against extravagance.
# The Shineidō soldier shall keep all matters of secrecy inviolate and shall never permit their disclosure.
# The Shineidō soldier shall refine his martial valour and strive for daily improvement.
# The Shineidō soldier shall hold honour and faith dear and shall never violate his sworn word.
# The Shineidō soldier shall recognise the enemy as a man of honour, and engage him with due respect, openly and with dignity.
# The Shineidō soldier shall act in concert with his comrades and shall never lose his composure.

=== Commentary ===
These are not mere religious precepts; they constitute a philosophy of what Aristotle termed ''phronesis'' — practical wisdom. Rather than abstract principle, they give primacy to sound judgement and right action in concrete circumstances.

The greatest strength of Shineidō lies in its practicality and its flexibility. The words — ''"Even one who has not mastered the doctrine, if he be of steadfast spirit and hold his soul aright, is already a man of the Shineidō"'' — express a refusal of dogmatism and place sincerity of spirit at the very highest station.
----

== Shineidō Organisations ==

=== The Shineidō Head Office ''(Shineidō Honchō)'' ===
The mainstream organisation, of which Kimitake Watanabe serves as Secretary-General. It venerates Hayato Kanda as a living deity, and as the majority of Shineidō soldiers belong to its ranks, it carries about it something of the atmosphere of a fraternity of warriors.

=== The National Shineidō Federation ''(Zenkoku Shineidō Renmei)'' ===
A contemporary Shineidō organisation to which many Shineishi who are not Shineidō soldiers belong. A broad diversity of adherents is to be found within its membership; it deifies Hayato Kanda as an absolute being, and stands in opposition to the Head Office on the matter of the degree of that deification.

=== The Shineidō Science League ''(Shineidō Kagaku Renmei)'' ===
An organisation that interprets Shineidō in a philosophical vein, expressing concern that the advance of science has led to the erosion of virtue and morality in religion, giving rise to a distorted individualism. Its aim is to root the Shineidō spirit within the foundations of learning and the arts.

There exist also independent Shineishi affiliated with none of these schools. This follows from Kimitake Watanabe's declaration that ''"Even one who has not mastered the doctrine, if he be of steadfast spirit and hold his soul aright, is already a man of the Shineidō"'' — from which it may be understood that any person who acts in the Shineidō manner and holds the will to believe is a Shineishi.
----

== Freedom of Belief ==
Whilst Shineidō is a religion, it is distinguished by an open disposition that acknowledges the faith of others. This reflects the spirit of the precept ''"Never treat the faith of another with contempt"'' from the Twenty-One Precepts of the Shineishi, and arises from the view that faith itself is an act that elevates the happiness of the individual. The founder Kimitake Watanabe places great importance upon the spiritual refinement attained through faith, and actively commends understanding and coexistence with other religions. Adherents who pursue their own happiness through their cultural background and inner inquiry are equally welcomed.

Yet this tolerance is not without its limits. Within Shineidō, voices persistently critical of monotheism — Christianity and Islam in particular — as "dangerous ideologies liable to engender slaughter and exclusion" remain considerable. Many Shineishi hold that the exclusivity and absolutism of monotheism have historically given rise to war and persecution, and regard this as contrary to the precepts ''"Never rejoice in the misfortune of another"'' and ''"Never pursue thine own good whilst disregarding that of others."'' This criticism has become a central point of debate, being seen as standing in opposition to the "philosophy of humanity" that Shineidō seeks to embody, and to the ideal of a harmonious communal society.

In practice, the majority of Shineidō adherents are of Japanese ethnicity, and those who follow Shintō constitute a considerable portion. The very name "Shineidō" carries the meaning of protecting that which is sacred, and the tradition holds a natural affinity with Shintō's veneration of nature and its belief in the myriad deities. Many Shineishi hold a dual identity — as Shintō practitioners and as Shineishi — venerating Hayato Kanda as a living deity whilst preserving their respect for Japan's traditional gods. In this regard, Shineidō may be regarded as a new religious movement rooted in the distinctively Japanese religious sensibility.

At the same time, there exist those who profess atheism whilst feeling an affinity with Shineidō. These individuals, whilst rejecting the concept of a creator deity, are drawn to the ethical norms and humanitarian values expressed in precepts such as ''"Devote thyself to sincerity"'' and ''"Serve the good to the utmost of thy ability,"'' and become Shineishi on that account.
[[Category:Uncategorized pages]]</text>
      <sha1>d6qwcuwjzxswaq154yaewg1sst6gplz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
