<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Help:File description page</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>4839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>777872</id>
      <timestamp>2024-06-18T21:27:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>en&gt;Kinu</username>
        <id>0</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit by [[Special:Contribs/Terence1979|Terence1979]] ([[User talk:Terence1979|talk]]) to last version by A455bcd9</comment>
      <origin>777872</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12104" sha1="ez40h1b6vuhc5mfmzbpqy5k5bcpgz5g" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[GIMP]] or [[Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]
[[Category:Wikipedia copyright]]</text>
      <sha1>ez40h1b6vuhc5mfmzbpqy5k5bcpgz5g</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777873</id>
      <parentid>777872</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-19T02:12:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 revision imported: importing wikipedia</comment>
      <origin>777872</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12104" sha1="ez40h1b6vuhc5mfmzbpqy5k5bcpgz5g" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[GIMP]] or [[Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]
[[Category:Wikipedia copyright]]</text>
      <sha1>ez40h1b6vuhc5mfmzbpqy5k5bcpgz5g</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777874</id>
      <parentid>777873</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-14T06:00:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove sole member from [[Category:Wikipedia copyright]]</comment>
      <origin>777874</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12071" sha1="aj90zipzmx586tbsf2tur9b31p18btu" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[GIMP]] or [[Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>aj90zipzmx586tbsf2tur9b31p18btu</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777875</id>
      <parentid>777874</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-19T04:51:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777875</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12075" sha1="pskzqmmv430fe2whan9afonjjkq961h" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>pskzqmmv430fe2whan9afonjjkq961h</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777876</id>
      <parentid>777875</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-19T17:06:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777876</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12084" sha1="5kgr89izf1ty04h1ku6ww2m2uf5f0e9" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>5kgr89izf1ty04h1ku6ww2m2uf5f0e9</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777877</id>
      <parentid>777876</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-19T19:42:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777877</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12115" sha1="976tdcn0mm6k29a08f52wcn3leui7mw" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>976tdcn0mm6k29a08f52wcn3leui7mw</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777878</id>
      <parentid>777877</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-20T19:12:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777878</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12124" sha1="d4lgkgz4n5pblnwtiphcs5qury3uvw2" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>d4lgkgz4n5pblnwtiphcs5qury3uvw2</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777879</id>
      <parentid>777878</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-20T19:30:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777879</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12133" sha1="rbod73dmco0ht2msomus1sg9zfh7cvs" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[:en:HTML|HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>rbod73dmco0ht2msomus1sg9zfh7cvs</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777880</id>
      <parentid>777879</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-24T18:24:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777880</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12141" sha1="ihdb2swy191u5wy3fpnbvkjhe5blsai" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[:en:URL|URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[:en:HTML|HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>ihdb2swy191u5wy3fpnbvkjhe5blsai</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777881</id>
      <parentid>777880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-24T21:45:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777881</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12185" sha1="8f6431zcnzphqc3wlroai6pgo3h9y6z" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[:en:URL|URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[:en:HTML|HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>8f6431zcnzphqc3wlroai6pgo3h9y6z</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>777882</id>
      <parentid>777881</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-05-24T22:18:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>777882</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12196" sha1="e4gvzxa8einqd78eigcg75f9il5wosg" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[:en:WinZip|WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[:en:URL|URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[:en:HTML|HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>e4gvzxa8einqd78eigcg75f9il5wosg</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>4840</id>
      <timestamp>2025-05-25T00:27:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>imported only latest revision from https://archive.org/details/miraheze-wiki-shintowiki-20251218 to avoid excessive disk usage, comment on the revision was Bot: convert local link → enwiki interwiki</comment>
      <origin>4840</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12200" sha1="mesa29uej42pphjmmj9gsc1x2hoiv79" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Wikipedia how-to|WP:IDP|H:FDP}}

When a file such as an image, video or sound clip is [[Help:Images and other uploaded files|uploaded]] to Wikipedia or the Wikimedia Commons, an associated '''file description page''' is created (also known as an '''image description page''' or '''file page'''). The purpose of these pages is to provide information about the file: for example the author, date of creation, who uploaded the file, any modifications that may have been made, an extended description of the file's subject or context, where the file is used, and license or copyright information. In the case of an image, the file description page shows a higher resolution version of the image, if available. 

To view the file description page for an image or video, click on the image itself. For a sound file, click on the information icon, [[File:OOjs UI icon information-progressive.svg]], near the sound clip link.

A file description page consists of five parts:
*The contents of the file itself.
*The [[Help:Editing|editable section]]: This should include a description of the file, plus source and copyright information. When editing, this section allows [[Wikipedia:Wiki Markup Language]] (also known as [[Wikipedia:Glossary#W|Wikitext]]) and should include some or all the parameters of [[Template:Information]]. 
*File history: If a new version of a file is uploaded with the same name, the existing file is replaced and becomes available via file history. See [[Help:Page history]].
*File usage: A list of pages that embed the file (including pages where the file appears as part of a template). If a file is stored on Commons and used on other Wikimedia wikis, a "Global file usage" section will be included as well.
*Metadata (images only): Technical information about the file and the equipment used to create it (camera model, etc.).

The following are examples of different types of files:
*[[:File:Leucospermum cultivar Edit.jpg|Image example]]
*[[:File:Russian national anthem at Medvedev inauguration 2008.ogv|Video example]]
*[[:File:Edison cylinder Lost Chord.ogg|Sound example]]
*[[:File:Abroad - 1882.djvu|Mixed content example (DjVu in this case, but could also be PDF)]]

==Useful things to include in the editable section==
The editable section of the page is used to describe the file and provide additional information. Initially this section automatically contains the upload summary supplied when the file was first uploaded. The following are useful things to put on a file page:

===File description===
E.g.: "Image of a goldfish in a small tank". This should not be an alternative text (see [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images|alternative text for images]]), but rather a description. This is useful for users who do not have direct access to the image, and is a temporary substitute for a proper &lt;code&gt;longdesc&lt;/code&gt; tag.

If you downloaded the file from somewhere else, you should give details of source, author, etc. If you made the file based on other sources, you should cite them. See [[Wikipedia:Cite your sources]].

===File summary===
This is where you write the additional information about the file and how it was created, where, when, how, and by whom, as well as what the image is and what it is about.
Example:
"A picture I took underwater with a ___ camera, of a ____ fish." or "An original illustration of cars from the future and their bent wheels."

====Image summary====
Most articles that use images will have a [[Wikipedia:Caption|caption]], but this will probably be shorter than the image's full description, and more closely related to the text of the article.

Keep in mind that everyone who sees this image in an article and clicks on it for more information (or to enlarge it) arrives at the file description page.

If you made the image yourself, there are certain questions which only you can answer. Because you may not be around to answer those questions later, you should include this information in the description page when you upload the image. This will help other editors to make better use of the image, and it will be more informative for readers.

For photographs:
* Where was the photograph taken?
* When was the photograph taken?
* What are the names of all the people and notable objects visible in the photograph?
* What is happening in the photograph?
* Who was the photographer?

For synthetic pictures:
* Diagrams and markings should be explained as completely as possible. 
* If necessary, a legend or key should be provided.

Technical information for photographs:
* If a film camera was used, provide the model number, lens information and exposure settings.
* What post-production modifications were made? (adjustments to color, contrast etc.)

Technical information for synthetic images:
* What software was used to create or edit the image?
* What pre-existing sources (free images, photos, etc.) were used as inputs?

===Copyright information===
All files must be provided with copyright information. This includes the author, the file's source and the file's license. All files must either be freely licensed or suitable for "[[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|fair use]]" (a low resolution image or only part of a song for example). You should choose the most appropriate tag from [[Wikipedia:File copyright tags]]. Please be aware that the copyright holder (the original creator of the file, their employer, or an official designee), not the uploader, decides on the licensing for the image, and that "fair use" of non-free files has a specific definition. Please read [[Wikipedia:Copyrights]], [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]], [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|Wikipedia:Fair use guideline]], and [[Wikipedia:Non-free content]] for information about what images are acceptable to upload. If you have a question about a specific image, you can ask at [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]].

===Relevant links (internal)===
Example:
* ''See also: [[:en:Flag of the United Kingdom|Flag of the United Kingdom]]''

===Other versions===
If other versions (especially a larger version) of the same file exists, link to them.

* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|different camera angle]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank2.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
* ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Media:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|textfree version]] ([[:Image:Goldfish-in-tank-textfree.jpg|info]])&lt;/nowiki&gt;''

Textfree versions are useful for using across language versions.

==Other points==
===Wikimedia Commons===
Files available on Wikipedia can be stored on Wikipedia or on [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]]. If a file is stored on Commons the following message will be shown on the file's description page:
{{MediaWiki:Sharedupload-desc-here}}
Any edits to the file's description page should be made on Commons, except in special circumstances, such as indicating the file has reached featured status on Wikipedia. To edit the Commons description page click on the "description page there" link. Like Wikipedia, anyone can edit the Commons. An account is not required.

===Preview===
When editing, the [[Help:Show preview|Show preview]] function only shows the editable part of a file page. The file itself, the file history and the file links are not displayed.

===Editing a file===
Files cannot be edited on Wikipedia or Commons. To edit a file it will need to be downloaded. Use a suitable software program (such as the [[:en:GIMP|GIMP]] or [[:en:Adobe Photoshop|Photoshop]] for images) to perform the modifications. Once the changes are completed upload the file to Wikipedia or Commons. The same filename may be used. This will overwrite the existing file.

===What happens when you upload===
The description text you supply during the upload process becomes the initial text of the image description page. (It also becomes the [[Wikipedia:Edit summary|edit summary]] for the initial version of the file.)

===Inter-language coordination===
On Wikipedia, please avoid adding a description in a language other than English. Instead, use [[Wikipedia:interlanguage links|interlanguage links]] to link to the image description page on the appropriate-language wiki, where you should upload a second copy of the image for local use.

On Commons, a translation may be added to the description page.

===Uploading original images===
If you have created an image yourself, and you have a higher-quality source file in a format such as .XCF, .PSD, or .AI, you may want to consider uploading that source file so that other users can more easily modify it if the need arises. Link the source file from the image description page. If the source file is too large to upload, try compressing it with a utility such as [[:en:WinZip|WinZip]] or [[:en:Gzip|Gzip]].

Wikipedia supports displaying [[:en:Scalable Vector Graphics|SVG]] images, so it's generally best to upload SVG copies of images in place of raster renderings of them.

===Categorizing files===
Files can be in the same category as other pages, but are treated separately: on the category page they are not included in the count of articles in the category, and they are displayed in a separate section, with for each a thumbnail and the name, see [[Help:Category#Category_pages|category page]]. A file category is typically a subcategory of the general category about the same subject, and a subcategory of a wider file category. On [[:en:Wikimedia Commons|Wikimedia Commons]] there are essentially only files. 

For categorizing a new file, the file page does not even have to be edited: the category tag can simply be put in the [[Help:Edit summary#File_upload_summary|upload summary]]. Many images can be categorized in one of the subcategories of [[:Category:Wikipedia images by subject]]. You might need to poke around the category hierarchy a bit to find the right place.

===File page location===
In English Wikipedia, the file page for a media file named &lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt; is at &amp;lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http&lt;/nowiki&gt;://{{SERVERNAME}}/wiki/File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;&amp;gt;, and it can be accessed using the [[WP:MARKUP|Wiki markup]] &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[&lt;/nowiki&gt;:File:&lt;var&gt;F&lt;/var&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt;. A media file's name can be determined from its [[:en:URL|URL]]: it is always the URL's last or second-from-last component. For example, a flag image [[Image:Flag of France.svg|x12px|border|link=|alt=]] might have the following URL:
: &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;&amp;lt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Flag_of_France.svg/18px-Flag_of_France.svg.png&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
This URL's second-from-last component is "Flag_of_France.svg", so the corresponding file page is ''[[:File:Flag_of_France.svg]]''.

The URL of an image can often be determined by asking a browser to display the image's properties, and similarly for other media files. Sometimes, however, you may need to view the [[:en:HTML|HTML]] of the page containing a media file to determine the file's URL. For example, in standard browsers the default English Wikipedia [[Wikipedia:Skin|skin]] displays at upper left a puzzle-globe image, which takes you to the [[Main Page]] if you click on it; to find this image's file page, look in this page's HTML for the following:
: &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;a style="background-image: url(http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/bc/Wiki.png);" href="/wiki/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
This HTML contains a URL whose last component is "Wiki.png", and the corresponding file page is therefore ''[[:File:Wiki.png]]''.

==See also==

*[[Help:Files]]
*[[Help:Visual file markup]] - for placing a visual file in an article
*[[Help:Sound file markup]] - for placing a sound file in an article
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images]]
*[[Template:Information]] - the template that is used in the file's description summary, including the template's documentation 
*[[Wikipedia:Uploading images#File description page's Summary mark-up text|Wikipedia:Uploading images § File description page's Summary mark-up text]] - an example of the Information template with the parameters explained, designed to be copied and pasted for easier editing

{{Wikipedia technical help}}
{{Help navigation}}

[[Category:Wikipedia image help|Description page, Wikipedia image]]</text>
      <sha1>mesa29uej42pphjmmj9gsc1x2hoiv79</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
