<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chinese Cultural Renaissance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1263</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3592916</id>
      <parentid>3397078</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:30:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3592916</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="40723" sha1="k3m3aauymoqw35rqu5qn1clr6uclces" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[de:Chinesische Kulturrenaissance]][[en:Chinese Cultural Renaissance]][[id:Renaisans Kebudayaan Tionghoa]][[ko:중화문화부흥운동]][[vi:Phong trào Phục hưng Văn hóa Trung Hoa]][[zh:中華文化復興運動]]
{{Multiple issues|
{{Essay-like|date=May 2023|qq=}}
{{grammar|date=June 2023|qq=}}
{{morefootnotes|date=June 2023|qq=}}
}}
{{Short description|1960s cultural movement in Taiwan|qq=}}
The '''Chinese Cultural Renaissance''' or the '''Chinese Cultural Renaissance Movement''' ({{zh|t=中華文化復興運動|p=Zhōnghuá Wénhuà Fùxīng Yùndòng|qq=}}) was a movement promoted in {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=Taiwan|1=Taiwan}} in opposition to the cultural destructions caused by the {{ill|Chinese Communist Party|en|Chinese Communist Party|qid=Q17427|lt=Chinese Communist Party|1=Chinese Communist Party}} during the {{ill|Cultural Revolution|en|Cultural Revolution|qid=Q8690|lt=Cultural Revolution|1=Cultural Revolution}}.&lt;ref name="Wachman"&gt;{{ill|Alan M. Wachman |en|Alan M. Wachman |qid=Q15429162|lt= Wachman, Alan M.|1=Alan M. Wachman}} [1994] (1994). Taiwan: National Identity and Democratization. M.E. Sharpe publishing. {{ISBN|1-56324-398-9|qq=}}. pg 274.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese Cultural Revival Movement is an ideological and cultural movement launched by {{ill|Government of the Republic of China|en|Government of the Republic of China|qid=Q5589404|lt=the government of the Republic of China|1=Government of the Republic of China}} with the aim of reviving {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}}. In order to maintain traditional Chinese culture and carry forward the revolutionary spirit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=李守孔 |title=《中國現代史》 |publisher=三民書局 |year=1973 |isbn=978-957-14-0663-3 |location=台北|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contend with the Cultural Revolution movement of the Chinese Communist Party to show that the Republic of China is the representative of orthodox {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}}. In November 1966, 1,500 people, including {{ill|Sun Fo|en|Sun Fo|qid=Q701897|lt=Sun Ke|1=Sun Fo}}, {{ill|Wang Yun-wu|en|Wang Yun-wu|qid=Q759889|lt=Wang Yunwu|1=Wang Yun-wu}}, {{ill|Chen Lifu|en|Chen Lifu|qid=Q698368|lt=Chen Lifu|1=Chen Lifu}}, [[:zh:陳啓天|Chen Qitian]], {{ill|Kung Te-cheng|en|Kung Te-cheng|qid=Q698846|lt=Kong Decheng|1=Kung Te-cheng}}, and [[:zh:張知本|Zhang Zhiben]], wrote a letter to the {{ill|Executive Yuan|en|Executive Yuan|qid=Q715055|lt=Executive Yuan|1=Executive Yuan}}, the "Chinese Cultural Revival Movement" was proposed and the "Chinese Cultural Revival Festival" was designated as November 12 each year.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |last=李松林 |title=《蔣介石的台灣時代》 |publisher=風雲時代出版 |year=1993 |isbn=957-645-416-6 |location=台北|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 28, 1967, people from all walks of life in {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=Taiwan|1=Taiwan}} held the initiation meeting of [[:zh:中華文化總會|the Chinese Cultural Revival Movement Implementation Committee]] (now known as the Chinese Cultural Federation), {{ill|President of the Republic of China|en|President of the Republic of China|qid=Q887003|lt=The President of the Republic of China|1=President of the Republic of China}} {{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Chiang Kai-shek|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} as the president, and the movement was implemented in {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=Taiwan|1=Taiwan}} and overseas.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
== Origin ==
Because {{ill|Mainland China|en|Mainland China|qid=Q19188|lt=Chinese mainland|1=Mainland China}} was in the midst of the catastrophe of the "{{ill|Cultural Revolution|en|Cultural Revolution|qid=Q8690|lt=Cultural Revolution|1=Cultural Revolution}}" at that time, under the slogan of "shattering the old and building the new", a significant amount of Chinese cultural heritage was greatly damaged, and mainland Chinese cultural and intellectual circles were humiliated and destroyed. This is another major disaster after the establishment of the Chinese Communist Party, which has had a very negative impact on the normal development of Chinese culture; The {{ill|Government of the Republic of China|en|Government of the Republic of China|qid=Q5589404|lt=Government of the Republic of China|1=Government of the Republic of China}} then raised the banner of reviving Chinese culture, hoping to establish itself as the successor and defender of Chinese culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |script-title=zh:《蔣介石與中國文化》 |publisher=中華書局 |year=1992 |location=Hongkong |page=122 |author=陳鐵健  |author2=黃鐵炫|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Aims and objectives of the movement ==
* Taking {{ill|Ethics|en|Ethics|qid=Q9465|lt=Ethics|1=Ethics}} and {{ill|Morality|en|Morality|qid=Q48324|lt=Morality|1=Morality}} as the foundation of a virtuous society. The most specific behavioral representations are {{ill|Loyalty|en|Loyalty|qid=Q1132131|lt=Loyalty|1=Loyalty}}, {{ill|Filial piety|en|Filial piety|qid=Q614263|lt=Filial piety|1=Filial piety}}, {{ill|Ren (philosophy)|en|Ren (philosophy)|qid=Q1196421|lt=Ren (philosophy)|1=Ren (philosophy)}}, {{ill|Love|en|Love|qid=Q316|lt=Love|1=Love}}, {{ill|Letter (message)|en|Letter (message)|qid=Q133492|lt=Letter (message)|1=Letter (message)}}, {{ill|Yi (philosophy)|en|Yi (philosophy)|qid=Q8053433|lt=''Yi'' (philosophy)|1=Yi (philosophy)}}, and peace; Its most important {{ill|Philosophy|en|Philosophy|qid=Q5891|lt=philosophical|1=Philosophy}} foundation is the word "Ren (philosophy)".
* Taking {{ill|Democracy|en|Democracy|qid=Q7174|lt=Democracy|1=Democracy}} and {{ill|Liberty|en|Liberty|qid=Q2979|lt=Liberty|1=Liberty}} as the principle of benefiting the country, there is a great law that the whole country adheres to, namely the {{ill|Constitution of the Republic of China|en|Constitution of the Republic of China|qid=Q213099|lt=Constitution of the Republic of China|1=Constitution of the Republic of China}}. Keep {{ill|Politics|en|Politics|qid=Q7163|lt=political|1=Politics}} initiatives on track.{{ill|Legislative Yuan|en|Legislative Yuan|qid=Q715869|lt=Legislative Yuan|1=Legislative Yuan}} should be able to exercise its powers freely, so that the effectiveness of the {{ill|Law of Taiwan|en|Law of Taiwan|qid=Q6503489|lt=law|1=Law of Taiwan}} can be eternal. Belonging to the rule of the people and establishing the rule of law.
* The ultimate goal of using science and technology as a moral principle and benefiting the people is to support them. The way of raising the people does not involve the six aspects of {{ill|Clothing|en|Clothing|qid=Q11460|lt=Clothing|1=Clothing}}, food, {{ill|Domicile (law)|en|Domicile (law)|qid=Q2641256|lt=Domicile (law)|1=Domicile (law)}}, transportation, {{ill|Education|en|Education|qid=Q8434|lt=Education|1=Education}}, and happiness. Therefore, the {{ill|Science|en|Science|qid=Q336|lt=scientific|1=Science}} {{ill|Construction|en|Construction|qid=Q3875186|lt=Construction|1=Construction}} of these six aspects is specially designed as the foundation for [[:en:Zhengde|Zhengde]], utilization, and good health.
== Rules and results of sports behavior ==
=== Lay the foundation for cultural revival from educational reform ===
To promote the general improvement of national knowledge level through {{ill|Education|en|Education|qid=Q8434|lt=Education|1=Education}} and increase national employment opportunities. We will help people adapt to their living environment and improve their lives.
In terms of education, it calls for attaching equal importance to moral, intellectual, physical and social education. Attaching importance to life education, revising textbooks on life education for [[Primary school|primary]] and [[:en:middleschool|middleschool]] students, focusing ethics in students' daily life. At the same time, we should increase the scientific and technological education of students, in addition to the implementation of tentative vocational cultivation in {{ill|Secondary education in Taiwan|en|Secondary education in Taiwan|qid=Q11421016|lt=national middleschools|1=Secondary education in Taiwan}}, and {{ill|High school in the United States|en|High school in the United States|qid=Q121116229|lt=in high schools|1=High school in the United States}}, we should focus on the development of {{ill|Vocational school|en|Vocational school|qid=Q322563|lt=Vocational school|1=Vocational school}}s, so as to meet the needs of national economic construction and production work. The Chinese Cultural Renaissance Association has also set up the Scientific and Technological Research and Invention Award to support scientific and technological inventions made by ordinary people.
In terms of sports, the committee focuses on the advocacy and implementation of sports for all, the cooperation and application of teams, the improvement of sports facilities in schools and society, the strengthening of training and activities of sports organizations and teams, and the frequent organization of international sports activities and contacts. And vigorously develop sports academic research, improve the people's sports skills.
=== From academic consolidation to cultural renewal ===
{{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Jiang Zhongzheng|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} called for "harmony between mind, matter, group and oneself, resulting in the {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=dd China|1=Taiwan}}'s Three Principles of ethics, democracy, scientific social blueprint, is to lead to cultural integration."
In the whole Chinese cultural Renaissance movement, the committee's goal is "to sort out the traditional culture and save the weeds. At the same time, the essence of Western culture is selected, absorbed and adopted, and the Chinese and Western cultures are integrated into one furnace, so as to create a new neutral culture that can benefit mankind. Under the supervision of Jiang, the Committee established a number of specialized organizations and committees, such as the Committee for the Promotion of Academic Publication, which was responsible for sorting out and publishing ancient books, popularizing academic essence to the younger generation, and publishing a large number of Chinese ancient books. For example, Zhouyijin Annotated the Present Translation, {{ill|en:Laozi|en|en:Laozi|qid=Q9333|lt=en:Laozi|1=Laozi}} Annotated the Present Translation, The Book of Songs Annotated the Present Translation, Menzi Annotated the Present Annotated the Present Translation, Baihua Historical Records, Vernacular Zizhi Tongjian&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news |date=2015-09-05 |title=大陆文革期间 蒋介石在台湾干些什么｜多维新闻｜中国 |work=多维新闻 |url=https://www.hk01.com/|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=蒋介石晚年曾坚决镇压台独分裂势力 |work=m.sohu.com |url=https://m.sohu.com/n/407456146/?page=16&amp;show_rest_pages=1&amp;image_mode=f&amp;_once_=000027_pages_leftallv2&amp;_smuid=wFUDZvYk6eLUY6EhkjBs5&amp;mv=2 |access-date=2021-10-26|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; collated a large number of ancient books to make the text plain and easy to understand, so that ordinary people could understand it. A large number of ancient Chinese classics have been photocopied and published, contributing to the preservation of the achievements of Chinese civilization.
To compile an overview of Chinese culture, publish 100 Chinese thinkers of all dynasties, introduce their lives, thoughts, activities and the influence of their works, so as to enable the Chinese people to have a deeper understanding of the evolution of Chinese academic thought. Compiled and printed stories of loyal and filial figures in the past dynasties of China (100) and selected writings of loyal and filial piety to carry forward the magnificent style of national cultural humanistic spirit. To re-translate the Four Books from English and distribute them overseas to enhance international scholars' understanding and appreciation of Chinese culture.&lt;ref&gt;陳鐵健、黃鐵炫著，《蔣介石與中國文化》，香港：中華書局，1992nd year 4月，第175頁&lt;/ref&gt;
Translated western classics, about {{ill|Politics|en|Politics|qid=Q7163|lt=Politics|1=Politics}}, {{ill|Economy|en|Economy|qid=Q159810|lt=Economy|1=Economy}}, {{ill|Society|en|Society|qid=Q8425|lt=Society|1=Society}}, {{ill|Science|en|Science|qid=Q336|lt=Science|1=Science}} and other aspects, has been published in a variety of. {{ill|Science and Civilisation in China|en|Science and Civilisation in China|qid=Q7433621|lt=Science and Civilization in China|1=Science and Civilisation in China}} by Needham, an Englishman.
The Chinese Science and Technology Series, the Bibliography of Zhou-Qin, Han and Wei Scholars, the Selected Essays on Chinese History, the History of Chinese Humanities and Social Sciences Series, The Legal System in Modern China, the Western Translation Bibliography of Chinese Literature, the Album of Modernization and Chinese Cultural Renaissance, the General Bibliography of Chinese Culture, the Collection of Essays on Chinese Cultural Renaissance, and the Research and Development of the standard Template book "and other books have been published.
Introduce new {{ill|Science and technology|en|Science and technology|qid=Q34104|lt=Science and technology|1=Science and technology}} and absorb new scientific knowledge to strengthen the [[Modernization theory|modernization]] of the country. Promote the exchange of Chinese and western culture, so as to receive the help of cultural integration. These academic collation work is a necessary way to promote {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}} and a necessary method to integrate Chinese and Western cultures.
=== From the study of literature and art to the development of cultural Renaissance emperor ===
From the national cultural humanism set off the thought of literature and art: the first is to promote the specific behavior of ethics and morality, in order to show the national spirit of loyalty, filial piety and kindness. The second is to advocate the democratic consciousness of anti-communism, anti-slavery and anti-persecution in order to stabilize the democratic thought and system. The third is to develop science and technology and promote scientific and technological progress in order to realize national modernization and modern civilization. The specific plan is as follows:
* A National Foundation for literature and Art was established.
* Formulate cultural policies.
* The Committee for the Promotion of {{ill|Chinese opera|en|Chinese opera|qid=Q737994|lt=Chinese Opera|1=Chinese opera}} is responsible for the improvement and promotion of Chinese opera, such as the regular performance of Chinese opera, the arrangement and creation of scripts, the training of scene personnel, the design of Chinese opera courses and the improvement of textbooks, and the holding of summer Chinese opera workshops for junior colleges and universities.
* The establishment of cultural centers from the central to the local level. In conjunction with the literary and art circles throughout the country, they hold symposiums on literature and art, hold various literary and art seasons, reward literary and art creation, set up literary and art research classes, and guide various literary and art activities. Such as painting and calligraphy exhibition, drama performance, dance performance, music performance, various literary and artistic creation competition, improve and carry forward the traditional arts.
* Handle international cultural and artistic exchanges and study international literary and artistic creation skills.
* To compile and print the history of Chinese literature and art to correct part of the destruction of traditional Chinese literature and art.
* To produce a large number of cultural and artistic programs in line with mass communication, and promote the colorful work of literature and art.
* Fine print Chinese contemporary famous painting and calligraphy album.
=== From national life coaching to cultural renewal ===
The committee put forward that culture is the representation of life, and the cultivation of ethics and the development of morality should start from the guidance of the people's life, so that the people understand the principle of living, acting and treating others. The true meaning of ethics should be embodied in the daily life of the people. The establishment of relevant norms and norms so that the interaction between people will have a certain standard scale and appropriate basis, so as not to deviate from the norm.
The Committee also promulgated and implemented the Guidelines for National Life, which set out 99 specific rules covering such areas as clothing, food, housing, travel and entertainment as guidelines for national life.&lt;ref&gt;陳鐵健、黃道炫著，《蔣介石與中國文化》，香港：中華書局，1992nd year 4月，第123頁&lt;/ref&gt; The National Life Counseling Committee is responsible for promoting ethics and morals, initiating the "Youth Practice Campaign to Revitalize Chinese Culture" and formulating the "Instructions for National Life", which sets out basic requirements for People's Daily life, with a view to promoting the civilization of a country of rites and ceremonies. The Model of National Etiquette was revised and formally issued in 1970, expanding the cultivation of young people as the ideal of social life.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
=== To achieve the goal of cultural innovation by integrating Chinese and Western cultures ===
To carry forward the cultural tradition of the Chinese nation and promote the continuous innovation and development of Chinese culture. The Committee formulated the "Implementation Plan for the Integration and Development of Chinese Culture and Modern Western Academic Thought" and the "Implementation Plan for the Compilation and Publication of Chinese Culture Series" to affirm the value of Chinese culture.
== Movement process ==
{{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Chiang Kai-shek|1=Chiang Kai-shek}}, the then {{ill|President of the Republic of China|en|President of the Republic of China|qid=Q887003|lt=President of the Republic of China|1=President of the Republic of China}} who launched the movement in November 1966—on the 100th anniversary of {{ill|Sun Yat-sen|en|Sun Yat-sen|qid=Q8573|lt=Sun Yat-sen|1=Sun Yat-sen}}'s birthday—by publicly announcing the official start of the renaissance movement.&lt;ref name="guy"&gt;Guy, Nancy. [2005] (2005). Peking Opera and Politics in Taiwan. University of Illinois Press. {{ISBN|0-252-02973-9|qq=}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the {{ill|Kuomintang|en|Kuomintang|qid=Q31113|lt=Kuomintang|1=Kuomintang}}'s first structured plan for cultural development on Taiwan. Chiang himself was the head of the movement promotion council.&lt;ref name="guy" /&gt; Future president {{ill|Lee Teng-hui|en|Lee Teng-hui|qid=Q315528|lt=Lee Teng-hui|1=Lee Teng-hui}} was also involved in the movement and served as the president for the cultural renaissance.&lt;ref name="Wachman" /&gt;
Chiang announced ten goals:&lt;ref name="guy" /&gt;
# To improve educational standards and promote family education with an emphasis on the {{ill|Confucius|en|Confucius|qid=Q4604|lt=Confucian|1=Confucius}} principles of filial duty and fraternal love.
# To reissue {{ill|Chinese literature|en|Chinese literature|qid=Q456012|lt=Chinese classic literary|1=Chinese literature}} works and translate important works with a view toward disseminating {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}} abroad.
# To encourage the creation of new literary and art works that are relevant to contemporary society and informed by the ideals of the cultural renaissance.
# To launch the government planning and construction of new theaters, {{ill|Chinese opera|en|Chinese opera|qid=Q737994|lt=opera|1=Chinese opera}} houses, auditoriums, and art galleries, as well as stadiums throughout the country, and to improve existing facilities.
# To utilize all mass media for the promotion of the cultural renaissance with an emphasis upon encouraging good customs and morals.
# To guide the modernization of national life under the influence of the Confucian Principles of the "Four Social Controls" (propriety, rectitude, honesty and a sense of shame)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| editor1-last  = De Bary
| editor1-first = William Theodore
| editor1-link   = Ted de Bary
| editor2-last  = Lufrano
| editor2-first = Richard John
| title         = Sources of Chinese Tradition: From 1600 Through the Twentieth Century
| url           = https://books.google.com/books?id=g0aAjW8GU7kC
| access-date    = 2011-11-05
| edition   = 2
| series    = Introduction to Asian civilizations
| volume    = 2
| year      = 2001 
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| isbn      = 978-0-231-11271-0
| page      = 342
| quote         = The meaning of Li, Yi, Lian, and Chi[.] [...] ''li'', ''yi'', ''lian'', and ''chi'' have always been regarded as the foundations of the nation [...] they may be interpreted as follows: ''Li'' means 'regulated attitude.' ''Yi'' means 'right conduct.' ''Lian'' means 'clear discrimination.' ''Chi'' means 'real self-consciousness.'
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and the "Eight Virtues" (Loyalty, filial piety, benevolence, love, faithfulness, justice, harmony and peace), a goal to be achieved with the help of the newly launched [[dd Life Movement]].
# To promote tourism and the preservation of historical relics.
# To increase support for overseas Chinese education, including the publication of newspapers and the promotion of cultural activities abroad.
# To maintain close ties with foreign institutions and intellectuals, particularly those whose research focuses on China.
# To revise tax statutes and regulations in order to encourage wealthy individuals, private industries, and private businesses to make donations to government-endorsed cultural and educational establishments.
[[File:Yangming Mountain National Park 03.jpg|thumb|200x200px|Yangming mountain]]
November 12, 1966, the centenary of Sun Yat-sen's birth. At the inauguration ceremony of the newly built [[:en:Zhongshan Building|Zhongshan Building]] Chinese Culture Hall on {{ill|Yangming Mountains|en|Yangming Mountains|qid=Q30326176|lt=Yangming Mountain|1=Yangming Mountains}} in {{ill|Taipei|en|Taipei|qid=Q1867|lt=Taipei|1=Taipei}}, Chiang Zhongzheng published the Commemorative Paper of the inauguration of the {{ill|Chung-Shan Building|en|Chung-Shan Building|qid=Q5116271|lt=Zhongshan Building|1=Chung-Shan Building}} Chinese Culture Hall, which continued to promote the cultural purpose of the integration of the Three People's Principles and Chinese tradition, and declared that "the thought of the Three People's Principles is not only the convergence of Chinese culture, but the national revolution of the Three People's Principles is the defender of Chinese national culture".&lt;ref&gt;陳鐵健、黃鐵炫著，《蔣介石與中國文化》，[[:zh:香港|香港]]：[[:zh:中華書局|中華書局]]，1992nd year 4月，第120頁&lt;/ref&gt; It says, "I firmly believe that ethics, democracy and science are the essence of the Three Principles of the People, which is also the cornerstone of the traditional culture of the Chinese nation." At that time, all the participants in the memorial meeting, then jointly signed a petition to the government to designate November 12 as the anniversary of the father's birthday, as well as the Chinese culture Renaissance Festival.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
On December 25, 1966, [[:en:Jiang Zhongzheng|Jiang Zhongzheng]] presided over the {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=Republic of China|1=Taiwan}} "[[National Assembly (Republic of China)|National Assembly Constitutional Studies]]" meeting. At the meeting, it was announced that it would launch a campaign to revive Chinese culture, implement the {{ill|Three Principles of the People|en|Three Principles of the People|qid=Q260998|lt=Three Principles of the People|1=Three Principles of the People}}, and awaken rational conscience by virtue of traditional humanistic spirit and ethical concepts. On December 26, the Fourth Plenary session of the ninth CPC Central Committee was held in {{ill|Taipei|en|Taipei|qid=Q1867|lt=Taipei|1=Taipei}}, {{ill|Taiwan Province|en|Taiwan Province|qid=Q32081|lt=Taiwan Province|1=Taiwan Province}}. The meeting adopted a plan for the Chinese Cultural Revival Movement.
[[File:ROC Legislative Yuan Seal.svg|thumb|200x200px|{{ill|Legislative Yuan|en|Legislative Yuan|qid=Q715869|lt=Legislative Yuan|1=Legislative Yuan}}]]
On February 14, 1967, {{ill|Premier of the Republic of China|en|Premier of the Republic of China|qid=Q702650|lt=Premier|1=Premier of the Republic of China}} {{ill|Yen Chia-kan|en|Yen Chia-kan|qid=Q335219|lt=Yim Ka-kam|1=Yen Chia-kan}} proposed to the {{ill|Legislative Yuan|en|Legislative Yuan|qid=Q715869|lt=Legislative Yuan|1=Legislative Yuan}} the policy of promoting the Cultural Revival Movement. On April 9, Chiang Zhongzheng sent a letter to the annual meeting of Confucius and Mencius Society, saying that carrying forward Confucius and Mencius theory will help implement the Three Principles of the People, reform people's life and realize cultural Renaissance. On July 28, a conference was held at Zhongshan Building, Yangming Mountain. The meeting adopted the program and constitution of the "Chinese Cultural Renaissance Movement" and elected the organization. The {{ill|Executive Yuan|en|Executive Yuan|qid=Q715055|lt=Executive Yuan|1=Executive Yuan}} of the Republic of China established the "China Renewal Movement Committee", with Chiang Zhongzheng as the chairman and {{ill|Sun Fo|en|Sun Fo|qid=Q701897|lt=Sun Ke|1=Sun Fo}}, {{ill|Wang Yun-wu|en|Wang Yun-wu|qid=Q759889|lt=Wang Yunwu|1=Wang Yun-wu}}, {{ill|Ch'ien Mu|en|Ch'ien Mu|qid=Q707313|lt=Qian Mu|1=Ch'ien Mu}}, {{ill|Paul Yu Pin|en|Paul Yu Pin|qid=Q700613|lt=Yu Bin|1=Paul Yu Pin}}, Zuo Shunsheng, {{ill|Lin Yutang|en|Lin Yutang|qid=Q334086|lt=Lin Yutang|1=Lin Yutang}}, Wang Shixian, {{ill|Chien Shih-Liang|en|Chien Shih-Liang|qid=Q697502|lt=Qian Siliang|1=Chien Shih-Liang}} and {{ill|Hsieh Tung-min|en|Hsieh Tung-min|qid=Q718107|lt=Xie Dongmin|1=Hsieh Tung-min}} as the presidium.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
On July 30, 1967, the Central Committee of the Kuomintang of China promulgated the Measures for Promoting the Chinese Cultural Revival Movement, proposing to strengthen academic research, promote social life, organize literary and artistic activities, cooperate in education, advocate mass communication, and strengthen women's work. Measures have also been promulgated to strengthen the education of the Three People's Principles, strengthen the will to fight, and carry forward traditional culture.
On August 24, 1967, {{ill|Sun Fo|en|Sun Fo|qid=Q701897|lt=Sun Ke|1=Sun Fo}}, {{ill|Wang Yun-wu|en|Wang Yun-wu|qid=Q759889|lt=Wang Yunwu|1=Wang Yun-wu}} and {{ill|Chen Lifu|en|Chen Lifu|qid=Q698368|lt=Chen Lifu|1=Chen Lifu}} became vice chairmen of the Committee for Promoting the Rejuvenation of Chinese Culture.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;陳鐵健、黃鐵炫著，《蔣介石與中國文化》，香港：中華書局，1992nd year 4月，第121頁&lt;/ref&gt; Gu Fengxiang was appointed Secretary-General.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
On August 28, 1967, {{ill|Ministry of Education (Taiwan)|en|Ministry of Education (Taiwan)|qid=Q697093|lt=the Ministry of Education of the Republic of China|1=Ministry of Education (Taiwan)}} issued a ten-point directive to promote nine-year [[:en:National education|National education]]:
* Promote the cultural Renaissance movement.
* National schools make long-term plans.
* The school arranges teaching hours according to the regulations of the Ministry of Education.
* Schools are not allowed to buy or sell unapproved tutoring materials.
* Teachers devote themselves to education, and shall not give paid tutoring.
* Make the students' homework guidance method, junior students homework no more than half an hour, senior students no more than one hour.
* Strengthen art education and cultivate practical working ability.
* Schools give play to teachers' expertise, the implementation of subject teaching.
* Various teaching seminars are established in the school.
* Combine national education with family education.
On November 21, 1967, the Fifth Plenary session of the Ninth CPC Central Committee of the Chinese Kuomintang adopted: carry forward the traditional Chinese culture, respect personality independence, respect democracy and freedom, implement land for the tiller, promote social welfare, safeguard the freedom of choosing a career, maintain family ethical relations, freedom of religious belief, equality of all nationalities, and maintain international peace.
On March 29, 1968, {{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Jiang Zhongzheng|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} issued a "Message to the Youth" on {{ill|Youth Day (China)|en|Youth Day (China)|qid=Q10881633|lt=Youth Day|1=Youth Day (China)}}, proposing to "serve the country with science and develop the essence of national culture. Ethics, democracy and science are linked together. If democracy does not flourish, science and ethics will not flourish. In national construction, the development of science is the first priority. We should be proud of being a Chinese, responsible for the nation and the human race."
April 30, 1968, the Committee for the Promotion of the Chinese Revival Movement issued the "Instructions for National Life". On October 15, the Committee for the Promotion of the China Renaissance Movement set several priorities for its work: promoting guidelines for people's life, strengthening physical education, formulating etiquette for people's life, carrying out education reform, setting up standard centers for literary and artistic activities, establishing large-scale national social education centers, sorting out Chinese operas and music, translating and interpreting ancient books as national readings, and translating and introducing world classics.
On November 12, 1968, {{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Jiang Zhongzheng|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} issued a Message to the Compatriots of the whole Country on [[:en:Sun Zhongshan|Sun Zhongshan]]'s birthday and the Festival of the Revival of Chinese Culture, proposing to "revive Chinese culture, create a new era of the Three People's Principles, carry forward the spirit of ethics, science and democracy, clarify ethics and righteousness, and know shame; To carry out the constitutionalism of the Three People's Principles, we should start from promoting the politics of integrity and energy. Together we can save our country, compatriots and culture."
On April 8, 1969, the tenth Plenary session of the Chinese Nationalist Party passed the "Program of Social Construction at the present stage" express "social construction objectives: carry forward scientific function, cultivate enterprise spirit. Use human resources to strengthen social welfare measures, establish social security, seek social development, balance social construction, balance wealth, and build a peaceful, happy and prosperous society. Foster law-abiding and orderly spirit among the people, promote local autonomy, and develop the national spirit. Inherit excellent cultural traditions, clear rites and righteousness, emphasize honesty and know shame".
On December 25, 1969, {{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Jiang Zhongzheng|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} wrote to [[National Assembly (Republic of China)|the delegates of the National Congress]] on the anniversary of the Constitution: "Strive to promote democratic constitutionalism, expounding the concept of combining science and ethics, cultivating moral and spiritual strength, and promoting the sound development of mankind. Master the spirit of benevolence of Chinese culture, eliminate the poison of materialism in the world ".
On July 29, 1970, the Ministry of Education of the Republic of China issued the "Patriotic and Founding of the country Education Program" proposed to strengthen teacher education, carry forward national cultural traditions, promote national self-esteem, encourage teachers to further study, develop vocational and technical education, improve junior college education, encourage scholars to return to Taiwan to teach.
[[File:Chiang Kai-shek（蔣中正）.jpg|thumb|265x265px|Jiang Zhongzheng]]
On July 26, 1971, {{ill|Chiang Kai-shek|en|Chiang Kai-shek|qid=Q16574|lt=Jiang Zhongzheng|1=Chiang Kai-shek}} put forward at the fourth meeting of the Committee for the implementation of the Chinese Cultural Renaissance Movement: "Keeping to the classics and abiding by them, innovating and adapting to new conditions, reviewing the past and learning the new, if one wishes to make new changes day by day, difficulties will revitalize the country, and sorrow will revitalize the saints." Further promote the development of the movement.
"From the overall perspective, from the practical focus, develop team spirit, establish a love for the people, convenient atmosphere; All governance to carry forward the national interests, to develop the national spirit, under the banner of the Three People's Principles of unity at home and abroad," was the proposal {{ill|Chiang Ching-kuo|en|Chiang Ching-kuo|qid=Q313598|lt=Jiang Jingguo|1=Chiang Ching-kuo}}  made in a June 13, 1972, policy address in the {{ill|Legislative Yuan|en|Legislative Yuan|qid=Q715869|lt=Legislative Yuan|1=Legislative Yuan}}.
The Republic of China's Society of Confucius and Mencius convened on April 22, 1973. Jiang Zhongzheng made the suggestion that "Chinese people should be clear in etiquette and law-abiding, practice benevolence and justice, and take Confucius and Mencius as the source of the Three Principles of the People" .
On December 17, Jiang Zhongzheng told the compatriots of the Republic of China to expand the movement of good people and good deeds, saying that the development of humanity is the best weapon, and the Republic of China is engaged in spiritual, cultural and ideological warfare with humanism to attack people's hearts and spirits.
On March 28, 1975, Jiang Jingguo published an article "Dedicating oneself to the country and dedicating one's heart to the people" to commemorate the Youth Day. To carry forward national morality, culture, tradition and intelligence, the destiny of China should be controlled by the young people.
On September 16, 1976, Jiang Jingguo delivered a policy address at the Legislative Yuan, stressing that "the way of education lies in consolidating the foundation of the country, the foundation of administration lies in serving the people, and working together to create a pure and simple society".
In response to the Chinese cultural Renaissance movement, the Yan Clan Association in Taiwan began to build the {{ill|Yan Hui|en|Yan Hui|qid=Q1155960|lt=Yan Zi Temple|1=Yan Hui}} in {{ill|Songshan District, Taipei|en|Songshan District, Taipei|qid=Q271124|lt=Songshan District|1=Songshan District, Taipei}}, {{ill|Taipei|en|Taipei|qid=Q1867|lt=Taipei City|1=Taipei}} in the late 1970s. The Zheng clan Association established the Kaitai Shengwang Chenggong Temple in Neihu District;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=1978-10-08 |title=宗親活動 |work=《聯合報》|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Meng Clan Association also planned to build a Mencius Temple near the Golden Dragon Temple in the Neihu District.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=1978-05-06 |title=亞聖孟子明誕辰紀念 各界籌備在內湖興建孟廟 |work=《民生報》|qq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Evaluate ==
{{citation needed section|date=May 2023|qq=}}
* [[File:Chen Li-fu (陳立夫).jpg|thumb|Chen Lifu]]{{ill|Chen Lifu|en|Chen Lifu|qid=Q698368|lt=Chen Lifu|1=Chen Lifu}}: It has been 13 years since the Chinese Cultural Renaissance Movement was launched. What are the achievements? Society has its fair judgment; But here it is necessary to say:
** First, the cultural revival has guided the correct line. {{ill|Ethics|en|Ethics|qid=Q9465|lt=Ethics|1=Ethics}}, {{ill|Democracy|en|Democracy|qid=Q7174|lt=Democracy|1=Democracy}} and {{ill|Science|en|Science|qid=Q336|lt=Science|1=Science}} are the cornerstone of {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}} and the essence of {{ill|Three Principles of the People|en|Three Principles of the People|qid=Q260998|lt=the Three People's Principles|1=Three Principles of the People}}. To revive {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}}, we must practice the Three Principles of the People.
** Second, the cultural Renaissance has promoted the flourishing of culture. In the past, international people called Taiwan a cultural desert. Now, Taiwan has a variety of cultural relics activities, books and periodicals printing, lectures, symposiums, viewing parties, exhibitions... Held almost every day, visible at any time, resulting in a general state of the ZTE scene.
** Third, cultural revival has elevated our country's cultural reputation and status. Internationally, Taiwan is regarded as the richest place to preserve the fine traditional culture of China, which has increased the admiration and reverence of international scholars for Taiwan, and even the love for Taiwan, which has increased the number of tourists to Taiwan and changed the perception of international scholars on {{ill|Taiwan|en|Taiwan|qid=Q865|lt=Taiwan|1=Taiwan}}.
* {{ill|Mou Zongsan|en|Mou Zongsan|qid=Q6918843|lt=Mou Zongsan|1=Mou Zongsan}}: "National cultural and spiritual education", like other aspects of education, is "material" and "teaching". There is no "spirit" at all. Naturally, it cannot be called "education".&lt;ref&gt;牟宗三講演，〈中國文化大動脈中的終極關心問題〉，《中國文化的省察》，台北，[[:zh:聯經出版|聯經出版]]，1983rd year ，第126頁，[[:zh:Special:网络书源/9570812001|ISBN 957-08-1200-1]]&lt;/ref&gt;
== External links ==
* [http://ap6.pccu.edu.tw/encyclopedia/data.asp?id=230&amp;forepage=1 Chinese Cultural Revival Movement] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110519141617/http://ap6.pccu.edu.tw/encyclopedia/data.asp?id=230&amp;forepage=1 |date=2011-05-19 |qq=}} (&lt;{{ill|Chinese Encyclopedia|en|Chinese Encyclopedia|qid=Q5100444|lt=Chinese Encyclopedia|1=Chinese Encyclopedia}}&gt;)
* [https://www.gacc.org.tw/TW/ Chinese Cultural Federation] (&lt;[[:zh:中華文化總會|General Association of Chinese Cultural Revival Movement]]&gt;)
== See also ==
{{Portal|China|Taiwan|qq=}}
* {{ill|History of the Kuomintang cultural policy|en|History of the Kuomintang cultural policy|qid=Q5869885|lt=History of the Kuomintang cultural policy|1=History of the Kuomintang cultural policy}}
* [[May Fourth Movement]]
* {{ill|Zoulu (culture)|en|Zoulu (culture)|qid=Q15954891|lt=Zoulu (culture)|1=Zoulu (culture)}}
* {{ill|Chiangism|en|Chiangism|qid=Q112205736|lt=Chiangism|1=Chiangism}}
* [[:zh:振兴中华|Revitalize China]] → The {{ill|Chinese Dream|en|Chinese Dream|qid=Q10874521|lt=Chinese dream|1=Chinese Dream}} of [[:zh:中华民族伟大复兴|the great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation]]
* {{ill|Chinese culture|en|Chinese culture|qid=Q645917|lt=Chinese culture|1=Chinese culture}}
* [[:zh:中華民國文化|Culture of the Republic of China]]
* [[dd Life Movement]]
=== The opposite cultural movement in {{ill|Greater China|en|Greater China|qid=Q1143195|lt=China|1=Greater China}} ===
* Before 1949: [[dd Culture Movement]], [[:zh:全盤西化|complete Westernization]]
* After 1949:
* {{ill|Mainland China|en|Mainland China|qid=Q19188|lt=Chinese mainland|1=Mainland China}}: {{ill|Cultural Revolution|en|Cultural Revolution|qid=Q8690|lt=Cultural Revolution|1=Cultural Revolution}}, Breaking the {{ill|Four Olds|en|Four Olds|qid=Q1713721|lt=Four Olds|1=Four Olds}}, {{ill|Criticize Lin, Criticize Confucius|en|Criticize Lin, Criticize Confucius|qid=Q14129|lt=Criticize Lin, Criticize Confucius|1=Criticize Lin, Criticize Confucius}}
* {{ill|Geography of Taiwan|en|Geography of Taiwan|qid=Q22528|lt=Taiwan|1=Geography of Taiwan}}: {{ill|De-Sinicization|en|De-Sinicization|qid=Q5264465|lt=De-Sinicization|1=De-Sinicization}}, [[:zh:台灣本土化運動|Taiwan Localization Movement]]
==References==
{{reflist|qq=}}
]]]]


[[en:Chinese Cultural Renaissance]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[de:Chinesische Kulturrenaissance]]
[[id:Renaisans Kebudayaan Tionghoa]]
[[ko:중화문화부흥운동]]
[[vi:Phong trào Phục hưng Văn hóa Trung Hoa]]
[[zh:中華文化復興運動]]

&lt;!--dewiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
&lt;!--zhwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;

{{wikidata link|Q1073969}}</text>
      <sha1>k3m3aauymoqw35rqu5qn1clr6uclces</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
