<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cofun Gal no Coffy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17734</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3593245</id>
      <parentid>3568588</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T18:41:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3593245</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="27354" sha1="9v29up9pob9ywkmghdhmvfnlu1gp7mz" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:古墳GALのコフィー]]
'''{{ill|Cofun Gal no Coffy|ja|古墳ギャルのコフィー|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Cofun Gal no Coffy|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 古墳GALのコフィー}}''' (こふんギャルのコフィー) is a Flash anime produced by {{ill|Froggyman Shokai|ja|蛙男商会|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Froggyman Shokai|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to ディー・エル・イー}}, created using {{ill|Macromedia Flash|ja|Macromedia Flash|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Macromedia Flash|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to Adobe Flash}}.
The first episode was released on kaeruotoko.com in May 2005, and a total of 10 episodes were made available online. The protagonist, {{ill|Coffy|en|Coffy|qid=Q2702180|lt=Coffy|1=Coffy}}, originally appeared as a character in a column published on kaeruotoko.com before Froggyman Shokai began producing Flash animations.
Since then the series has been expanded into multiple series.
== Overview ==
Like other works by {{ill|Froggyman Shokai|ja|蛙男商会|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Froggyman Shokai|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to ディー・エル・イー}}, the early episodes were entirely handled by {{ill|FROGMAN|ja|FROGMAN|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/FROGMAN|qq=}} in terms of script, direction, and animation (later works feature collaborators on writing and animation).
Although nearly all the voice acting was performed by FROGMAN himself, almost all female characters—except for Dorothy—were voiced by professional female voice actors.
In the first season’s third episode, the voice of the Honey Tama Shop manager was provided by [[Furuyama Yōhei|フルヤマヨウヘイ]], and in the sixth episode the voice of the teacher {{ill|Ono no Komachi|en|Ono no Komachi|qid=Q198984|lt=Ono Komachi|1=Ono no Komachi}} was done by [[:en:Aizawa Mai|相沢舞]].
== Series History ==
For detailed broadcast and screening information on each series, please refer to the “[[#関連項目]]” link at the end of this section.
=== Web Version ===
In 2005, episodes were distributed on a commercial website at a rate of one episode every two weeks, with a total of 10 episodes produced.
=== TV Series – Season 1 ===
From April to June 2006, episodes were broadcast under the omnibus TV anime program block of {{ill|TV Asahi|en|TV Asahi|qid=Q908436|lt=TV Asahi|1=TV Asahi}}’s [[THE FROGMAN SHOW]], under the title '''{{ill|Coffy: Kofun Gal|ja|古墳ギャルのCoffy|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Coffy: Kofun Gal|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 古墳GALのコフィー}}''' (in a dual-bill with {{ill|Eagle Talon (TV series)|en|Eagle Talon (TV series)|qid=Q1458106|lt=Secret Society Taka no Tsume|1=Eagle Talon (TV series)}}). Essentially based on the episodes originally released online, slight modifications were made for the TV adaptation.
=== TV Series – Season 2 ===
Starting in October 2009, the second season titled '''{{ill|Kofun Gal no Coffy: Campus Life|ja|古墳ギャルのコフィー　キャンパスライフ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Kofun Gal no Coffy: Campus Life|qq=}}''' began airing as part of the TV anime program block of {{ill|TV Asahi|en|TV Asahi|qid=Q908436|lt=TV Asahi|1=TV Asahi}}’s {{ill|Secret Society Taka no Tsume Countdown|ja|秘密結社鷹の爪 カウントダウン|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Secret Society Taka no Tsume Countdown|qq=}}. Due to various circumstances&lt;ref&gt;According to the Season 2 intro released online and in the opening of the first broadcast, Coffy's voice actor was changed because the original actor simply "got tired of acting." Other reasons provided on kaeruotoko.com and the official website include humorous explanations such as “it was too troublesome to have Coffy’s voice come in separately from Shimane” or “I felt sorry to have to voice on TV when it wasn’t even my main job.”&lt;/ref&gt;, the voice of Coffy was changed from {{ill|Honma Kyōko|ja|ホンマキョウコ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Honma Kyōko|qq=}} to professional voice actress [[:en:Aizawa Mai|相沢舞]].
=== Theatrical Anime Versions ===
In March 2007, a theatrical version titled '''{{ill|Coffy: The Battle of Okehazama|ja|古墳ギャルのCoffy 〜桶狭間の戦い〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Coffy: The Battle of Okehazama|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}''' was released (simultaneously with {{ill|THE FROGMAN SHOW: Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE – The Dictator Dies Twice|ja|秘密結社 鷹の爪 THE MOVIE〜総統は二度死ぬ〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/THE FROGMAN SHOW: Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE – The Dictator Dies Twice|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}). For details, see the [[THE FROGMAN SHOW#劇場版]] section.
In May 2008, the second theatrical film, '''{{ill|Coffy: 12 People and the Furious Kofun|ja|古墳ギャルのCoffy〜12人と怒れる古墳たち〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Coffy: 12 People and the Furious Kofun|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 古墳GALのコフィー}}''' was released (simultaneously with {{ill|THE FROGMAN SHOW: Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE2 – The Black Oolong Tea That Loved Me|ja|秘密結社 鷹の爪 THE MOVIE2〜私を愛した黒烏龍茶〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/THE FROGMAN SHOW: Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE2 – The Black Oolong Tea That Loved Me|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}).
In January 2010, the third theatrical film, '''{{ill|Coffy: Coffinderella|ja|古墳ギャルのCoffy〜コフンデレラ〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Coffy: Coffinderella|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}''' was released (simultaneously with {{ill|Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE3 – [URL omitted] The Empire Never Dies|ja|秘密結社 鷹の爪 THE MOVIE3〜http:// 鷹の爪.jpは永遠に〜|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE3 – [URL omitted] The Empire Never Dies|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}).
== Synopsis ==
A surreal comedy featuring Coffy, a girl depicted as a {{ill|keyhole-shaped kofun|ja|前方後円墳ギャル|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/keyhole-shaped kofun|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}} who attends a school or university where various kofun (ancient Kofuns) and mound tombs are congregated, along with the kofun themselves.
== Characters ==
=== Main Characters ===
===Kabe Island Coffy’s Family ===
; '''Coffy'''
: '''Voice:''' {{ill|Honma Kyōko|ja|ホンマキョウコ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Honma Kyōko|qq=}} (Season 1), {{ill|Mai Aizawa|en|Mai Aizawa|qid=Q2630749|lt=Aizawa Mai|1=Mai Aizawa}} (Season 2)
: The protagonist. A {{ill|keyhole-shaped kofun gal|ja|前方後円墳ギャル|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/keyhole-shaped kofun gal|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, in Season 1 she is a 17-year-old student in class 2-2 at Tokyo Metropolitan Kofun High School; in Season 2 (Campus Life), she is a 20-year-old student at National Kofun University. Her name is derived from the film {{ill|Coffy|ja|Coffy|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Coffy|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}. Her parents run a used car dealership.
: When she collapses, the "person inside" is revealed. The iron sword among her funerary goods is designated as an Important Cultural Property. Her body is covered with trees; normally she appears green, but when the trees planted on her change to autumn colors, her body turns brown.
: She harbors feelings for {{ill|Nintoku|ja|仁徳|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nintoku|qq=}}, which causes jealousy in her rival Dorothy, another kofun gal (depicted as a keyhole-shaped kofun). Initially, although she occasionally utters extreme vulgarities, she was an ordinary girl, but as the series progresses her abusive language toward Daniel increases dramatically—she even frames Daniel for a crime leading to his execution. Consequently, she has earned a reputation among the kofun for being especially brutal toward Daniel. Generally speaking, Daniel is considered inferior to 鹿肉 (deer meat). From Season 2 onward, when angry, she brandishes an {{ill|iron club|ja|アイアンクラブ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/iron club|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, swinging it wildly to destroy everything around her.
; '''Papa'''
: Coffy’s father, who runs the used car dealership.
: A stubborn and strict man who is actually a tender-hearted worrywart. In an unaired episode, he mistakenly replaced the tree on his body with a pine, causing it not to display autumn colors, and ended up sulking and lashing out at Daniel. He also once caused a fire while camping.
: He was once an {{ill|F1 (disambiguation)|en|F1 (disambiguation)|qid=Q225109|lt=F1 pilot|1=F1 (disambiguation)}}, known as "the Speed of Sound Kofun," and was even a Driver's Champion in '88. He met Coffy’s mother at an event in {{ill|Indianapolis|en|Indianapolis|qid=Q6346|lt=Indianapolis|1=Indianapolis}} that same year. He still maintains ties with his F1 colleagues.
; '''Mama'''
: Coffy’s mother, renowned for her gentle nature—she is never seen angry.
: Formerly a pit crew member for {{ill|McLaren Honda|ja|マクラーレンホンダ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/McLaren Honda|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, she traveled the world and is still capable of a 10-second flat tire change.
: Unlike others, her body appears pink because the trees on her are cherry trees, which remain in full bloom all year round.
: It is said that she once prepared ramen broth from her "inside person," creating a nostalgic flavor.
; '''Ueda'''
: Coffy’s pet, a horse-shaped {{ill|Haniwa|en|Haniwa|qid=Q849376|lt=haniwa|1=Haniwa}}.
: Short-tempered; when angry, it swings a bamboo sword with its front legs, often kicking Daniel high into the air. It was once the head thug at Kofun High School. When it assumes its role as head thug, its face transforms dramatically like a {{ill|Daimajin|en|Daimajin|qid=Q1165332|lt=Great Demon God|1=Daimajin}}.
: In Season 2, it only appears in the first episode, and Coffy seems to lose interest in it thereafter. The character is apparently based on {{ill|Ueda Banosuke|ja|上田馬之助|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Ueda Banosuke|qq=}}.
==== Kofun High School and Kofun University Affiliates ====
; '''Daniel'''
: Coffy’s childhood friend, depicted as a {{nihongo|{{ill|zenpō-kōhō-fun|lt=zenpō-kōhō-fun|ja|前方後方墳|lt=Zenpō-kōhō-fun|1=Zenpō-kōhō-fun|comment=doing this because I need to differentiate it in piped links too with my new interwiki tool as not the ambiguous phrase keyhole shaped kofun|1=Zenpō-kōhō-fun|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/zenpō-kōhō-fun|13=User:Immanuelle/Zenpō-kōhō-fun|comment=enwiki is a redirect}}|前方後方墳|lt=Zenpō-kōhō-fun|1=Zenpō-kōhō-fun|comment=doing this because I need to differentiate it in piped links too with my new interwiki tool as not the ambiguous phrase keyhole shaped kofun|qq=}}; during Kofun High School he was her classmate. In Season 2, he becomes a rōnin after failing university entrance exams, working as a cashier at the co-op of Kofun University operated by Okihazama. His name is derived from Daniel in {{ill|The Best Kid|ja|ベストキッド|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/The Best Kid|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to ベスト・キッド}}.
: He is ridiculed by other kofun (especially the girls) for being a mound tomb, but only Coffy maintains a relationship with him. He shows some affection for Coffy. Known for his impersonation of [[Shijimaru]], he is also an excellent goalkeeper.
: He is arguably the unluckiest character in the series—constantly suffering mishaps such as being sacrificed for plot resolutions, having his "inside person" overtaken by designated National Natural Monuments, invasive species, or even being nearly turned into residential property. Nevertheless, he possesses an incredibly robust body that never dies.
: He is self-conscious about not only being a kofun but also a mound tomb and about his timid nature; once, based on a theory that "if the person inside changes, one's personality changes," his "inside person" was replaced with that of {{ill|Soga no Iruka|en|Soga no Iruka|qid=Q736621|lt=Soga Iruka|1=Soga no Iruka}}, turning him into a delinquent.
: His family is very poor, yet he is said to be robbed ({{ill|katsuage|ja|カツアゲ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/katsuage|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 恐喝罪}}) four times a day. He is also frequently kicked into the stratosphere by Coffy’s pet Ueda.
: His birthday (or the anniversary of the death of his "inside person") is April 19. Daniel humorously describes it as “the 4 (something), the most, and 9 times suffering on April 19.”
; '''Nintoku (Charles)'''
: The object of Coffy’s affection, depicted as a {{ill|Zenpokoenfun|en|Zenpokoenfun|qid=Q11268718|lt=Zenpokoenfun|1=Zenpōkōenfun}}, who was her classmate at Kofun High School and becomes her boyfriend in Season 2. He is tall, handsome, and from an exceptional family; he is also the heir to the kofun throne. His name is derived from the {{ill|Nintoku-tennō Tomb|ja|仁徳天皇陵|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Nintoku-tennō Tomb|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to 大仙陵古墳}}.
: He is admired by not only Coffy but by all the female kofun. As the series progresses, the distance between him and Coffy gradually decreases. He occasionally speaks condescendingly. In addition to his influence among the kofun, he appears to wield considerable power among humans.
: In Season 2, he enters the Medical School at Kofun University, studying civil engineering.
: In the fifth episode of Season 2, his name is changed to {{ill|Charles III|ja|チャールズ3世|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Charles III|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to チャールズ3世 (イギリス王)}}, and this new name is emphasized in that episode; however, by the seventh episode (with the sixth episode not yet aired) he reverts to being called Nintoku, prompting Coffy to remark, "Ah, Char— no, Nintoku-kun, not this week." The change is explained as due to "too many complications in this anime, so please don’t worry about it." (As stated in a line by Coffy in episode 8.) Note that in the third theatrical film his character is consistently called Charles.
; '''Okihazama-sensei (Okehazama Shop Manager)'''
: The homeroom teacher of Coffy’s class at Kofun High School; a recurring character from another Froggyman Shokai work, [[Okehazama-sensei from Class 3B]].
: He resembles a warrior from the Sengoku period, complete with arrows embedded in his body, and speaks in a deep, gruff voice. When excited, he performs a dance reminiscent of the choreography from [[:en:Kudo Shizuka|Kudo Shizuka]]’s "Face of the Storm." He is frequently mistaken for being associated with ancient battlefields such as the Battle of {{ill|Okehazama|ja|桶狭間|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Okehazama|qq=}}, and he repeatedly corrects others by exclaiming "It’s Okehazama!" When Coffy first enrolled, he appeared as a typical warrior, but after the theatrical film episode "The Battle of Okehazama," he transformed into a warrior with a battered appearance.
: In Season 2, shortly after Coffy and her friends graduate, he suddenly loses his sanity, can no longer stop dancing the "Face of the Storm" routine, quits teaching, and becomes the shop manager at the Kofun University co-op run by Okihazama. At that time he introduces himself as "Store Manager Okehazama!"
: In Froggyman Shokai’s publications, it is revealed that he is a close friend of Dr. Leonardo from [[Secret Society Taka no Tsume]] (details remain unclear).
; '''Dorothy'''
: A rival kofun gal (depicted as a {{ill|Zenpokoenfun|en|Zenpokoenfun|qid=Q11268718|lt=Zenpokoenfun|1=Zenpōkōenfun}}) and Coffy’s classmate at Kofun High School.
: Like Coffy, she is attracted to Nintoku, and frequently insults Coffy. She has a harsh personality and tone, and is constantly seen bullying Daniel. She once underwent cosmetic surgery to round her face, but defective work left her disfigured.
: In Season 2, she becomes a student at Kofun Junior College but rarely attends classes, instead roaming the downtown area. Additionally, while she had no hair in Season 1, in Season 2 her hair appears permed.
==== Subcharacters ====
; '''Yamamoto Saburō'''
: A minor character who appears during the investigation into a series of thefts at Kofun High School; he is also implicated in a case involving continuous robberies of cash transport vehicles.
: When he appeared on the TV show {{ill|Shinkon-san Irasshai!|ja|新婚さんいらっしゃいませ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Shinkon-san Irasshai!|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, he humorously stated his occupation as "charging mobile phone batteries at an indoor dog training center."
: In the end, Coffy arrests him, and the theft case is blamed solely on Daniel’s poverty.
: His character is based on [[Yamamoto Jōji|山本譲二]].
; '''Hongijirō Motomiya'''
: The head bully (banchō) at Coffy’s school.
: He has a look reminiscent of characters drawn by the hard-boiled manga artist [[Hiroshi Homami|本宮ひろ志]].
: He is infatuated with Coffy and once confessed, only to be rejected with “I don’t like rough people!”
; '''Kuf'''
: The head bully of Pyramid High School, nicknamed “Pyramid.”
: He attacks Kofun High School in revenge for his subordinates being beaten by Hongijirō, but is counterattacked by Ueda (the head thug of Kofun High School’s underworld), along with his pet carnivorous {{ill|Sphinx|en|Sphinx|qid=Q151480|lt=Sphinx|1=Sphinx}}.
: His character is based on the Great Pyramid of Giza as built during the reign of {{ill|Khufu|ja|クフ王|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Khufu|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to クフ}}.
; '''Elvis Tomb-kun'''
: A foreign exchange student from the United States who comes to Kofun High School.
: His "tomb" is that of {{ill|Elvis Presley|ja|エルビス・プレスリー|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Elvis Presley|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to エルヴィス・プレスリー}}.
: In his early days, he naively believed in a distorted version of Japanese culture, insisting that ninjas and samurai still exist.
: In emotional scenes, he became known in Japan by the catchphrase “Chinpiyorospoon,” after being deceived by Coffy.
; '''Tenuki Reporter'''
: A news anchor character drawn in a purposely slovenly style; he also appears in works such as [[Secret Society Taka no Tsume]].
; '''King of Kofun'''
: A character who appears only in the final episode of both the web version and Season 1.
: He is Nintoku’s father and is depicted as hating commoners.
: Despite being a kofun himself, he is linked with {{ill|Abukuma Buvamon|ja|阿武隈ブヴァエモン|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Abukuma Buvamon|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, and is portrayed as a cold, ruthless king.
: He is smaller in stature than Nintoku.
; '''Kozoshi'''
: A kofun character who came to Tokyo from the countryside.
: Fired from his company and abandoned by his girlfriend, he once attempted suicide by jumping off a building until Coffy intervened.
: Also, as a reconstructed kofun (lacking an "inside person"), he harbors a complex about his nonexistence, claiming, “My true self is actually 50 m away from where I currently am.”
: He later helps with a nearby kofun’s childbirth, which restores his will to live.
: His character is based on the Kofun Hill Park in Matsue, {{ill|Shimane Prefecture|en|Shimane Prefecture|qid=Q132751|lt=Shimane Prefecture|1=Shimane Prefecture}}.
; '''Peter Carnegie and Peter’s Papa'''
: They appear only in episodes 4, 7, and 10 of Season 1.
: Minor characters seen casually playing catch at the beginning.
: In episode 7, they appear as guests at a deer meat party.
: Later, a spin-off series titled [[Denno Senshi Dodokan-kun]] was produced featuring them as main characters.
; '''(Repeated Subcharacters)'''
: [Note: The following subcharacter entries appear multiple times due to source duplication and have been consolidated.]
==== (Appearing in both the Web Version and Seasons 1 &amp; 2) ====
; '''Abukuma Buvamon'''
: The president of {{ill|Abukuma Construction|ja|阿武隈建設|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Abukuma Construction|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid}}, who runs a store in a multi-tenant building behind the station. In cahoots with the infamous Abukuma Buvamon, he illegally attempts to erect a condominium without proper archaeological surveys or permits, but is thwarted by Nintoku.
: He reappears in the first episode of Season 2 as a swindler running a fraudulent business, and in the second theatrical film he appears as "Kaminarioyaji" (Thunder Uncle), whose bonsai, sprouting mandrake, is smashed by Coffy.
==== (Appearing only in Theatrical Versions) ====
; '''Pascal'''
: A character who appears in every theatrical film, taking on different roles in each.
: Originally from another FROGMAN work, [[Denno Senshi Dodokan-kun]], his character is recycled across films.
: In the first film, he appears as a retainer of {{ill|Imagawa Yoshimoto|en|Imagawa Yoshimoto|qid=Q1054305|lt=Imagawa Yoshimoto|1=Imagawa Yoshimoto}}; in the second film, as Daniel’s lawyer; and in the third film, as Coffy’s stepmother.
=== Other Characters ===
==== The Little People ====
; '''Little Person'''
: A human-like figure about 30 cm tall, dressed in attire reminiscent of the {{ill|Kofun period|en|Kofun period|qid=Q459939|lt=Kofun period|1=Kofun period}} with a hairstyle featuring braided hair (角髪). Unlike normal-sized humans, they never speak.
: These represent the "inside person" (中の人) or the deceased individuals originally buried in kofun.
; '''Inside Person'''
: In every kofun (except in reconstructions), a tiny human corpse—the "inside person"—is always present. In genuine kofun, these are the individuals interred. Typically, only those from aristocratic or royal lineages become an inside person, and while some are "under cultivation," they are treated roughly (e.g. used as bait) compared to those carefully preserved.
: They are considered equivalent to a brain or heart for the kofun. Consequently, if the inside person is replaced with another, the personality may change or even swap with that of the replacement.
: It is said that when a female kofun’s inside person weeps while smiling, good fortune ensues. Normally, their faces are turned upward with a contorted expression of agony.
: In the case of the pyramids in Pyramid High School, "inside mummies" are present. For kofun and pyramids, the inside person or mummy is something they are embarrassed to have seen by others.
; '''Kofun Builder'''
: The person who originally built the kofun; a type of little person.
: They are essentially the "parents" of all kofun. In recent times, since kofun are no longer being built in the Kofun period, issues of "shōkofun-ka" (the decline in new kofun construction) have emerged. Consequently, the aging of kofun builders and a decline in younger builders have been noted.
: They are often hot-tempered and prideful craftsmen, quick to quarrel with one another or complain to site supervisors, making mental management among them particularly challenging.
: New kofun are sometimes constructed when a female kofun goes into labor, which simultaneously indicates that a little person from an aristocratic or royal lineage is either near death or has already died.
== Episode Titles ==
=== Web Version ===
(The episode numbers are preceded by a #.)
# “An Unbelievable Tale”
# “The Ambition of Daniel”
# “The Frontline of Adolescence”
# “Daniel’s Crisis”
# “Kofun Gal White Paper”
# “The Great Love Gift Operation”
# “The Arrival of the Kofun Banchō!”
# “The Man Who Came from America”
# “Kofun Detective”
# “Goodbye, Kofun Gal”
※ Note: The web version is no longer available.
=== Season 1 Series ===
# “Daniel’s Ordeal”
# “The Men from America”
# “Kofun Gal White Paper”
# “Kofun Family”
# “Kofun Brawl”
# “Okehazama-sensei’s Love”
# “George”
# “Beautiful Kofun”
# “Life”
# “The Christmas Operation” (Unaired on TV)
# “2015”
# “Farewell, Kofun Gal”
※ In episode #3, the on-screen title is identical to that in #4 (“Kofun Family”), but according to Froggyman’s internet radio, this was simply a mistake.
=== Season 2 Series ===
# “GOTO HELL, You!”
# “Yōrō no Taki Takeshi-sensei” 
# “Shōkofun-ka” 
# “Azuchi no Joe”
# “Sawakura”
# “Purple Haze”
# “Invasive Species Crisis”
# “All Days”
# “Keyhole”
# “Transfer Student”
# “Sky High”
※ Episode #11 was originally produced for a movie but was moved to the series final episode due to excessive length.
== Supplementary Information ==
FROGMAN initially intended to voice Coffy himself, but after numerous unsuccessful attempts, he enlisted the help of {{ill|Honma Kyōko|ja|ホンマキョウコ|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Honma Kyōko|qq=}} (the original voice of Coffy). (Works in which he eventually managed to voice the character himself include the OVA version of “Secret Society Taka no Tsume THE MOVIE4: The Man with Kaspersky”.)
As a promotional work for [[THE FROGMAN SHOW]], a spin-off featuring Daniel as the protagonist, titled “Mound Tomb Salaryman Daniel,” was released on kaeruotoko.com (it is no longer available).
=== Episode Titles (Web Version) ===
* Part 1: “A Tale That Will Make You Doubt Your Ears”
* Part 2: “Advertising Conference”
* Part 3: “Catchphrase”
* Part 4: “Commercial Production Meeting”
* Part 5: “TAF Great Operation”
* Part 6: “Mobile Operation”
== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist|qq=}}
== Related Articles ==
* [[THE FROGMAN SHOW]] – For information on the broadcast and theatrical release details of the TV anime Season 1.
* [[Secret Society Taka no Tsume Countdown]] – For information on the broadcast details of TV anime Season 2.
* [[D.L.E]]
* [[Kerotan]] – Special guest appearance as a poster in the first theatrical film.
* [[Gāko]] – Same as above.
* {{ill|Suntory|en|Suntory|qid=Q1345267|lt=Suntory|1=Suntory}} – Collaborative project at the Bingo★Bongo Theater.
* {{ill|Triangular Rim Divine Beast Mirror|ja|三角縁神獣鏡|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Triangular Rim Divine Beast Mirror|qq=}} – Set as a present from Coffy to her mother.
== External Links ==
* [http://www.kaeruotoko.com/works_coffy.html?snd=1] – Official character introduction page by {{ill|Froggyman Shokai|ja|蛙男商会|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Froggyman Shokai|ja_comment=jawiki redirects to ディー・エル・イー}}
{{anime-stub|qq=}}
{{anime-stub|qq=}}

{{translated page|ja|古墳GALのコフィー|version=103835974|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:古墳GALのコフィー]]
[[ja:古墳ギャルのコフィー]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q11411017}}
[[Category:2005 anime ONAs]]
[[Category:Anime series|Kofun Gal no Coffy]]
[[Category:Anime starting with Ko]]
[[Category:Anime starting with Ko|ふんきやるのこふいい]]
[[Category:Kaeruotoko Shōkai]]
[[Category:Original Web Anime of Japan]]
[[Category:Surreal comedy anime]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]
[[Category:Anime starting with Ko]]
[[Category:Surreal comedy anime]]
[[Category:日本のオリジナルWebアニメ]]
[[Category:蛙男商会]]</text>
      <sha1>9v29up9pob9ywkmghdhmvfnlu1gp7mz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
