<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Honji suijaku</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3594683</id>
      <parentid>3570796</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:01:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3594683</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="19045" sha1="5nocyq4ywtggss6cnea8orh81e50w51" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[en:Honji suijaku]][[fi:Honji suijaku]][[fr:Honji suijaku]][[id:Honji suijaku]][[it:Honji suijaku]][[ja:本地垂迹]][[ko:본지수적]][[pt:Honji suijaku]][[zh:本地垂迹说]]


{{Short description|Japanese Buddhist theory incorporating kami into the Buddhist pantheon}}
{{Italic title|reason=

&lt;}}
The term {{nihongo|'''''honji suijaku''''' or ''honchi suijaku''|本地垂迹}} in Japanese religious terminology refers to a theory widely accepted until the {{ill|Meiji era|en|Meiji era|qid=Q3125096|lt=Meiji era|1=Meiji era}} according to which Indian Buddhist deities choose to appear in Japan as native ''[[kami]]'' to more easily convert and save the Japanese.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="BT95"&gt;Breen and Teeuwen (2000:95)&lt;/ref&gt; The theory states that some ''kami'' (but not all) are local manifestations (the {{nihongo|''suijaku''|垂迹}}, literally, a "trace") of Buddhist deities (the {{nihongo|''honji''|本地}}, literally, "original ground").&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="masato"&gt;Satō Masato (2007)&lt;/ref&gt; The two entities form an indivisible whole called ''[[gongen]]'' and in theory should have equal standing, but this was not always the case.&lt;ref name="BTOS"/&gt; In the early {{ill|Nara period|en|Nara period|qid=Q189178|lt=Nara period|1=Nara period}}, for example, the ''honji'' was considered more important and only later did the two come to be regarded as equals.&lt;ref name="BTOS"&gt;Basic Terms of Shinto&lt;/ref&gt; During the late {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}} it was proposed that the ''kami'' were the original deities and the buddhas their manifestations (see the ''Inverted honji suijaku'' section below).&lt;ref name="BTOS"/&gt;

The theory was never systematized but was nonetheless very pervasive and very influential.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; It is considered the keystone of the [[shinbutsu-shūgō]] (syncretism of Buddhist deities and Japanese ''kami'') edifice.&lt;ref name="Sato"&gt;Satō Makoto&lt;/ref&gt; ''Honji suijaku'' has often been seen as similar to ''[[:en:interpretatio Romana|interpretatio Romana]]'', 
a mode of comparison promoted in antiquity by scholars such as {{ill|Tacitus|en|Tacitus|qid=Q2161|lt=Tacitus|1=Tacitus}} who argued that {{ill|Barbarian|en|Barbarian|qid=Q134313|lt=Barbarian|1=Barbarian}} gods were just the foreign manifestations of Roman or Greek deities.&lt;ref&gt;Josephson, Jason Ānanda, ''The Invention of Religion in Japan'' (University of Chicago Press, 2012), 25-26&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''honji suijaku'' itself is an example of the Japanese practice of ''{{ill|Yojijukugo|en|Yojijukugo|qid=Q7010524|lt=Yojijukugo|1=Yojijukugo}}'', a four-character combination of phrases which can be read literally or idiomatically.

==History==
[[File:kasugamandala detail.jpg|thumb|A mandala showing Buddhist deities and their ''kami'' counterparts]]
Early Buddhist monks did not doubt the existence of ''kami'' but saw them as inferior to their {{ill|Buddhahood|en|Buddhahood|qid=Q56247062|lt=buddhas|1=Buddhahood}}.&lt;ref name="sheid"&gt;Bernhard Scheid&lt;/ref&gt; Hindu deities had had the same reception: They were thought of as non-illuminated and prisoners of {{ill|Saṃsāra|en|Saṃsāra|qid=Q173324|lt=Saṃsāra|1=Saṃsāra}}.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Buddhist claims of superiority, however, encountered resistance; monks tried to overcome it by deliberately integrating ''kami'' in their system.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Japanese Buddhists themselves wanted to somehow give the ''kami'' equal status.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Several strategies to do this were developed and employed, and one of them was the ''honji suijaku'' theory.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

The expression was originally developed in China&lt;ref&gt;Sueki (2007:24)&lt;/ref&gt; and used by {{ill|Tendai|en|Tendai|qid=Q855964|lt=Tendai|1=Tendai}} Buddhists to distinguish an absolute truth from its historical manifestation (for example, the eternal {{ill|The Buddha|en|The Buddha|qid=Q9441|lt=The Buddha|1=The Buddha}} from the historical Buddha, or the absolute {{ill|Dharma|en|Dharma|qid=Q134293|lt=Dharma|1=Dharma}} from its historical forms, the first being the ''honji'', the second the ''suijaku'').&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="masato"/&gt; The term makes its first appearance with this meaning in the ''Eizan Daishiden'', a text believed to have been written in 825.&lt;ref name="masato"/&gt; The ''honji suijaku'' theory proper later applied it to buddhas and ''kami'', with its first use within this context dated to 901, when the author of the ''Sandai Jitsuroku'' says that "mahasattvas (buddhas and {{ill|Bodhisattva|en|Bodhisattva|qid=Q178149|lt=Bodhisattva|1=Bodhisattva}}) manifest themselves at times as kings and at times as ''kami''."&lt;ref name="masato"/&gt; The dichotomy was applied to deities only in Japan and not, for example, in China.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

A different but equivalent explanation, the idea that Buddhist deities choose not to show themselves as they are, but manifest themselves as ''kami'', was expressed in a poetic form with the expression {{nihongo|''wakō dōjin''|和光同塵}}, which meant that to assist sentient beings, deities "dimmed their radiance and became identical to the dust of the profane world."&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Their brightness would otherwise be such to destroy mere mortals.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

In the 10th and 11th centuries there are numerous examples of Buddhist deities and ''kami'' pairings: The deities are usually [[Kannon]], [[:en:Yakushi|Yakushi]], [[Amitābha|Amida]] or [[Shakyamuni Tathāgata|Shaka Nyorai]].&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The association between them was usually made after a dream or revelation made to a famous monk, later recorded in a temple's or shrine's records.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; By then, ''kami'' in Japan were universally understood to be the form taken by buddhas to save human beings, that is, local manifestations of universal buddhas.&lt;ref name="teram"&gt;Teeuwen, Rambelli (2002:6)&lt;/ref&gt; Around the beginning of the {{ill|Kamakura period|en|Kamakura period|qid=Q236205|lt=Kamakura period|1=Kamakura period}} the pairings had become solidly codified in large temples or shrines.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The frequency of the practice is attested by the {{nihongo|''kakebotoke''|懸仏}}, or "hanging buddhas," found in many large shrines—metal mirrors that carry on the front the effigy of the shrine's ''kami'' and on the rear the relative Buddhist deity.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The name shows that they are usually hung from a shrine's outer wall.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

As the theory gradually spread around the country, the concept of ''[[gongen]]'' ("provisional manifestation", defined as a Buddha that chooses to appear to the Japanese as a ''kami''&lt;ref name="masato"/&gt;) evolved.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; One of the first examples of ''gongen'' is Hie's famous {{nihongo|''Sannō Gongen''|山王権現}}.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Under the influence of {{ill|Tendai|en|Tendai|qid=Q855964|lt=Tendai Buddhism|1=Tendai}} and [[Shugendō]], the ''gongen'' concept was adapted, for example, to religious beliefs tied to {{ill|Mount Iwaki|en|Mount Iwaki|qid=Q713857|lt=Mount Iwaki|1=Mount Iwaki}}, a volcano, so that female ''kami'' Kuniyasutamahime became associated with Jūichimen [[:en:Kannon Bosatsu|Kannon Bosatsu]] (eleven-faced Kannon), ''kami'' [[Ōkuninushi]] with [[:en:Yakushi Nyorai|Yakushi Nyorai]], and [[:en:Kunitokotachi|Kunitokotachi]] no Mikoto with [[:en:Amida Nyorai|Amida Nyorai]].&lt;ref&gt;Breen, Teeuwen (2000:194)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Practice==
The ''honji suijaku'' paradigm remained a defining feature of Japanese religious life up to the end of the {{ill|Edo period|en|Edo period|qid=Q184963|lt=Edo period|1=Edo period}}. Its use was not confined to deities but was often extended even to such historical figures as {{ill|Kūkai|en|Kūkai|qid=Q222227|lt=Kūkai|1=Kūkai}} and {{ill|Prince Shōtoku|en|Prince Shōtoku|qid=Q263972|lt=Prince Shōtoku|1=Prince Shōtoku}}.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; It was claimed that these particular human beings were manifestations of ''kami'', which in turn were manifestations of buddhas.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; Sometimes the deity involved was not Buddhist.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; This could happen because the theory was never formalized and always consisted of separate events usually based on a temple or shrine's particular beliefs.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

Nothing was fixed: A deity could be identified both as a ''honji'' and a ''suijaku'' in different parts of the same shrine, and different identifications could be believed to be true at the same time and place.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The religious situation during the Middle Ages was, therefore, confused and confusing. Historians have tried to concentrate on the reformers of that age with a clear philosophy and little interest in ''kami'' questions because they are easier to understand.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The theory was ultimately beneficial to the ''kami'', which went from being considered unilluminated outsiders to actual forms assumed by important deities.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt; The ultimate expression of this shift is {{ill|Shinto sects and schools|en|Shinto sects and schools|qid=Q3952369|lt=Ryōbu Shintō|1=Shinto sects and schools}}, in which Buddhist deities and ''kami'' are indivisible and equivalent like the two sides of a coin.&lt;ref name="sheid"/&gt;

The use of the ''honji suijaku'' paradigm was not limited to religion—it had important consequences for society in general, culture, art and even economy.&lt;ref name="teram1"&gt;Teeuwen, Rambelli (2002:1-2)&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism, for example, proscribed fishing, hunting, and agriculture because they involved the killing of living beings (insects, moles and the like in the case of farming), but the ''honji suijaku'' concept permitted people to void the prohibition.&lt;ref name="BT88"/&gt; If one fished for oneself, the reasoning went,  you were guilty and should go to hell. However, if the catch was offered to a ''kami'' that was a known emanation of a buddha, the gesture had an obvious karmic value and was permissible.&lt;ref name="BT88"&gt;Breen and Teeuwen (2000:88-89)&lt;/ref&gt; The idea allowed the forbidding of individual, and therefore uncontrolled, economic activity.&lt;ref name="BT88"/&gt; Applied as it was to all major economic activities, this interpretation of ''honji suijaku'' allowed a thorough control of popular dissent.&lt;ref name="BT88"/&gt;

How important the concept was can be understood from how the idea that some local phenomenon may be somehow linked to an absolute and sacred object found extensive application in the medieval and early modern periods.&lt;ref name="teram1"/&gt; It was often said that temple lands in Japan were local emanations of Buddhist paradises or that an artisan's work was one with the sacred actions of an Indian Buddha.&lt;ref name="teram1"/&gt;

==Art==
[[File:Sōgyō Hachiman.jpg|thumb|200 px|''Kami'' Hachiman in Buddhist attire]]
The ''honji suijaku'' paradigm found wide application in religious art with the {{nihongo|''Honji Suijaku Mandara''|本地垂迹曼荼羅}} or {{nihongo|''Songyō Mandara''|尊形曼荼羅}}.&lt;ref name="JAANUS2"&gt;Songyō Mandara&lt;/ref&gt; The {{nihongo|''Honjaku Mandara''| 本迹曼荼羅}} (see image above) shows Buddhist deities with their ''kami'' counterparts, while the {{nihongo|''Honjibutsu Mandara''|本地仏曼荼羅}} show only Buddhist deities, and the {{nihongo|''Suijaku Mandara''|垂迹曼荼羅}} show only ''kami''.&lt;ref name="JAANUS2"/&gt;

The {{nihongo|Sōgyō Hachiman|僧形八幡}}, or "Hachiman in priestly attire", is one of the most popular syncretic deities.&lt;ref name="JAANUS"&gt;Sōgyō Hachiman&lt;/ref&gt; The ''kami'' is shown dressed as a Buddhist priest and is considered the protector of people in general and warriors in particular.&lt;ref name="JAANUS"/&gt; From the 8th century on, Hachiman was called ''Hachiman Daibosatsu'', or Great {{ill|Bodhisattva|en|Bodhisattva|qid=Q178149|lt=Bodhisattva|1=Bodhisattva}} Hachiman.&lt;ref name="JAANUS"/&gt; That he is dressed like a Buddhist priest is probably meant to indicate the sincerity of his conversion to Buddhism.&lt;ref name="JAANUS"/&gt; By the 13th century, other ''kami'' would also be portrayed in Buddhist robes.&lt;ref name="JAANUS"/&gt;

===Shintōshū===
{{main|Shintōshū}}
The Shintōshū is a  book in ten volumes believed to date from the {{ill|Nanboku-chō period|en|Nanboku-chō period|qid=Q264012|lt=Nanboku-chō period|1=Nanboku-chō period}} (1336–1392).&lt;ref name=kojien&gt;Iwanami {{nihongo|{{ill|Kōjien|en|Kōjien|qid=Q1192611|lt=Kōjien|1=Kōjien}}|広辞苑}} Japanese dictionary, 6th edition (2008), DVD version&lt;/ref&gt; It illustrates with tales about shrines the ''honji suijaku'' theory. The common point of the tales is that, before reincarnating as tutelary ''kami'' of an area, a soul has first to be born and suffer there as a human being.&lt;ref name=yahoo&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Murakami|first=Manabu|title=Shintōshū|url=http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E7%A5%9E%E9%81%93%E9%9B%86/|encyclopedia=Shogakukan Encyclopedia|publisher=Yahoo Japan|accessdate=15 June 2011|language=Japanese|archive-url=https://archive.today/20121209055811/http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E7%A5%9E%E9%81%93%E9%9B%86/|archive-date=9 December 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The suffering is mostly caused by relationships with relatives, especially wives or husbands.
The book had great influence over literature and the arts.&lt;ref name="kojien"/&gt;

==Inversion==
The dominant interpretation of the buddha-''kami'' relationship came to be questioned by what modern scholars call the {{nihongo|''inverted honji suijaku''|反本地垂迹|han honji suijaku}} or {{nihongo|''shinpon butsujaku''|神本仏迹}} paradigm, a theology that reversed the original theory and gave the most importance to the ''kami''.&lt;ref name="teram35"&gt;Teeuwen, Rambelli (2002: 35-36)&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters of the theory believed that, while those who have achieved buddhahood have acquired {{ill|Enlightenment in Buddhism|en|Enlightenment in Buddhism|qid=Q1137019|lt=enlightenment|1=Enlightenment in Buddhism}}, a ''kami'' shines of his own light.&lt;ref name="teram35"/&gt; The doctrine was first developed by Tendai monks, and its first full formulation is attributed to [[Jihen]], a monk tied to the great [[Ise Grand Shrine|Ise]] shrine who was most active around 1340.&lt;ref name="teram35"/&gt; In the first fascicle of the ''Kuji hongi gengi'' he argued that, in the beginning, Japan had only ''kami'' and that only later did buddhas take over.&lt;ref name="shirayama"/&gt; He believed that for this reason there had been a decadence in the country's morals and that a world where ''kami'' dominated would soon reappear.&lt;ref name="shirayama"&gt;Shirayama Yoshitarō&lt;/ref&gt; In the fifth fascicle of the same work, he compared Japan to a seed, China to a branch and India to a flower or fruit.&lt;ref name="shirayama"/&gt; Just like flowers that fall and return to the roots, India had come back to its roots, the ''kami'' were the ''honji'' and the buddhas their manifestations.&lt;ref name="shirayama"/&gt;

[[Yoshida Kanetomo]] was influenced by these ideas and brought them further, making a clean break with the past, becoming the creator of {{ill|Yoshida Shintō|en|Yoshida Shintō|qid=Q1760351|lt=Yoshida Shintō|1=Yoshida Shintō}} and bringing inverted ''honji suijaku'' to maturation.&lt;ref name="shirayama"/&gt;

While it is usually claimed that inverted ''honji suijaku'' was a reaction of native cults to the dominance of Buddhism, it also came out of Buddhist intellectualism.&lt;ref name="teram35"/&gt; The theory is not ''per se'' anti-Buddhist and does not question the existence of buddhas but simply seeks to invert the established order of importance between ''kami'' and buddhas.&lt;ref name="BT119"&gt;Breen and Teeuwen (2000:119)&lt;/ref&gt; Why Buddhists should develop such a theory to the detriment of their own divinities is unclear, but it is possible that it was developed by shrine monks, or ''[[shasō]]'', who took care of the shrine part of temple-shrine complexes to enhance their status.&lt;ref name="teram35"/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{cite web
  |url=http://www.univie.ac.at/rel_jap/gesch/honjisuijaku.htm
  |title=Honji suijaku: Die Angleichung von Buddhas und Kami
  |last=Scheid, Bernhard
  |author-link=Bernhard Scheid
  |date=2008-04-16
  |language=German
  |accessdate=2008-11-04
}}
*{{cite web
  |url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=1355
  |title=Han-Honji Suijaku Setsu (Anti-Honjisuijaku thought)
  |last=Shirayama
  |first=Yoshitarō
  |year=2007
  |publisher=Encyclopedia of Shinto
  |language=
  |accessdate=2008-11-02
}}
*{{cite web
  |url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=1356
  |title=Honji Suijaku Setsu
  |last=Satō
  |first=Masato
  |year=2007
  |publisher=Encyclopedia of Shinto
  |language=
  |accessdate=2008-11-02
}}
*{{cite web
  |url=http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/s/sougyouhachiman.htm
  |title=Sougyou Hachiman
  |publisher=JAANUS
  |accessdate=2008-11-07
}}
*{{cite web
  |url=http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/s/songyoumandara.htm
  |title=Songyou Mandara
  |publisher=JAANUS
  |accessdate=2008-11-07
}}
*{{cite book
  |last=Sueki, Fumihiko
  |author-link=Fumihiko Sueki
  |title=Chūsei no kami to hotoke
  |publisher=Yamakawa Shuppansha
  |location=Tokyo
  |year=2007
  |isbn=978-4-634-54320-1
  |language=Japanese
}}
* {{cite book
  |isbn=978-0-415-29747-9
  |editor=Teeuwen, Mark
  |editor-link=Mark Teeuwen
  |editor2=Fabio Rambelli
  |editor2-link=Fabio Rambelli
  |date=Dec 27, 2002
  |publisher=RoutledgeCurzon
  |location=London
  |title=Buddhas and Kami in Japan: Honji Suijaku as a Combinatory Paradigm}}
* {{cite web
  |url=http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=826
  |title=Shinto and Buddhism —Development of Shinbutsu Shūgō (Combinatory Religion of Kami and Buddhas)
  |publisher=Encyclopedia of Shinto
  |last=Satō  
  |first=Makoto
  |year=2006
  |language=
  |accessdate=2008-11-02
}}
* {{cite book
  |editor=Breen, John
  |editor-link=John Breen (scholar)
  |editor2=Mark Teeuwen
  | title = Shinto in History: Ways of the Kami 
  | publisher = University of Hawaii Press
  | date = July 2000
  | location = Honolulu
  | language =
  | isbn = 978-0-8248-2363-4
 }}
*Encyclopedia of Shinto, ''Basic Terms of Shinto'', [http://www2.kokugakuin.ac.jp/ijcc/wp/bts/bts_h.html#honji-suijaku_setsu Honji Suijaku Setsu], accessed on November 2, 2008
*[http://www.lares.dti.ne.jp/~hisadome/honji/index.html 本地垂迹資料便覧]



[[en:Honji suijaku]]
&lt;!--enwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
[[fi:Honji suijaku]]
[[fr:Honji suijaku]]
[[id:Honji suijaku]]
[[it:Honji suijaku]]
[[ja:本地垂迹]]
[[ko:본지수적]]
[[pt:Honji suijaku]]
[[zh:本地垂迹说]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
&lt;!--zhwiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q3080781}}
[[Category:Buddhism in the Heian period]]
[[Category:Buddhism in the Kamakura period]]
[[Category:Gongen]]
[[Category:Japanese historical terms]]
[[Category:Japanese words and phrases]]
[[Category:Shinbutsu shūgō]]
[[Category:Shinto terminology]]
[[Category:Wikidata has short description]]</text>
      <sha1>5nocyq4ywtggss6cnea8orh81e50w51</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
