<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hot spring algae</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3594721</id>
      <parentid>3570811</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-04T19:01:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "WD=" to "qid="</comment>
      <origin>3594721</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8764" sha1="8x6byzw1v2o4wsairoset6baclydvfi" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--interwikis from wikidata--&gt;[[ja:温泉藻]]


'''Onsensō''' (温泉藻, {{ill|hot spring algae|de|Heißquellenalgen|ja|温泉藻|zh|温泉藻|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/hot spring algae|qq=}}) are algae that inhabit areas near hot spring vents, flow channels, and bathing pools. They are extremophilic microorganisms adapted to environments of 50–80 °C, where typical organisms cannot thrive.

==Characteristics==
[[File:Norris_Geyser_Basin_03.jpg|thumb|right|Thermal algae proliferating at a hot spring vent in Yellowstone National Park.]]
Onsensō are primarily unicellular organisms. They consist mainly of cyanobacteria (prokaryotes), red algae, and diatoms (eukaryotes), forming unique hot spring ecosystems along with archaea&lt;ref&gt;Inoue p. 89–90&lt;/ref&gt;. Some species form filamentous colonies visible to the naked eye, but none produce large seaweed-like bodies. Planktonic species live as phytoplankton in water flows, while species exposed to water vapor colonize as epibionts. Major cyanobacteria and red algae contain chlorophyll a and phycocyanin, appearing blue-green; therefore, areas of dense growth often display turquoise hues.

Like thermophiles, onsensō possess heat-stable proteins. Acidophilic species also tolerate metal ions such as aluminum dissolved in the springs. Notably, thermophilic cyanobacteria produce little scytonemin, a UV-protective pigment&lt;ref name="GWp121"&gt;Graham and Wilcox p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;, likely because high-temperature, humid conditions allow rapid DNA repair&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | editor=Stal LJ, Caumette P | title=Structure, Development and Environmental Significance of Microbial Mats | edition=G35 | year=1994 | publisher=NATO Advanced Research Workshop | pages=377–392}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Constituent organisms==
===Cyanobacteria===
[[File:Lyngbya.jpg|thumb|right|A Lyngbya species in Baja California, Mexico.]]
[[File:Oscillatoria sp.jpg|thumb|right|An Oscillatoria species.]]
Cyanobacteria are common hot spring algae found worldwide, including Yellowstone National Park. Many genera thrive above 45 °C and are defined as thermophilic&lt;ref name="GWp120"&gt;Graham and Wilcox p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;. Major genera include&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Jackson JE, Castenholz RW | title=Fidelity of thermophilic blue-green algae to hot spring habitats | journal=Limnology and Oceanography | year=1975 | volume=20 | issue=3 | pages=305–322}} [PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;:

;{{ill|Mastigocladus laminosus|de|Mastigocladus laminosus|ja|イデユアイミドリ|zh|伊甸藻|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Mastigocladus laminosus|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid|qid=Q135579096|1=Mastigocladus laminosus}}
:Formerly classified as Fischerella; found in almost all springs below 58 °C worldwide due to thick-walled akinete spores that enable wind dispersal. Underwater, cells form spherical to subspherical chains, creating biofilms with sulfur bacteria. Also inhabits warm volcanic soils.
;{{ill|Lyngbya|en|Lyngbya|qid=Q310362|lt=Lyngbya|1=Lyngbya}}
:Occurs in fresh and marine waters; some species inhabit hot springs and adjacent soils.
;{{ill|Microcystis|en|Microcystis|qid=Q309928|lt=Microcystis|1=Microcystis}}
:Planktonic cyanobacteria that bloom in freshwater, controlling buoyancy with gas vesicles. Hot spring species include M. protea and M. thermalis.
;{{ill|Oscillatoria|en|Oscillatoria|qid=Q141259|lt=Oscillatoria|1=Oscillatoria}}
:Forms filamentous colonies similar to Mastigocladus; hot spring species include O. geminata, O. jovis, O. lemmermannii, O. subbrevis, O. tenuis.
;{{ill|Phormidium|en|Phormidium|qid=Q2793866|lt=Phormidium|1=Phormidium}}
:Similar to Oscillatoria but produces an agarose sheath; includes P. fragile, P. subuliforme, P. tenue. P. fragile also inhabits thermally influenced soils.
;{{ill|Synechococcus|en|Synechococcus|qid=Q150962|lt=Synechococcus|1=Synechococcus}}
:Varied morphology; hot spring species include S. caldasius, S. eximius, S. lividus, S. minervae, S. praelongus, S. salina, S. sublividus, S. vulcanus. S. lividus tolerates 70 °C but not below 54 °C&lt;ref name="GWp121"/&gt;.
;{{ill|Thermosynechococcus|de|Thermosynechococcus|ja|サーモシネココッカス属|zh|热雪球藻属|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Thermosynechococcus|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid|qid=Q135579100|1=Thermosynechococcus}}
:Includes T. elongatus; cells ~5 × 1 µm with optimal growth at 57 °C. The BP-1 strain from Beppu Onsen, Ōita, has a completed genome project&lt;ref&gt;[CyanoBase]&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Red algae===
[[File:Cyanidium O5A.jpg|thumb|right|Cyanidium under differential interference contrast microscopy.]]
Eukaryotic hot spring algae are single-celled red algae of the class Cyanidiophyceae. They lack phycoerythrin and appear blue-green like cyanobacteria. Preferring low-pH, sulfuric acid springs, they occur worldwide. Three genera in the order Cyanidiales include:

;{{ill|Cyanidium caldarium|de|Cyanidium caldarium|ja|イデユコゴメ|zh|卡尼斯藻|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Cyanidium caldarium|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid|qid=Q135579102|1=Cyanidium caldarium}}
:Only species in the genus; cells spherical, 1–20 µm in diameter with a robust cell wall and silicate deposits, enhancing heat and acid tolerance. Named after the caldarium (hot room) of ancient Roman baths. In Japan, abundant on rock surfaces at Kusatsu Onsen. Grows in water and in vapor-exposed rock surfaces&lt;ref name="Ciniglia2004"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Yoon2006"/&gt;.
;{{ill|Galdieria sulphuraria|en|Galdieria sulphuraria|qid=Q21271606|lt=Galdieria sulphuraria|1=Galdieria sulphuraria}}
:Several species with varied chloroplast arrangement. G. sulphuraria inhabits vapor-exposed rocks; its genome is sequenced&lt;ref name="Yoon2006"/&gt;. G. partita and G. daedala from Russian springs are closely related; G. maxima is phylogenetically distinct&lt;ref name="Kondo2006"/&gt;.
;{{ill|Cyanidioschyzon|en|Cyanidioschyzon|qid=Q16034656|lt=Cyanidioschyzon merolae|1=Cyanidioschyzon}}
:Monotypic genus discovered in Naples, Italy; optimal growth at pH 2.0 and 42 °C. Very small (1–2 µm) lacks a cell wall and inhabits aquatic or moist sites. A model organism with a completed genome; transfer of genes to Arabidopsis enhances heat tolerance.

===Diatoms===
Diatom diversity in hot springs is under-studied, but many Japanese endemics likely exist&lt;ref&gt;[National Museum PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;. Common genera include:

;{{ill|Pinnularia acidojaponica|de|Pinnularia acidojaponica|ja|ハネケイソウ属|zh|羽裂藻属|12=simple|13=User:Immanuelle/Pinnularia acidojaponica|ja_comment=jawiki link invalid|qid=Q135579104|1=Pinnularia acidojaponica}}
:Identified in 2001; inhabits acid hot springs.

==Habitat==
[[File:WhirligigGeyser-Peaco2001.jpg|thumb|right|Isothermal zone distribution at Norris Geyser Basin, Yellowstone National Park.]]
Different species inhabit zones from high-temperature vents to cooler peripheries, forming bands along isotherms&lt;ref name="GWp120"/&gt;. Some red algae colonize endolithic niches within rocks. Onsensō also flourish in man-made hot spring baths.

==Interaction with humans==
No toxic hot spring algae are reported&lt;ref&gt;[Toho University Q&amp;A]&lt;/ref&gt;. However, biofilms formed by thermophiles can harbor pathogens like Legionella, posing public health risks; removal or control via chlorine or copper ion treatments is recommended&lt;ref&gt;[Ministry Guidelines]&lt;/ref&gt;. Cyanidioschyzon, Galdieria, and other algae serve as model organisms due to heat-stable proteins and ease of culture. Their genes are applied in plants for enhanced thermal and heavy metal tolerance.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Nagashima H. “Microorganisms in Hot Springs.” [PDF]–NPO Health &amp; Hot Springs Forum.
* Graham LE, Wilcox LW, eds. Algae. Prentice Hall, 2000. ISBN 0-13-660333-5.
* Chihara M., Biodiversity Series Vol. 3: Diversity and Phylogeny of Algae. Shokabo, 1999. ISBN 978-4785358266.
* Inoue I. Algal Natural History: 3 Billion Years of Evolution. Tokai Univ. Press, 2006. ISBN 978-4486016441.

==See also==
* {{ill|Snow algae|en|Snow algae|qid=Q111700916|lt=Snow algae|1=Snow algae}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mnc.toho-u.ac.jp/v-lab/onsen/index.htm Onsen Microbial Virtual Laboratory] – Tōhō University MediaNet Center.
* [https://www.kahaku.go.jp/special/past/bisyoso/ipix/mo/1/1_6.html The World of Microalgae at Hot Springs] – National Museum of Nature and Science.

{{温泉}}
{{Good article}}

{{Onsen}}

{{translated page|ja|温泉藻|version=101159372|comment=Imported full ja history}}



[[ja:温泉藻]]
[[de:Heißquellenalgen]]
&lt;!--jawiki derived wikidata interwikis--&gt;
{{wikidata link|Q11562968}}
[[Category:Cyanobacteria]]
[[Category:Extremophiles]]
[[Category:Hot_springs_of_Japan]]
[[Category:Onsens]]
[[Category:Red algae]]
[[Category:Wikidata no short description]]</text>
      <sha1>8x6byzw1v2o4wsairoset6baclydvfi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
