<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hyakushu (Honda Chikaatsu)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56417</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3611009</id>
      <parentid>3606655</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-22T08:26:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove 12 stale untranslated-japanese char-count category tag(s) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24756154998|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3611009</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="55493" sha1="k0x4tqh7gz6ier7viplxej72f0embgq" xml:space="preserve">The '''''Hyakushu'' (百首)''' ("Hundred Poems") series by Honda Chikaatsu

==Ubusuna Hyakushu (産土百首)==
This is a complete translation of the "Ubusuna Hyakushu" (産土百首), or "One Hundred Poems on the Guardian Deity of the Birthplace," composed by Taira no Asomi Chikayoshi in 1885.

===上巻 (Jōkan) - Volume One===

:'''産土百首(上巻) (Ubusuna Hyakushu (Jōkan))'''
:'''One Hundred Poems on the Guardian Deity of the Birthplace (Volume One)'''

:1.  '''産土尔生連出都々産土尔帰留此身止不知也母人'''
::''Ubusuna ni are-idetsutsu, ubusuna ni kaeru kono mi to shirazu ya mo hito''
::To be born from the Ubusuna, and to the Ubusuna this body returns—do the people not know this?

:2.  '''往還留足踏毎尔産土之神乃恵乎思閉世乃人'''
::''Yukikaeru ashifumi goto ni ubusuna no kami no megumi o omoe yo no hito''
::With every step you take, coming and going, think of the blessings of the Ubusuna god, O people of this world.

:3.  '''草母樹母吾産土乃御体乃御毛津物曾止人者不知也母'''
::''Kusa mo ki mo waga ubusuna no mi-karada no mi-ketsu-mono zo to hito wa shirazu ya mo''
::That the grasses and the trees are the very hair of our Ubusuna god's sacred body—do people not know this?

:4.  '''産土乃霊乃懸留此身乎之仏乃子曾止言者誰子曾'''
::''Ubusuna no tama no kakareru kono mi o shi hotoke no ko zo to iu wa ta ga ko zo''
::This body, which is a vessel for the spirit of the Ubusuna, if you say it is a child of Buddha, then whose child is it truly?

:5.  '''産土乎神止母不知祭良受弖棄置村者獣成加母'''
::''Ubusuna o kami to mo shirazu, matsuraide suteoku mura wa kemono naru kamo''
::A village that does not know its Ubusuna as a god and neglects to worship it will surely become one of beasts.

:6.  '''産土乃神乃霊乃無理世婆人乃産業如何加母世牟'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no tama no muri seba hito no nariwai ikaga ka mo semu''
::If the spirit of the Ubusuna god were to act unreasonably, what would become of the livelihoods of men?

:7.  '''産土乃神乃形乎人皆乃同形止人勿思比曾'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no katachi o hito-mina no onaji katachi to hito na omoi so''
::People, do not think that the form of the Ubusuna god is the same form as all of you.

:8.  '''産土乃御体踏弖世乎渡留人乎之見連婆貴木呂加毛'''
::''Ubusuna no mi-karada fumite yo o wataru hito o shi mireba tōtokiro kamo''
::How noble they seem, the people who walk through the world treading upon the sacred body of the Ubusuna.

:9.  '''産土乃道行人乎見母知連神乃恵乃限無幾世乎'''
::''Ubusuna no michi yuku hito o mo shire kami no megumi no kagiri naki yo o''
::Know this, you who walk the Ubusuna's path: the blessings of the god in this world are without limit.

:10. '''産土乃数限奈木御恵乎一二三四毛知良奴哀左'''
::''Ubusuna no kazu kagiri naki mi-megumi o hitotsu futatsu mo shiranu aware sa''
::How pitiable are those who do not know even one or two of the countless blessings of the Ubusuna.

:11. '''産土波尊木母乃加飽奈久尔物知牟我士恵牟乎見連婆'''
::''Ubusuna wa tōtoki mono ka, ana kuni omochimu washi emu o mireba''
::Is the Ubusuna not a sacred thing? When I see how it smiles upon this land that I hold dear.

:12. '''産土乃産土多留乎知時波人乃人多留道尔違波自'''
::''Ubusuna no ubusuna taru o shiru toki wa hito no hito taru michi ni tagawaji''
::When you know what makes the Ubusuna what it is, you will not stray from the path of what makes a person what they are.

:13. '''産土乃富士与里高木御恵乎少加知良奴民乃悲左'''
::''Ubusuna no Fuji yori takaki mi-megumi o sukoshi ka shiranu tami no kanashi sa''
::How sorrowful are the people who know so little of the Ubusuna's blessings, which are higher than Mount Fuji.

:14. '''産土乃神乃恵乎知留人者人乃神奈留人止知留倍志'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no megumi o shiru hito wa hito no kami naru hito to shiru-beshi''
::You should know that a person who understands the blessings of the Ubusuna god is a person who is a god among men.

:15. '''産土乃海与里深木朝夕乃恵乎露母知良邪留波憂志'''
::''Ubusuna no umi yori fukaki asayū no megumi o tsuyu mo shiranu wa ushi''
::It is grievous that they do not know a drop of the morning and evening blessings of the Ubusuna, which are deeper than the sea.

:16. '''産土乃恵乃露乃懸良受波四方乃草木乃何尔育多牟'''
::''Ubusuna no megumi no tsuyu no kakarazu wa yomo no kusaki no nani ni sodatamu''
::If not touched by the dew of the Ubusuna's blessing, how could the grasses and trees in all directions grow?

:17. '''地乎走獣也空乎飛鳥母御霊賜留産土乃神'''
::''Chi o hashiru kemono ya sora o tobu tori mo mi-tama tamawaru ubusuna no kami''
::The beasts that run on the ground and the birds that fly in the sky also receive their spirits from the Ubusuna god.

:18. '''這虫母水行魚母産土乃神乃賜物慈愛世与'''
::''Hau mushi mo mizu yuku uo mo ubusuna no kami no tamamono,慈愛 seyo''
::The crawling insects and the fish that go in the water are also gifts from the Ubusuna god; you must treat them with loving compassion.

:19. '''寺々尔住武僧等母産土乃神乃御子曾母悪敷須奈人'''
::''Tera-dera ni sumu sō-domo mo ubusuna no kami no mi-ko zo mo, ashiku suna hito''
::The priests who live in the temples are also children of the Ubusuna god; people, do not treat them ill.

:20. '''魚乎食比美酒飮母産土乃恵成曾止思閉僧等'''
::''Uo o kui bi-shu nomu mo ubusuna no megumi naru zo to omoe sō-domo''
::Even when you eat fish and drink fine sake, O priests, you must remember that this too is a blessing of the Ubusuna.

:21. '''錦着弖妻子止寝留母産土乃神恩重禰之僧原加母'''
::''Nishiki kite saishi to neru mo ubusuna no shion kasanete no sō-bara ka mo''
::Wearing fine brocades and sleeping with wife and children—is this not the life of priests who have received layer upon layer of the Ubusuna god's grace?

:22. '''産土乃道知禰古曾僧等賀道乃巷尔立食須奈礼'''
::''Ubusuna no michi shine koso sō-domo ga michi no chimata ni tachi-habamu nare''
::It is ignorance of the Ubusuna's path that stands to obstruct the path of the priests.

:23. '''産土尔見放多連多留僧等賀石根木根尔人乃夢美留'''
::''Ubusuna ni mihanasaretaru sō-domo ga iwane kone ni hito no yume miru''
::The priests who have been abandoned by the Ubusuna see people in their dreams among the roots of rocks and trees.

:24. '''物食閉婆父乎之思比衣着連婆母思倍之僧奈賀良母'''
::''Mono kueba chichi o shi omoi, koromo kireba haha o omoe shi sō nagara mo''
::When you eat, think of your father; when you dress, think of your mother, even while you are a priest.

:25. '''僧等賀経誦武声母産土乃人尔授計志人乃声曾毛'''
::''Sō-domo ga kyō yomu koe mo ubusuna no hito ni sazukeshi hito no koe zo mo''
::The voices of the priests chanting sutras are also the voices of people, bestowed upon them by the Ubusuna.

:26. '''八十神乃遺世之道加母西戎国乃耶蘇賀教乃曲連留見連婆'''
::''Yasogami no nokoseshi michi ka mo saijū-koku no Yaso ga oshie no magaretaru mireba''
::Is this the path left by the myriad gods? When I see how twisted are the teachings of Jesus from the Western lands.

:27. '''産土乃神止神止乃神議尔結給比之夫婦乃縁之曾'''
::''Ubusuna no kami to kami to no kami-hakari ni musubi-tamaishi meko no enishi zo''
::The bond between husband and wife is one that was tied by the divine council of the Ubusuna gods.

:28. '''雨霰雪也氷母産土乃人乎憐牟涙奈留良免'''
::''Ame, arare, yuki ya kōri mo ubusuna no hito o awaremu namida naru ramu''
::The rain, hail, snow, and ice may well be the tears of compassion shed by the Ubusuna for its people.

:29. '''産土乃恵乃露尔梁良連弖花母紅葉母色尔出良志'''
::''Ubusuna no megumi no tsuyu ni yaraite hana mo momiji mo iro ni idurashi''
::Touched by the dew of the Ubusuna's blessing, the flowers and autumn leaves seem to burst forth in color.

:30. '''飛雲母鳴雷毛產土乃神乃声曾毛神乃像曾毛'''
::''Tobu kumo mo naru ikazuchi mo ubusuna no kami no koe zo mo kami no sugata zo mo''
::The flying clouds and the roaring thunder are the voice of the Ubusuna god, and they are the form of the god.

:31. '''産土乃神心善志產子等賀背向弖母恵麻須見礼婆'''
::''Ubusuna no kami-gokoro yeshi ubuko-ra ga somukite mo emasu mireba''
::The heart of the Ubusuna god is benevolent; I see that it smiles even upon the children of the soil who turn their backs.

:32. '''産土乃罰中連利止人皆尔指勿左々礼曾吾党乃子等'''
::''Ubusuna no bachi atareri to hito-mina ni yubi na sasare so waga tō no ko-ra''
::Do not be pointed at by all and told, "You have been punished by the Ubusuna," O children of my clan!

:33. '''産土乃神像与久見余金毛木母土毛水火母其中尔有'''
::''Ubusuna no kami-sugata yoku miyo, kane mo ki mo tsuchi mo mizu hi mo sono naka ni ari''
::Look closely at the form of the Ubusuna god: metal, wood, earth, water, and fire are all within it.

:34. '''音尔聞眼尔見物等悉尔産土神乃神身尔許曾阿連'''
::''Oto ni kiku me ni miru mono nado koto-goto ni ubusunagami no kami-mi ni koso are''
::All things heard by the ear and seen by the eye are indeed the divine body of the Ubusuna god.

:35. '''産土乃神不在地奈之烏鳴邪留里波有登毛'''
::''Ubusuna no kami imasanu chi nashi, karasu nakeru sato wa aredomo''
::There is no land where the Ubusuna god does not exist, though there may be villages where only crows cry.

:36. '''産土乃神随奈留国土尔出留宝乃限里阿良免也'''
::''Ubusuna no kannagara naru kokudo ni izuru takara no kagiri arame ya''
::In a land that is in accord with the Ubusuna god, can there be any limit to the treasures it yields?

:37. '''敷島乃大倭尔波有良奴西戎国毛産土神乃不在那志'''
::''Shikishima no Yamato ni wa aranu saijū-koku mo ubusunagami no imasanu wa nashi''
::Even in the lands of the West, which are not Yamato of the Isles, there is no place where an Ubusuna god does not exist.

:38. '''年尔日尔積留多加良母産土乃御骨血塩尔不有波那志'''
::''Toshi ni hi ni tsumoru takara mo ubusuna no on-hone-chi-shio ni aranu wa nashi''
::The treasures accumulated over the years and days are nothing but the bones, blood, and sweat of the Ubusuna.

:39. '''雨不降奴国波雖有産土乃御魂乃露乃加々良奴波奈志'''
::''Ame furanu kuni wa aredomo ubusuna no mi-tama no tsuyu no kakaranu wa nashi''
::Though there may be lands where no rain falls, there are none untouched by the dew of the Ubusuna's spirit.

:40. '''時々乃暑寒毛産土乃恩賴曾齋祁世乃人'''
::''Tokidoki no atsusa samusa mo ubusuna no onrai zo, itsuke yo no hito''
::The heat and cold of the seasons are also the blessings of the Ubusuna; O people of the world, be reverent.

:41. '''産土乃神乃神山尔啼鳥波不啼人尔満左里多留良志'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no mi-yama ni naku tori wa nakanu hito ni masaritarurashi''
::The birds that sing on the sacred mountain of the Ubusuna god seem to be superior to the people who do not sing.

:42. '''産土乃神乃御名乎之人問婆国津御魂乃御子止答倍牟'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no mi-na o shi hito towaba, kunitsu-mitama no mi-ko to kotaemu''
::If someone asks the name of the Ubusuna god, I shall answer: "It is the child of the Spirit of the Land."

:43. '''可惜産土神波在世礼止神名無伝百乃西戎国'''
::''Atarashi ubusunagami wa imaseredo kami-na tsutaenaki no saijū-koku''
::How regrettable are the hundred lands of the West, where the Ubusuna gods exist, yet their divine names are not passed down.

:44. '''産土乃神名不伝定麻礼留無君国曾殊尔悲志岐'''
::''Ubusuna no kami-na tsutaezu sadamareru kimi-naki kuni zo koto ni kanashiki''
::A land without a sovereign, where the names of the Ubusuna gods are not passed down, is especially sorrowful.

:45. '''悲岐波彼乃西戎国産土乃神名不伝道毛知那久'''
::''Kanashiki wa kano saijū-koku, ubusuna no kami-na tsutaezu michi mo shirinaku''
::How sorrowful are those Western lands; they do not pass down the names of their Ubusuna gods and do not know the Way.

:46. '''人今尔産土神乃神徳乎知尽倍岐時至倍志'''
::''Hito ima ni ubusunagami no shintoku o shiri-tsukusu-beki toki itaru-beshi''
::The time must come when people will fully know the divine virtue of the Ubusuna gods.

:47. '''産土乃神尔習弖顕人乃道乃柱尔立倍岐吾曾'''
::''Ubusuna no kami ni narate akitsuhito no michi no hashira ni tatsu-beki ware zo''
::It is I who must learn from the Ubusuna god and stand as a pillar of the Way for all living people.

:48. '''産土乃神者我神今世止後世万伝止我者賴麻牟'''
::''Ubusuna no kami wa waga kami, kono yo to nochi no yo yorozu-tsute to ware wa tanomamu''
::The Ubusuna god is my god; I will rely on it as my guide in this life and for all the ages to come.

:49. '''敷島乃日本国乎産土乃道乃御供止出立我波'''
::''Shikishima no Yamato no kuni o ubusuna no michi no mi-tomo to ide-tatsu ware wa''
::I shall set out to make the country of Yamato an attendant to the Way of the Ubusuna.

:50. '''産土乃神乃御典乎文机乃上尔演都々斃牟我波'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no mi-nori o fuzukue no ue ni nobetsutsu taoremu ware wa''
::I shall collapse while spreading the sacred teachings of the Ubusuna god upon my writing desk.

:'''従五位平朝臣親徳謹詠'''
:''Jūgoi Taira no Asomi Chikayoshi tsutsushinde yomu''
:Respectfully composed by Taira no Asomi Chikayoshi, Junior Fifth Rank.

===下巻 (Gekan) - Volume Two===

:'''産土百首(下巻) (Ubusuna Hyakushu (Gekan))'''
:'''One Hundred Poems on the Guardian Deity of the Birthplace (Volume Two)'''

:51. '''産土乃神不在者吾霊乎神府尔誰加送良武'''
::''Ubusuna no kami imasaneba waga tama o shinfu ni tare ka okuramu''
::If the Ubusuna god did not exist, who would send my spirit to the realm of the gods?

:52. '''人霊乃楽之悲之止活久波其産土乃在尔社与連'''
::''Hito-dama no tanoshiki kanashiki to iku wa sono ubusuna no aru ni koso yore''
::The joy and sorrow of the human spirit's life depend entirely on the existence of that Ubusuna.

:53. '''産土乃吾皇神波萬世耳霊体守良須神尔社有連'''
::''Ubusuna no waga sume-kami wa yorozuyo ni reitai mamorasu kami ni koso are''
::Our imperial Ubusuna god is the god who protects our spirit and body for all ages.

:54. '''親乃親子乃子末母産土乃神乃恩波尽留時奈之'''
::''Oya no ko ko no ko no sue mo ubusuna no kami no on wa tsukiru toki nashi''
::From parent to child, and from that child to their descendants, the blessings of the Ubusuna god will never end.

:55. '''産土乃神乃稜威乎不知之弖異之幾蕃神仰世人'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no itsu o shirashite koto no shiki adashi-kami o aoge yo no hito''
::You must know the divine power of the Ubusuna god, and not look up to other, foreign deities, O people of this world.

:56. '''安祁久争弖渡良武産土乃神乃幸乃世尔那加里勢婆'''
::''Akeku arasoute wataramu ubusuna no kami no sachi no yo ni nakariseba''
::People would live their lives in constant strife, if not for this blessed age of the Ubusuna god.

:57. '''産土乃神乃心尔符那婆家尔宝尔富栄那武'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no kokoro ni kanainaba ie ni takara ni tomi-sakaenamu''
::If you are in harmony with the heart of the Ubusuna god, your home will flourish in wealth and treasure.

:58. '''産土乃神祈之弖其後尔天地乃神者祈倍木也'''
::''Ubusuna no kami o inorite sono nochi ni ametsuchi no kami wa inoru-beki ya''
::After you have prayed to the Ubusuna god, then you may pray to the gods of Heaven and Earth.

:59. '''産土乃厳乃華表波霊止体乃不浄乎祓布門尔古曾安礼'''
::''Ubusuna no itsu no torii wa rei to tai no fujō o harau kado ni koso are''
::The sacred torii gate of the Ubusuna is the gate that purifies the impurities of spirit and body.

:60. '''可祈吾神置弖他村乃産土拝牟人者惑倍里'''
::''Kaku waga kami o okite hoka-mura no ubusuna ogamu hito wa madoeri''
::Those who neglect their own god to worship the Ubusuna of another village have gone astray.

:61. '''穀物秋乃初穂者産土乃神乃御前尔捧留物曾'''
::''Kokumotsu aki no hatsuho wa ubusuna no kami no mi-mae ni sasaguru mono zo''
::The first grains of the autumn harvest are something to be offered before the Ubusuna god.

:62. '''衆神波吾産土乃神祭々里弖後尔相祭留倍志'''
::''Morogami wa waga ubusuna no kami o matsuri-matsurite nochi ni ai-matsuru-beshi''
::You should worship the myriad gods only after you have fully worshipped your own Ubusuna god.

:63. '''産土乃霊招万須加旅人賀己国村慕乎見連婆'''
::''Ubusuna no tama maneku ka tabibito ga onoga kuni-mura o shitau o mireba''
::Does the spirit of the Ubusuna beckon? I see the traveler longing for the village of his own land.

:64. '''旅衣重之我毛産土乃霊思婆涙久満之母'''
::''Tabigoromo omoshi ware mo ubusuna no tama o omoeba namida kumashi mo''
::My traveler's robes are heavy, and when I think of the spirit of my Ubusuna, my eyes fill with tears.

:65. '''産土波貴物加毛山人賀京見捨弖帰留乎見礼婆'''
::''Ubusuna wa tōtoki mono ka mo yamabito ga miyako misutete kaeru o mireba''
::Is the Ubusuna not a precious thing? I see the man of the mountains leaving the capital to return to it.

:66. '''産土乃霊乃露乃如此志古曾綾尔染祁女百乃樹花'''
::''Ubusuna no tama no tsuyu no kaku shi koso aya ni somekere momo no ki no hana''
::It is the dew of the Ubusuna's spirit that has dyed the many tree blossoms in such wondrous patterns.

:67. '''安良加尔高枕之弖居留事母其産土乃幸尔社安礼'''
::''Arakaru ni takamakura shite oru koto mo sono ubusuna no sachi ni koso are''
::To be able to live with a high pillow in peace is a blessing of that Ubusuna.

:68. '''物皆者其産土乃賚曾人乃手力何乎那志得牟'''
::''Mono mina wa sono ubusuna no tamamono zo hito no tejikara nani o nashi-emu''
::All things are gifts from that Ubusuna; what can be achieved by human strength alone?

:69. '''眼尔見留物耳聞声悉久吾産土乃神乃御幸曾'''
::''Me ni miru mono mimi ni kiku koe kotogotoku waga ubusuna no kami no mi-sachi zo''
::All things seen by the eye and all sounds heard by the ear are the blessings of my Ubusuna god.

:70. '''吹風母雨降音母産土乃神乃御声止聞与產子等'''
::''Fuku kaze mo ame furu oto mo ubusuna no kami no mi-koe to kike yo ubuko-ra''
::The blowing wind and the sound of falling rain—listen to them as the sacred voice of the Ubusuna god, O children of the soil!

:71. '''遠郷尔身波志雖在産土乃神乃恩者忘連兼都母'''
::''Tozato ni mi wa shi aredomo ubusuna no kami no on wa wasurekanetsu mo''
::Though my body is in a distant village, I cannot forget the grace of my Ubusuna god.

:72. '''皇軍乃中尔在弖母産土乃夢見留宵曾我者楽敷'''
::''Sumeragi no naka ni arite mo ubusuna no yume miru yoi zo ware wa tanoshiki''
::Even when I am among the Emperor's soldiers, the nights I dream of my Ubusuna are joyous for me.

:73. '''敵人乃矢串尔向武夫母其産土者思出良牟'''
::''Teki no yagushi ni mukau masurao mo sono ubusuna wa omoi-izuramu''
::Even the warrior who faces the enemy's volley of arrows surely thinks of his Ubusuna.

:74. '''人波与志如何言登母産土乃神殿守止成倍志我波'''
::''Hito wa yoshi ika ni iu tomo ubusuna no miya-mori to naru-beshi ware wa''
::Let others say what they will; as for me, I shall become a guardian of my Ubusuna shrine.

:75. '''霊魂尔玷付受之弖産土乃神尔帰須曾人乃道曾毛'''
::''Reikon ni kizu tsukezu shite ubusuna no kami ni kaesu zo hito no michi zo mo''
::To return your soul to the Ubusuna god without a single wound upon it—that is the path of a person.

:76. '''霊魂乃道乃行末者産土乃神乃宮辺曾初也祁留'''
::''Reikon no michi no yukusue wa ubusuna no kami no miya-be zo hatsu ya keru''
::The final destination on the path of the soul is the beginning: the shrine of the Ubusuna god.

:77. '''眼前尔産土乃神立坐弖魂乃善悪見給母乃曾'''
::''Me no mae ni ubusuna no kami tachi-imashite tama no zen-aku mitamau mono zo''
::The Ubusuna god stands before your very eyes and sees the good and evil of your soul.

:78. '''産土乃神乃耳眼者大山乎隔多里止母見透尔坐須'''
::''Ubusuna no kami no mimi me wa ōyama o hedatari tomo mitōshi ni imasu''
::The eyes and ears of the Ubusuna god can see through even great mountains that stand as barriers.

:79. '''秘事人者不知母産土乃神者熟知留慎女与人'''
::''Hisokegoto hito wa shirazu mo ubusuna no kami wa tsura-tsura shiru, tsutsushime yo hito''
::People may not know your secret affairs, but the Ubusuna god knows them in full detail. Be prudent, O people!

:80. '''各々乃胸腹内尔産土乃神隱坐須恐弖与人'''
::''Ono-ono no muna-hara-uchi ni ubusuna no kami kakuri-imasu, kashikome yo hito''
::Within the heart and belly of each and every person, the Ubusuna god resides in hiding. Be reverent, O people!

:81. '''霊魂乃帰着倍木産土乃神乎神登母知人乃奈支'''
::''Reikon no kaeri-tsuku-beki ubusuna no kami o kami to mo shiru hito no naki''
::There are no people who do not know as a god the Ubusuna god, to whom their souls must return.

:82. '''狡意尔言挙勿勢曾産土乃神乃正道聞知受之弖'''
::''Sakashira ni kotoage na se so ubusuna no kami no masamichi kikishirazu shite''
::Do not speak with false wisdom, ignorant of the true path of the Ubusuna god.

:83. '''彼母亦神乃産子曾我母亦神乃産子曾美三世与'''
::''Are mo mata kami no ubuko zo ware mo mata kami no ubuko zo, umashi mitsuse yo''
::That person is a child of the god, and I too am a child of the god. Oh, how beautiful is this world!

:84. '''瓢形乃雲乃上人母草野成蒼生母産土乃子曾'''
::''Hisago-gata no kumo no uebito mo kusano naru aohitogusa mo ubusuna no ko zo''
::The nobles above the gourd-shaped clouds and the common folk who are like the grasses of the field are all children of the Ubusuna.

:85. '''家居那支野乃末山乃奥山母産土乃神在佐奴者那志'''
::''Ie-i naki no no sue-yama no oku-yama mo ubusuna no kami imasanu wa nashi''
::Even in the remote mountains beyond the fields where no one lives, there is no place where the Ubusuna god does not exist.

:86. '''青雲乃向伏限産土乃神乃霊乃到良奴者有良自'''
::''Aogumo no mukabusu kagiri ubusuna no kami no rei no itaranu wa araji''
::To the very limits where the blue clouds hang low, there can be no place the spirit of the Ubusuna god does not reach.

:87. '''産土乃皇神置弖吾霊乃帰着倍支八十隈者奈之'''
::''Ubusuna no sume-kami o okite waga tama no kaeri-tsuku-beki yaso-kuma wa nashi''
::There is no other corner of the world where my soul can return, except to the imperial Ubusuna god.

:88. '''独行帰良奴旅乎産土乃神之命曾誘比給閉留'''
::''Hitori yuki kaeranu tabi o ubusuna no kami no mikoto zo sasoitamaeru''
::This journey of no return that one travels alone—it is the Ubusuna god who has invited us upon it.

:89. '''唯賴女産土神乎唯賴女唯今乃世母唯未来乃世母'''
::''Tada tanome ubusunagami o tada tanome, tada ima no yo mo tada来 no yo mo''
::Rely only on the Ubusuna god! Rely only on it, in this present world and in the world to come!

:90. '''善悪敷霊乃審判乎産土乃神府波定給閉留'''
::''Zen-ashiki tama no tadasu o ubusuna no shinfu wa sadame-tamaeru''
::The divine court of the Ubusuna determines the judgment of good and evil souls.

:91. '''産土乃神不在者愚那留此吾魂乎誰加救波牟'''
::''Ubusuna no kami imasaneba oroka naru kono waga tama o tare ka sukuwamu''
::If the Ubusuna god did not exist, who would save this foolish soul of mine?

:92. '''千萬尔神者雖坐産神乃吾皇神波身守乃神'''
::''Chi-yorozu ni kami wa imasedo ubusuna no waga sume-kami wa mi-mamori no kami''
::Though ten million gods may exist, my imperial Ubusuna god is the god who protects my body.

:93. '''阿弥陀等賀言喧久止母産土乃吾神達波微笑坐倍之'''
::''Amida-ra ga koto yakamashiku tomo ubusuna no waga kami-tachi wa emi-imasu-beshi''
::However loudly Amida and the others may preach, my Ubusuna gods will only sit and smile.

:94. '''産土乃神達祈里子孫乃八十次々尔栄行祁人'''
::''Ubusuna no kami-tachi o inori, ko-mago no yaso-tsugi-tsugi ni sakae-yuke hito''
::Pray to the Ubusuna gods, and may your children and grandchildren flourish for eighty generations!

:95. '''修身斉家道社者産土神乃道乃本那礼'''
::''Shūshin seika michi koso wa ubusunagami no michi no moto nare''
::The way of cultivating the self and ordering the home is the very foundation of the way of the Ubusuna god.

:96. '''前世母現世母後世乃事母産土神曾主宰坐須'''
::''Saki-yo mo utsushi-yo mo nochi-yo no koto mo ubusunagami zo shusai shimasu''
::The Ubusuna god presides over the affairs of the past life, the present life, and the life to come.

:97. '''産土乃神忽忘曾産土乃恩者後乃萬世麻伝尔'''
::''Ubusuna no kami na wasure so, ubusuna no on wa nochi no yorozuyo madeni''
::Do not forget the Ubusuna god, for its blessings extend to ten thousand generations in the future.

:98. '''産土者眼尔見由流神産土者耳尔聞神信女世乃人'''
::''Ubusuna wa me ni miyuru kami, ubusuna wa mimi ni kiku kami, shinze yo no hito''
::The Ubusuna is a god that can be seen by the eye; the Ubusuna is a god that can be heard by the ear. Believe in it, O people of the world!

:99. '''霊魂乃汚乎祓比産土乃神乃愛子止在世世人'''
::''Reikon no kegare o harai ubusuna no kami no manashi-go to are yo yo no hito''
::Cleanse the stains from your soul and live as the beloved child of the Ubusuna god, O people of the world!

:100. '''産土乃神許有弖天地乃神者諾比給布倍木那理'''
::''Ubusuna no kami yuri-arite ametsuchi no kami wa uke-gai-tamau-beki nari''
::It is with the permission of the Ubusuna god that the gods of Heaven and Earth must give their consent.

:'''桓武天皇之皇子葛原親王三十四世'''
:'''平朝臣親徳謹詠'''
:'''明治十八年五月六日'''
:'''六十一年五ケ月'''

:''Kanmu-tennō no miko Katsurabara-shinnō sanjūyonsei''
:''Taira no Asomi Chikayoshi tsutsushinde yomu''
:''Meiji jūhachinen gogatsu muika''
:''Rokujūichinen gogetsu''

:Respectfully composed by Taira no Asomi Chikayoshi,
:34th generation descendant of Prince Katsurabara, son of Emperor Kanmu.
:May 6th, Meiji 18 (1885).
:Age sixty-one years and five months.

==Reikon Hyakushu (霊魂百首)==
This text is the "Reikon Hyakushu," which translates to "One Hundred Poems on the Soul." It is a collection of one hundred Japanese poems (''waka'') about the nature of the spirit, structured around key concepts in Shinto thought.

The poems are written in Man'yōgana, an ancient script that uses Chinese characters phonetically. The work explores the divine "Way," the virtues of the soul, and the four aspects of the spirit known as the ''Shikon'' (Four Souls): the Rough Soul (''Aramitama''), the Harmonious Soul (''Nigimitama''), the Nurturing Soul (''Sakimitama''), and the Wondrous Soul (''Kushimitama'').

Below is a complete translation of the text, organized by its original sections. Each translation is preceded by a romanized version of the Japanese text.
;霊魂百首 (Reikon Hyakushu)

One Hundred Poems on the Soul

===道 (Michi) - The Way===

:1.  '''大神乃真能道波天地仁先立成礼留物尔社有礼'''
::''Ōkami no makoto no michi wa ametsuchi ni sakidachi nareru mono ni koso are''
::The true Way of the Great God is indeed that which was established before Heaven and Earth.

:2.  '''大神乃真能道波諸神乃生始太留根本尔社有礼'''
::''Ōkami no makoto no michi wa morogami no umare-hajimetaru konpon ni koso are''
::The true Way of the Great God is indeed the root from which all other gods began to be born.

:3.  '''大神乃道波美波志天地乎鎔造給比之根元尔之有礼婆'''
::''Ōkami no michi wa mibashi ametsuchi o ite-tsukuri-tamaishi konpon ni shi areba''
::Because the Way of the Great God is the very origin from which Heaven and Earth were forged and made.

:4.  '''大神乃道波尊登志日一日毛行波連左留未志母無志'''
::''Ōkami no michi wa tōtoshi hi ni ichinichi mo okonawaresaru mashi mo nashi''
::The Way of the Great God is so sacred that not a single day passes when it is not in motion.

:5.  '''大神乃道波恐古之天地能萬乃物能出来留見礼婆'''
::''Ōkami no michi wa kashikoshi ametsuchi no yorozu no mono no idekitaru mireba''
::The Way of the Great God is awesome to behold, for from it all things in Heaven and Earth have come forth.

:6.  '''大神能道有礼婆社神毛人毛千世萬世母生弖社有礼'''
::''Ōkami no michi areba koso kami mo hito mo chiyo yorozuyo mo ikite koso are''
::It is because the Way of the Great God exists that gods and men can live for a thousand, for ten thousand generations.

:7.  '''大神乃道乃光尔因利弖社天照神毛伊照利徹世'''
::''Ōkami no michi no hikari ni yorite koso Amaterasu kami mo iteri-tōrase''
::It is by the light of the Great God's Way that even the Sun Goddess Amaterasu shines through.

:8.  '''大神乃広介伎道乎際涯無伎大虛能星乃数尔弖叙知留'''
::''Ōkami no hirosuki michi o saihate naki ōzora no hoshi no kazu nite zo shiru''
::One can know the breadth of the Great God's Way by the number of stars in the boundless great sky.

:9.  '''天地乃道有礼婆社諸乃神毛神多利人母人太利'''
::''Ametsuchi no michi areba koso moro no kami mo kami-tari hito mo hito-tari''
::It is because the Way of Heaven and Earth exists that the many gods can be gods, and people can be people.

:10. '''神隨奈留大道波後世乃末賀末麻弖変良左留道'''
::''Kannagara naru ōmichi wa nochinoyo no sue no sue made kawarasaru michi''
::The Great Way that flows from the gods is a path that will remain unchanged until the very end of future ages.

===理 (Kotowari) - Reason / Principle===

:1.  '''大神乃経志緯志乃理波萬世経登母違布時無志'''
::''Ōkami no tateshi nukishi no kotowari wa yorozuyo hedomo tagau toki nashi''
::The principles of the warp and weft set by the Great God will never be defied, though ten thousand ages pass.

:2.  '''理波正之伎物乎紊佐牟斗思比謀良布人乃悲之佐'''
::''Kotowari wa tadashiki mono o midasamu to omoi-hakurau hito no kanashisa''
::How sorrowful are those who scheme and plot to disturb that which is correct by principle.

:3.  '''理乃其正志伎遠不得与利人乃行比打乱連太利'''
::''Kotowari no sono tadashiki o enu yori hito no okanai uchi-midaretari''
::By failing to grasp this correct principle, the conduct of people has fallen into disorder.

:4.  '''経緯乃其理乎得弖斯有良婆神尔恥左留人止為倍志'''
::''Tate-nuki no sono kotowari o ete shi araba kami ni hazaru hito to naru-beshi''
::If you can grasp the principle of the warp and weft, you shall become a person who is unashamed before the gods.

:5.  '''理乎攪美探利美世中乃人能真事波尽寸倍伎奈利'''
::''Kotowari o kakimi sagurimi yononaka no hito no makoto wa tsukusu-beki nari''
::One must seek out and explore principle, and thereby perfect the truth of the people of this world.

:6.  '''火仁焼受水仁溺連奴大神乃理社波尊加利介礼'''
::''Hi ni yakezu mizu ni oborenu Ōkami no kotowari koso wa tōtokarikere''
::Unyielding to fire, unsinking in water—how sacred is the principle of the Great God.

:7.  '''独立独行倍伎経緯乃此理之神随奈留'''
::''Hitori-dachi hitori-okonau-beki tate-nuki no kono kotowari shi kannagara naru''
::This principle of the warp and weft, which one must uphold and practice alone, flows from the very nature of the gods.

:8.  '''事物仁顕連出留理乃象波綾尔奇有介利'''
::''Koto-mono ni araware-izuru kotowari no katachi wa aya ni kushiku arikere''
::The forms of principle that manifest in all things and affairs are wondrously beautiful.

:9.  '''踏分与吾経緯乃理波吾大神能敷坐留道'''
::''Fumiwake yo waga tate-nuki no kotowari wa waga Ōkami no shiki-maseru michi''
::Tread this path well! My principle of warp and weft is the Way laid down by my Great God.

:10. '''経緯乃理能絲不紊波織成世留絹伊照良牟物叙'''
::''Tate-nuki no kotowari no ito midare neba ori-naseru kinu iteramu mono zo''
::If the threads of the principle of warp and weft are not tangled, the silk they weave shall surely shine brightly.

===徳 (Toku) - Virtue===

:1.  '''世中乃有乃尽幽冥乃神能神徳曾仰介人之子'''
::''Yononaka no ari no kagiri kakuriyo no kami no shintoku zo aoge hito no ko''
::Revere the divine virtue of the gods of the hidden world, who encompass all that exists in this one, O children of men!

:2.  '''神徳仁化育良礼由久諸乃萬乃物波見礼杼飽奴加母'''
::''Shintoku ni keiku-serare-yuku moro no yorozu no mono wa miredo akanu kamo''
::I shall never tire of seeing the myriad things that are nurtured and raised by divine virtue.

:3.  '''春波花秋波紅葉斗世中乃遷呂比往毛神乃神徳叙'''
::''Haru wa hana aki wa momiji to yononaka no utsuroi-yuku mo kami no shintoku zo''
::Flowers in spring, crimson leaves in autumn—the changing of the seasons in this world is also the virtue of the gods.

:4.  '''夢仁太仁神乃神徳乎不知婆人仁生礼志甲斐也無良牟'''
::''Yume ni dani kami no shintoku o shirazuba hito ni umareshi kai ya nakaramu''
::If you do not know the virtue of the gods even in your dreams, there is no meaning in having been born a person.

:5.  '''天尔坐寸神能神徳波限無志何礼乃人加算閉尽左牟'''
::''Ame ni masu kami no shintoku wa kagiri nashi izure no hito ka kazoe-tsukusamu''
::The virtue of the gods in heaven is boundless. What person could ever count it all?

:6.  '''天地乎動須神乃神徳遠之仰岐弖見礼婆尊伎呂加母'''
::''Ametsuchi o ugokasu kami no shintoku o shi aogite mireba tōtokiro kamo''
::When I look up in reverence at the divine virtue of the gods who move Heaven and Earth, how sacred it is!

:7.  '''生留々毛死留毛共尔皇神能物乎恵麻須数仁社有礼'''
::''Umaruru mo shinuru mo tomo ni sume-kami no mono o emasu kazu ni koso are''
::Both being born and dying are counted among the blessings bestowed by the Imperial God.

:8.  '''雨降礼婆風日加照礼婆雨大神乃物遠恵麻須験也介利'''
::''Ame fureba kaze hi ka tereba ame Ōkami no mono o emasu shirushi ya keri''
::When the rain falls, when the wind blows, when the sun shines—these are all signs of the blessings bestowed by the Great God.

:9.  '''大神乃神徳尊止志人皆乃心能玉波昼夜照良勢里'''
::''Ōkami no shintoku tōtoshi hito-mina no kokoro no tama wa hiru-yoru teraseri''
::The virtue of the Great God is sacred; it illuminates the jewel of every person's heart, day and night.

:10. '''神徳乎今毛委曲仁言継志吾遠都祖波真神乃子'''
::''Shintoku o ima mo kuwashiku ni ii-tsugishi waga tōtsu-oya wa makami no ko''
::My distant ancestors who passed down these detailed words about divine virtue are children of a true god.

===義 (Gi) - Righteousness===

:1.  '''義言義行波大神能賦賜比之道能大本'''
::''Gigengigyō wa Ōkami no yosoi-tamaishi no michi no ōmoto''
::Righteous words and righteous deeds are the great foundation of the Way bestowed upon us by the Great God.

:2.  '''青雲乃向伏極美築立之神乃柱波義心奈利'''
::''Aogumo no mukabusu kiwami tsuki-tateshi kami no hashira wa gishin nari''
::The pillar of the gods, erected to the very limits where the blue clouds hang low, is a righteous heart.

:3.  '''義波賞米不義波爵武大神乃厳乃御規則波天地乃共'''
::''Gi wa home fugi wa semuru Ōkami no itsu no mi-nori wa ametsuchi no tomo''
::Righteousness is praised, unrighteousness is punished—this strict law of the Great God is shared by Heaven and Earth.

:4.  '''義務々米受志弖波自然神爵麻須人登為留倍志'''
::''Gi o tsutomezu shite wa onozukara kami semasu hito to naru-beshi''
::One who does not strive for righteousness will naturally become a person punished by the gods.

:5.  '''神習閉又神習閉大神能与伎義務乃神乃御教'''
::''Kami-narai mata kami-narae Ōkami no yoki gi o tsutomu no kami no mi-oshie''
::Learn from the gods, and learn again! The sacred teaching of the gods is to strive for good and righteousness.

:6.  '''夜光留珠与利光礼里大神能義心波朝奈夕奈尔'''
::''Yoru-hikaru tama yori hikareri Ōkami no gishin wa asana yūna ni''
::Shining brighter than a jewel that glows in the night is the righteous heart of the Great God, morning and evening.

:7.  '''不義弖富遠貪保留心遠之鳥虫乃如神波見麻左牟'''
::''Fugi shite tomi o musaboru kokoro o shi tori-mushi no goto kami wa mimusamu''
::A heart that unrighteously covets wealth will be seen by the gods as no different from a bird or an insect.

:8.  '''義心有良受弖世尔志在人能神乃爵乎受左留波奈之'''
::''Gishin arazu shite yo ni shi aru hito no kami no seme o ukezaru wa nashi''
::There is no one living in this world without a righteous heart who will escape the punishment of the gods.

:9.  '''世乃中乃公民能宝波之神乃授介志義心叙母'''
::''Yononaka no ōmitakara no takara wa shi kami no sazukeshi gishin zo mo''
::The true treasure of the people of this world is the righteous heart bestowed upon them by the gods.

:10. '''名乎惜美身乎惜麻左留心社神能教閉志義心奈礼'''
::''Na o oshimi mi o oshimazaru kokoro koso kami no oshieshi gishin nare''
::A heart that values its honor and does not spare its body—that is the righteous heart taught by the gods.

===直霊 (Naohi) - The Straight Spirit===

:1.  '''天地乃直良比巡留蹤乎見弖神能直霊乃直伎遠叙知留'''
::''Ametsuchi no naorai-meguru ato o mite kami no naohi no naoki o zo shiru''
::Seeing the path of Heaven and Earth circling in right order, one knows the straightness of the Straight Spirit of the gods.

:2.  '''天地遠直須皇神能御心乎受弖生連志人能直霊叙'''
::''Ametsuchi o naosu sume-kami no mi-kokoro o ukete umareshi hito no naohi zo''
::It is the Straight Spirit of a person, born having received the heart of the Imperial God who makes Heaven and Earth right.

:3.  '''皇神乃直霊乃心賜波里志人斗思閉婆於武加志伎可母'''
::''Sume-kami no naohi no kokoro tamawarishi hito to omoeba omokashiki kamo''
::When I think that I am a person who has been granted the heart of the Straight Spirit of the Imperial God, I feel a sense of honor.

:4.  '''大地廼底比乃宇良仁突立留魂能柱波直霊奈留叙母'''
::''Ōchi no sokohi no ura ni tsuki-tateru tama no hashira wa naohi naru zo mo''
::The pillar of the soul, planted deep in the bottom of the great earth, is indeed the Straight Spirit.

:5.  '''人皆乃直毘乃魂波人皆能萬世麻伝迺珠乃真宝'''
::''Hito-mina no naobi no tama wa hito-mina no yorozuyo madeni no tama no matakara''
::The jewel of the Straight Spirit in every person is the true treasure for all people, for ten thousand generations.

:6.  '''其身仁志直毘廼神能坐須事乎知得弖後乃人登社言免'''
::''Sono mi ni shi naobi no kami no imasu koto o shiri-ete nochi no hito to koso iwame''
::Only after one understands that the god of the Straight Spirit resides within one's own body can one be called a true person.

:7.  '''皇神乃神子尔志有礼婆於乃豆加良神乃直霊波腹古母利太里'''
::''Sume-kami no kami-ko ni shi areba onozukara kami no naohi wa hara-komorしたり''
::Because we are the children of the Imperial God, the Straight Spirit of the gods naturally dwells within us.

:8.  '''直霊波志貴伎呂加母直霊波志貴伎呂迦母神乃賜物'''
::''Naohi wa shikikiro kamo naohi wa shikikiro kamo kami no tamamono''
::The Straight Spirit is a wondrous thing! The Straight Spirit is a wondrous thing! A gift from the gods.

:9.  '''直霊波毛魂乃安留自叙庫内仁斎伎祀里弖拝免神乃子'''
::''Naohi wa mo tama no aruji zo kura-uchi ni itsuki-matsurite ogame kami no ko''
::The Straight Spirit is the master of the soul! O child of the gods, enshrine it within you and worship it with reverence.

:10. '''言直志見直須神乃心遠志人波心尔習布倍伎那利'''
::''Koto-naoshi mi-naosu kami no kokoro o shi hito wa kokoro ni narau-beki nari''
::People must learn in their own hearts the heart of the gods, who correct what is said and what is seen.

===荒魂 (Aramitama) - The Rough Soul===

:1.  '''国乃為家能為仁登身遠碎伎力尽須曾荒魂那留'''
::''Kuni no tame ie no tame ni to mi o kudaki chikara tsukusu zo aramitamam naru''
::To shatter one's body and exhaust one's strength for the sake of country and home—that is the Rough Soul.

:2.  '''荒魂乎伊振起志弖道能為尔神子人波相斃留倍志'''
::''Aramitama o ifuri-okoshite michi no tame ni kami-ko hito wa ai-taoru-beshi''
::Rouse your Rough Soul! For the sake of the Way, the children of the gods must strive together.

:3.  '''勉武倍支道乃為尔波荒魂乎弥進武倍志人多留人波'''
::''Tsutomu-beki michi no tame ni wa aramitama o iya susumu-beshi hito-taru hito wa''
::For the sake of the Way you must follow, a true person must advance their Rough Soul ever forward.

:4.  '''荒魂乃魂能柱波天地止共仁立倍伎厳乃柱曾'''
::''Aramitama no tama no hashira wa ametsuchi to tomo ni tatsu-beki itsu no hashira zo''
::The pillar of the Rough Soul is a mighty pillar that must stand together with Heaven and Earth.

:5.  '''荒魂乃活加左連婆世中乃有能事毎成果麻自母'''
::''Aramitama no ikasazareba yononaka no ari no kotogoto naru-bekumaji mo''
::If the Rough Soul is not brought to life, then nothing in this world can ever be accomplished.

:6.  '''天皇乃御上思比弖荒魂乎突立人波貴伎呂加母'''
::''Sumeragi no mi-kami omoite aramitama o tsuki-tatsu hito wa tōtokiro kamo''
::How noble is the person who, thinking of the Emperor, lets their Rough Soul rise up.

:7.  '''善事尔弥進武倍志荒魂乃弥進牟倍之吾党乃子等'''
::''Yoki koto ni iya susumu-beshi aramitama no iya susumu-beshi waga tō no ko-ra''
::You must advance toward good deeds! Advance your Rough Soul ever forward, O children of my clan!

:8.  '''荒魂乃伊照輝久重嶋乃日本能国波安良介久古曾'''
::''Aramitama no iteri-kagayaku shikishima no yamato no kuni wa arakesuku koso''
::Where the Rough Soul shines brightly, the land of Yamato of the many isles is ever valiant.

:9.  '''道乃為劎能中仁荒魂乃立倍伎事遠夢奈忘礼叙'''
::''Michi no tame tsurugi no naka ni aramitama no tatsu-beki koto o yume na wasure so''
::For the sake of the Way, do not ever forget that your Rough Soul must rise even amidst swords.

:10. '''荒魂乃光波後乃世乃末乃常闇廼世毛照寸倍支也'''
::''Aramitama no hikari wa nochinoyo no sue no tokoyami no yo mo terasu-beki ya''
::The light of the Rough Soul shall illuminate even the age of eternal darkness at the end of the world.

===和魂 (Nigimitama) - The Harmonious Soul===

:1.  '''天地乃伊行巡良比離礼左留心曾神乃和魂那留'''
::''Ametsuchi no iki-megurai hanaresaru kokoro zo kami no nigimitama naru''
::The heart that moves in harmony with the cycles of Heaven and Earth and is never separated from them—that is the Harmonious Soul of the gods.

:2.  '''親魂廼相和比弖天下能政事者突立母乃曾'''
::''Nigi-tama no ai-awaite amenoshita no matsurigoto wa tsuki-tatsu mono zo''
::The governance of the realm is established when the Harmonious Souls are in accord.

:3.  '''空翔留鳥乃類毛親魂乃神乃幸加毛相並行久'''
::''Sora-kakeru tori no tagui mo nigi-tama no kami no sachi kamo ai-narabi-yuku''
::Even the flocks of birds that fly through the sky, flying side-by-side, are a blessing from the god of the Harmonious Soul.

:4.  '''恵良恵良尔歌比賑布家尔古曾親魂幸布神者寄坐世'''
::''Era-era ni utai-nigiwau ie ni koso nigi-tama sakiwau kami wa yori-imase''
::It is in a home that is cheerful with song and celebration that the god who blesses with the Harmonious Soul will draw near.

:5.  '''彼止言比是止言斗毛和魂乃神乃見坐左婆同志祁武加母'''
::''Ka to ii shi to iu domo nigimitama no kami no mimaseba onajikemu kamo''
::Though some say this and others say that, if the god of the Harmonious Soul were to look, would they not all appear the same?

:6.  '''君親母夫婦兄弟毛子毛友毛親魂合弖立倍木道曾'''
::''Kimi oya mo meko kyōdai mo ko mo tomo mo nigi-tama awasete tatsu-beki michi zo''
::Lord and parent, husband and wife, brothers, children, and friends—it is a path that must be walked by joining their Harmonious Souls together.

:7.  '''和魂乃神乃御霊従国乎治米家乎斉布法者立曾毛'''
::''Nigimitama no kami no mi-tama yori kuni o osame ie o totonou nori wa tatsu zo mo''
::From the spirit of the god of the Harmonious Soul comes the law for governing the country and ordering the home.

:8.  '''和魂乃神乃神慮奈加里世婆己賀乖々人者安里奈武'''
::''Nigimitama no kami no mi-kokoro nakariseba onoga somuki-somuki hito wa arinamu''
::If the heart of the god of the Harmonious Soul did not exist, people would surely live in opposition to one another.

:9.  '''親敷支心曾人乃心那留踏勿惑比曾和能和道'''
::''Shitashiki kokoro koso hito no kokoro naru fumi-madowai so wa no wa-dō''
::A heart of intimacy is the true heart of a person; do not stray from the peaceful path of harmony.

:10. '''藰菰乃乱連之世仁母和魂乃乱連奴人曾功勲者立都'''
::''Saga no midareru yo ni mo nigimitama no midarenu hito zo isao wa tatsu''
::Even in a world as tangled as wild rice, it is the person whose Harmonious Soul is undisturbed who achieves great deeds.

===幸魂 (Sakimitama) - The Nurturing Soul===

:1.  '''家母身母顧奈久弖国乃為尽須心曾幸魂那留'''
::''Ie mo mi mo kaerimi-naku shite kuni no tame tsukusu kokoro zo sakimitama naru''
::A heart that serves the nation without regard for home or self—that is the Nurturing Soul.

:2.  '''幸魂乃全祁牟人者国乃為家乃為奈留底宝主'''
::''Sakimitama no mattakemu hito wa kuni no tame ie no tame naru di-takara-nushi''
::A person whose Nurturing Soul is whole is a true treasure-holder for both the nation and the home.

:3.  '''白金母黄金母珠母幸魂乃開出太理之華尔社安良目'''
::''Shirogane mo kogane mo tama mo sakimitama no saki-idetarishi hana ni koso arame''
::Silver, gold, and jewels are all but flowers that have blossomed forth from the Nurturing Soul.

:4.  '''人那良奴活物須良母子乎思布幸魂而己者等加里祁里'''
::''Hito naranu ikimono sura mo ko o omou sakimitama nite ko wa hitoshikarikeri''
::Even in beasts, the Nurturing Soul that loves its young is one and the same as our own.

:5.  '''物幸布魂之無連婆人尔之弖人尔不有人止見留倍之'''
::''Mono sakiwau tama shi nakereba hito ni shite hito ni aranu hito to miru-beshi''
::If one lacks the soul that brings forth blessings, one must be seen as a person who is not truly a person.

:6.  '''彼我乃差別不有幸魂乃神乃真幸者厚久広祁志'''
::''Are-ware no shabetsu wa arazu sakimitama no kami no masachi wa atsuku hirokeshi''
::There is no distinction between "self" and "other"; the true blessings of the god of the Nurturing Soul are deep and wide.

:7.  '''幸々者己賀幸々蒙布留曾神幸魂乃御幸尔者安留'''
::''Saki-saki wa onoga saki-saki kōmuru zo kami sakimitama no mi-sachi ni wa aru''
::To nurture others is to receive nurturing for oneself; such is the great blessing of the god of the Nurturing Soul.

:8.  '''百々千々尔形異連杼幸魂乃神乃神幸乃姿止曾視留'''
::''Momo-chiji ni katachi kotoredo sakimitama no kami no mi-sachi no sugata to zo miru''
::Though their forms differ in a hundred, a thousand ways, I see them all as figures of the blessings from the god of the Nurturing Soul.

:9.  '''子乎思布親乃心者天地乃自然那留幸魂那里'''
::''Ko o omou oya no kokoro wa ametsuchi no onozukara naru sakimitama nari''
::The heart of a parent who loves their child is the Nurturing Soul, born of the very nature of Heaven and Earth.

:10. '''己賀身乎幸波布心本尔之弖人乎幸布者末尔之有良之'''
::''Onoga mi o sakiwau kokoro moto ni shite hito o sakiwau wa sue ni shi arurashi''
::A heart that nurtures the self is the root, and nurturing others, it seems, is the branch that grows from it.

===奇魂 (Kushimitama) - The Wondrous Soul===

:1.  '''前世母即今乃世母後世母覚留者厳乃奇魂曾母'''
::''Saki-yo mo ima no yo mo nochi-yo mo satoru wa itsu no kushimitama zo mo''
::That which comprehends the past life, the present life, and the next life is the sacred Wondrous Soul.

:2.  '''奇魂乃神乃恵乎得志我也現世乃事何尔加惑波牟'''
::''Kushimitama no kami no e o eshi ware ya utsushiyo no koto nani ni ka madowamu''
::Having received the wisdom of the god of the Wondrous Soul, how could I be led astray by the affairs of this world?

:3.  '''天地乃依合乃極美奇魂乃伊照到良奴処之母奈之'''
::''Ametsuchi no yoriai no kiwami kushimitama no iteri-itaranu tokoro shi mo nashi''
::To the farthest reaches where Heaven and Earth meet, there is no place the light of the Wondrous Soul does not reach.

:4.  '''奇魂波常闇乃世乎照良須倍伎神乃玉曾母琢祁世乃人'''
::''Kushimitama wa tokoyami no yo o terasu-beki kami no tama zo mo migake yo no hito''
::The Wondrous Soul is a divine jewel that can illuminate an age of eternal darkness. Polish it, O people of the world!

:5.  '''奇魂乃神光者大神乃八十乃垧道母照左留奈祁武'''
::''Kushimitama no mi-hikari wa Ōkami no yaso no kumaji mo terasazaru nakemu''
::There are no winding paths of the Great God that the divine light of the Wondrous Soul cannot illuminate.

:6.  '''萬事奇魂乃神尔事議々弖後尔事波成倍志'''
::''Yorozu-goto kushimitama no kami ni koto-hakarite nochi ni koto wa nasu-beshi''
::In all matters, you should first consult with the god of the Wondrous Soul, and only then act.

:7.  '''奇魂者奇敷母乃加世乃中乃心乃闇乎照須乎見礼婆'''
::''Kushimitama wa kushiki mono ka yo no naka no kokoro no yami o terasu o mireba''
::The Wondrous Soul is a miraculous thing, for I see it illuminates the darkness in the hearts of this world.

:8.  '''天尔事国尔事知留奇魂乃神乃活用毎尔奇之幾'''
::''Ame ni koto kuni ni koto shiru kushimitama no kami no hataraki goto ni kushishiki''
::Knowing the affairs of heaven and the affairs of the nation, the workings of the god of the Wondrous Soul are ever miraculous.

:9.  '''奇魂乃奇幾乎綾尔知時者奇奈良奴奈之国乃物事'''
::''Kushimitama no kushiki o aya ni shiru toki wa kushi naranu nashi kuni no monogoto''
::When one truly understands the wonder of the Wondrous Soul, there is nothing in the nation's affairs that is not wondrous.

:10. '''奇魂乃太幾久広久成那牟止世中人者相勤牟倍志'''
::''Kushimitama no futoku hiroku narinamu to yonaka-bito wa ai-tsutomu-beshi''
::The people of the world must strive together so that the Wondrous Soul may become thick and wide.

===去就 (Kyoshū) - Departure and Whereabouts===

:1.  '''神去弖後乃行方波八雲立出雲乃宮曾其初発那留'''
::''Kami-sarite nochi no yukue wa yakumo tatsu Izumo no miya zo sono hotchi naru''
::After the spirit departs, its destination begins at the palace of Izumo, where the eight-layered clouds rise.

:2.  '''霊魂乃往母来留母出雲那留大国主神乃神定'''
::''Reikon no yuku mo kuru mo Izumo naru Ōkuninushi no kami no sadame''
::The coming and going of souls is decreed by the god Ōkuninushi, who resides in Izumo.

:3.  '''霊魂乃往来乃道乃八巷尔分割志道曾神随奈留'''
::''Reikon no yukiki no michi no yachimata ni wakareshi michi zo kannagara naru''
::The path of the soul's journey, which splits at the eight-forked road, follows the divine nature.

:4.  '''眼前尔在加止須礼波後辺尔在志賀如志霊魂乃行道'''
::''Me no mae ni aru ka to sureba shirie ni ari shi ga gotoshi reikon no yuku michi''
::The path the soul travels is like this: you think it is before your eyes, and then it is already behind you.

:5.  '''天地乃外尔母非自天地乃内尔母非自霊乃在処者'''
::''Ametsuchi no hoka ni mo arazu ametsuchi no uchi ni mo arazu rei no arika wa''
::The place where the spirit resides is neither outside Heaven and Earth, nor is it inside Heaven and Earth.

:6.  '''霊魂乃往辺如何尔止言牟与理先来志方乎神慮留倍志'''
::''Reikon no yukue ikan to iu yori saki ni koshi kata o omoihakaru-beshi''
::Rather than asking where the soul goes, one should first contemplate the place from which it came.

:7.  '''善事乎世尔施良須霊魂波神乃上多留神尔社安連'''
::''Yoki koto o yo ni shirasu reikon wa kami no ue taru kami ni koso are''
::A soul that performs good deeds in the world will surely become a god who is counted among the highest gods.

:8.  '''善魂乎持帰那者幽世乃吾大神者愛敷見坐左武'''
::''Yoki tama o mochi-kainaba kakuriyo no waga Ōkami wa medeku mimusamu''
::If you return with a good soul, my Great God in the hidden world will look upon you with love.

:9.  '''悪魂者既我知然後尔幽世乃神討爵米坐須'''
::''Ashiki tama wa sunawachi waga shiru nochi ni kakuriyo no kami uchi-semesimasu''
::An evil soul—as soon as I know of it, the gods of the hidden world will strike it down in punishment.

:10. '''幽世乃神乃賜比志霊魂尔疵乎勿附祁曾天下人'''
::''Kakuriyo no kami no tamaishi reikon ni kizu o na tsuke so amenoshita-bito''
::Do not inflict a single wound upon the soul that was granted to you by the gods of the hidden world, O people of the realm!

==Sources==
&lt;references/&gt;
*https://ja.wikisource.org/wiki/%E7%94%A3%E5%9C%9F%E7%99%BE%E9%A6%96
*https://ja.wikisource.org/wiki/%E9%9C%8A%E9%AD%82%E7%99%BE%E9%A6%96

==Notes==
Google Gemini 2.5 Pro intelinear translation. Please check for errors.

[[Category:Honda Chikaatsu]]
[[en:Hyakushu (Honda Chikaatsu)]]
[[Category:Pages without wikidata]]
[[Category:Translated pages]]</text>
      <sha1>k0x4tqh7gz6ier7viplxej72f0embgq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
