<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Why am I me?</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>107181</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3193553</id>
      <timestamp>2025-12-09T04:13:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yenistardom</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>translation of Japanese Wikipedia article なぜ私は私なのか</comment>
      <origin>3193553</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11822" sha1="3koq8xensuoprr4ctf9n07fympd0d4i" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''</text>
      <sha1>3koq8xensuoprr4ctf9n07fympd0d4i</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3413632</id>
      <parentid>3193553</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T00:48:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>3413632</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11849" sha1="b5ms0ze713vrph5cu89fb2avl88qen2" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''[[Category:orphaned pages]]</text>
      <sha1>b5ms0ze713vrph5cu89fb2avl88qen2</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3414096</id>
      <parentid>3413632</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T00:51:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>3414096</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11876" sha1="9e1set87a3pxfqpv3afvhsj9p75tjf8" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''[[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]]</text>
      <sha1>9e1set87a3pxfqpv3afvhsj9p75tjf8</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3414940</id>
      <parentid>3414096</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T00:54:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>3414940</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11903" sha1="98ffydht1ok1z1j0mv8fdv9t1bn6ran" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''[[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]]</text>
      <sha1>98ffydht1ok1z1j0mv8fdv9t1bn6ran</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3415404</id>
      <parentid>3414940</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T00:55:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>3415404</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11930" sha1="c09k10rmec6ql7pbsyunbzrbboex9dn" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''[[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]][[Category:orphaned pages]]</text>
      <sha1>c09k10rmec6ql7pbsyunbzrbboex9dn</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3564456</id>
      <parentid>3415404</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-23T19:53:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: remove [[Category:Orphaned pages]] (crud category cleanup) [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23455888809|manual triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3564456</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11822" sha1="3koq8xensuoprr4ctf9n07fympd0d4i" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''</text>
      <sha1>3koq8xensuoprr4ctf9n07fympd0d4i</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3571423</id>
      <parentid>3564456</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-26T01:13:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: categorize uncategorized page [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/23530060143|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3571423</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="11855" sha1="js9l51m0vo6njdap2cdwbncs31t5ii5" xml:space="preserve">'''Why am I me?''' (Japanese: なぜ私は私なのか, Hepburn: ''Naze watashi wa watashi nanoka'') is a problem discussed in [[metaphysics]], a branch of [[philosophy]], and in the [[philosophy of mind]]. While formulated in various ways, the problem is most generally expressed as follows:

There are many people in the world right now; countless people have been born in the past, and many more will be born and die in the future. Despite this, "Why am I me, rather than someone else?"

This inquiry goes by several names. It is sometimes referred to as the '''Problem of the "I"''' (using angle brackets, as &lt; I &gt;, a notation used by Japanese philosopher [[Hitoshi Nagai]]). It is also occasionally called the '''Harder Problem of Consciousness'''&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Tim S. (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;, in contrast to the "[[Hard problem of consciousness|Hard Problem of Consciousness]]" proposed by Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]]. Due to the content of the question asking "Why now, why here?", it is also known as the '''Here-Now Problem'''.

Some Japanese psychologists study this question from a psychological perspective. Unlike philosophers who discuss the question through speculation, these researchers investigate and analyze the psychological states of humans who ask this question through statistical and scientific methods such as questionnaires and interviews. In the context of such psychological research, the psychological state or experience of asking "Why am I me?" is referred to as "[[Ego experience]]" (Japanese: 自我体験).&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
(The original article refers to diagrams here which illustrate the concept)

Imagine a diagram abstracting a scene where you and four friends are eating together. In an objective view, everyone is depicted as an identical circle. However, the actual situation is not like that objective view; it is more appropriate to depict it differently. Among the five bodies, only one body (the "I") exists in a special way. Specifically:
* The world is visible only through the eyeballs attached to that body (it is not visible through other eyeballs).
* Only when that body is pinched does it hurt (it does not hurt when other bodies are pinched).
* Only that body can be moved by the intention to move it (other bodies cannot be moved directly).

Furthermore, the situation is more appropriately depicted as the world being centralized around one specific body and opening up from there. That is, if any other body disappears, it is merely one event within the "world". However, the disappearance of that one specific body is not an event ''within'' the world, but the disappearance ''of'' the "world" itself.

Why does the situation actually take this special form, centered on a specific point, rather than the objective view where everyone is equal?

The matter being questioned here is extremely obvious. It is so obvious that in daily social life, it is passed over without ever being questioned. However, this is not a question asked only by philosophers; it is one that ordinary people sometimes encounter in their lives. While not everyone encounters this question, a survey of Japanese university students by Watanabe found that nearly 1 in 10 people had experienced this type of questioning. Regarding the timing of the first experience of this question, a survey by Amaya suggests it often occurs from late elementary school to the first year of junior high school.&lt;ref&gt;Amaya, Yuko (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The 17th-century French philosopher [[Blaise Pascal]] (1623–1662) left the following description:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I see those frightful spaces of the universe which surround me, and I find myself tied to one corner of this vast extent, without knowing why I am put in this place rather than in another, nor why the short time which is given me to live is assigned to me at this point rather than at another of the whole eternity which was before me or which shall come after me. I see nothing but infinites on all sides... All I know is that I must soon die, but what I know least is this very death which I cannot escape.
— [[Blaise Pascal]] (1670), ''[[Pensées]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Pascal raised the question but did not specifically attempt to answer it.

In the 18th century, Scottish philosopher [[Thomas Reid]] (1710–1796) wrote the following in a letter to the renowned judge [[Lord Kames]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would be glad to know your Lordship's opinion whether when my brain has lost its original structure, and when some hundred years after the same materials are fabricated so curiously as to become an intelligent being, whether, I say, that being will be me; or, if, two or three such beings should be formed out of my brain; whether they will all be me, and consequently one and the same intelligent being.
— Letter from Thomas Reid to Lord Kames (1775)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Thought experiments involving the duplication or reconstruction of the brain or body, such as the one shown by Reid, have been discussed by philosophers with various variations even into the 20th century. A famous example is the teletransporter thought experiment by [[Derek Parfit]].

In the early 20th century, the Austrian theoretical physicist [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1887–1961) described this problem as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose you are sitting on a bench by the wayside in the high Alps...
All that you see has—apart from small changes—been there for thousands of years before you. After a while—not long—you will no longer exist, and the woods and rocks and sky will continue, unchanged, for thousands of years after you.
What is it that has called you so suddenly out of nothingness to enjoy for a brief while a spectacle which remains quite indifferent to you? The conditions for your existence are almost as old as the rocks. For thousands of years men have striven and suffered and begotten and women have brought forth in pain. A hundred years ago, perhaps, another man sat on this spot; like you he gazed with awe and yearning in his heart at the dying light of the glaciers. Like you he was begotten of man and born of woman. He felt pain and brief joy as you do. Was he someone else? Was it not you yourself? What is this Self of yours? ... Is there any scientific meaning to this "someone else"? ... Why is your brother not you, and why are you not a distant cousin? What justifies you in obstinately discovering this difference—the difference between you and someone else—when objectively what is there is the same?
— [[Erwin Schrödinger]] (1925/1961), ''My View of the World''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Schrödinger noted that this problem "has been thought important only in the [[Samkhya]] philosophy of India,"&lt;ref&gt;Schrödinger (2002), p.101&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed, this question has not been asked very actively in the West. In Western philosophy and the flow of modern [[analytic philosophy]], a similar but slightly different question, [[Personal identity]] (the conditions under which persons at different temporal or spatial locations can be said to be the same individual), has become a key keyword representing various topics surrounding this issue. The treatment has mainly been such that references to the question of "Why am I me?" appear occasionally within discussions centered on personal identity.

In the 20th century and beyond, the philosopher who most actively discussed this problem in the English-speaking world was the Yugoslavian-born American philosopher [[Thomas Nagel]]. Nagel discussed the problem through the contrast between the first-person view of the world (the subjective view from the "now and here" one is experiencing) and the description of the centerless objective world.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Suppose we have a description of the world that includes everyone, including Thomas Nagel, from no particular point of view. It seems that something has been left out, something indispensable, namely, which of them is me. Yet there seems to be no room in the centerless world for such a further fact... It seems impossible that I should be a particular individual, Thomas Nagel, one of many persons in an objectively centerless world.
...The connection I may have to Thomas Nagel or any other objectively identifiable person seems accidental and arbitrary.
— [[Thomas Nagel]] (1986), ''[[The View from Nowhere]]''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nagel argued that in the objective description of the world, there is no necessity and it seems accidental that the subjectivity currently being experienced opens up from this specific person—that is, why "I" am this person.

== Candidate Answers ==
Various answers and approaches have been proposed for this problem.

=== It is a pseudoproblem ===
The stance that "Why am I me?" is not a valid question. This is often divided into two types:
==== Incorrect use of language ====
The view that the question arises from a misunderstanding or misuse of the grammar and logic of language (e.g., [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], [[Toshihiko Miura]]).
==== Reduced to other problems of consciousness ====
The view that once the general mechanisms of consciousness and [[qualia]] are explained, this question will also be resolved, and thus it does not exist as an independent "Harder Problem" (e.g., [[David Chalmers]] suggests this possibility).

=== Only I exist ===
The stance of [[Solipsism]]. It asserts that only "I" exist specially, and others are merely like philosophical zombies or characters in a dream. While this answers the question of "specialness," it is generally considered philosophically indefensible.

=== It can only be said to be so ===
The stance that it is a [[brute fact]]. There is no deeper reason; it just happens to be the case that I am this person. This is a position of accepting the fact without seeking a further metaphysical ground.

=== I am all living things ===
The stance known as [[Open Individualism]]. It proposes that there is only one subject of experience in the universe, which experiences life through everyone over time. If "I" am everyone, the question "Why am I this specific person?" dissolves because you are essentially everyone (e.g., [[Arnold Zuboff]], the [[Upanishads]]).

=== I am the whole world ===
A variation related to the above, often found in Eastern philosophies (e.g., [[Brahman]], [[Atman]]). The idea that the separation between the self and the world is an illusion.

=== "I" has also vanished ===
The stance of [[No-self]] (Anatta) in [[Buddhism]] or the [[Bundle theory]] of [[David Hume]]. It argues that a persistent metaphysical "self" does not exist, therefore the question of why "that self" is allocated to "this body" is based on a false premise.

== Related Topics ==
* [[The Hard Problem of Consciousness]]
* [[Personal Identity]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Open Individualism]]
* [[Indexicality]]
* [[Anthropic Principle]]
* [[Reincarnation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Nagel, Thomas. ''The View from Nowhere''. Oxford University Press, 1986.
* Schrödinger, Erwin. ''My View of the World''.
* Nagai, Hitoshi. ''The Metaphysics of 'I'''.
* Watanabe, Tsuneo. ''Ego Experience and Solipsistic Experience''.
* Parfit, Derek. ''Reasons and Persons''.

== See Also ==
* [[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]
* [[Swampman]]
* [[Qualia]]
* [[Self-consciousness]]
* [[Problem of other minds]]
* [[Philosophical zombie]]
* [[What Is It Like to Be a Bat?]]
* [[Umwelt]]
* [[Why there is anything at all]]
* [[Tat Tvam Asi]]
* [[Your Name.]] (Anime film dealing with body swapping)
* [[Principle of sufficient reason]]
* [[Depersonalization disorder]]

== External Links ==
* [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%9C%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AF%E7%A7%81%E3%81%AA%E3%81%AE%E3%81%8B Original Japanese Article: なぜ私は私なのか]

''Note: Gemini 3 Pro translation''
[[Category:Uncategorized pages]]</text>
      <sha1>js9l51m0vo6njdap2cdwbncs31t5ii5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
