<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Shinto Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>shintowiki</dbname>
    <base>https://shinto.miraheze.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.45.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Project</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Project talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="420" case="first-letter">GeoJson</namespace>
      <namespace key="421" case="first-letter">GeoJson talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="860" case="first-letter">Item</namespace>
      <namespace key="861" case="first-letter">Item talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="862" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="863" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Amitābha</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>108498</id>
    <revision>
      <id>3229396</id>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T20:29:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: migrate talk page structure; import discussion seed (ja:阿弥陀如来, en:Amitābha); add local discussion section + dated import note</comment>
      <origin>3229396</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="22048" sha1="02hx1v69ysdvqhaea9obv0fxrsr36ex" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-25 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[利用者:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[利用者:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[利用者:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>02hx1v69ysdvqhaea9obv0fxrsr36ex</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3232064</id>
      <parentid>3229396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T21:30:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: migrate talk page structure; import discussion seed (ja:阿弥陀如来, en:Amitābha); add local discussion section + dated import note</comment>
      <origin>3232064</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="22220" sha1="8ihmgy4vm7qys8k3yi2khx0pcmh63ms" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-25 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[利用者:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[利用者:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[利用者:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8ihmgy4vm7qys8k3yi2khx0pcmh63ms</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3232525</id>
      <parentid>3232064</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T22:44:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: migrate talk page structure; import discussion seed (ja:阿弥陀如来, en:Amitābha, simple:Amitabha); add local discussion section + dated import note</comment>
      <origin>3232525</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="23891" sha1="0qgjjeg6em8gfyd489sd1h85jxs5sbf" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-25 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[利用者:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[利用者:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[利用者:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from Simple English Wikipedia (2026-02-25, [https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/10561656 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: simple:Talk:Amitabha | revid=10561656 --&gt;
== The lede must 'start encyclopedic' ==

This article does not.--If that idea is helpful, then fine.--Good luck (while i fix other articles, for now.) [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:08, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:@[[User:~2025-27778-01|~2025-27778-01]] How do you suggest I fix it? [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 19:11, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
&lt;br&gt;
I put 'ten, new words at the beginning of the lede'.--'''Encyclopedic''', 'and i sourced it'.--Not sure that i will be back to this thread. Have a nice day. [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:20, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:I don't get what you mean but happy it seems okay [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 21:10, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0qgjjeg6em8gfyd489sd1h85jxs5sbf</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3233844</id>
      <parentid>3232525</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-26T00:46:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: migrate talk page structure; import discussion seed (ja:阿弥陀如来, en:Amitābha, simple:Amitabha); add local discussion section + dated import note</comment>
      <origin>3233844</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="24063" sha1="oemt16nixudcnngegp7lmxl84il9lk4" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[利用者:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[利用者:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[利用者:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from Simple English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/10561656 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: simple:Talk:Amitabha | revid=10561656 --&gt;
== The lede must 'start encyclopedic' ==

This article does not.--If that idea is helpful, then fine.--Good luck (while i fix other articles, for now.) [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:08, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:@[[User:~2025-27778-01|~2025-27778-01]] How do you suggest I fix it? [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 19:11, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
&lt;br&gt;
I put 'ten, new words at the beginning of the lede'.--'''Encyclopedic''', 'and i sourced it'.--Not sure that i will be back to this thread. Have a nice day. [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:20, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:I don't get what you mean but happy it seems okay [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 21:10, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>oemt16nixudcnngegp7lmxl84il9lk4</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3416031</id>
      <parentid>3233844</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-13T02:02:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Immanuelle</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Text replacement - "利用者:" to "User:"</comment>
      <origin>3416031</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="24048" sha1="cechmupdtgzv0elurrmottnnp4k90nt" xml:space="preserve">{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[User:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[User:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[User:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from Simple English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/10561656 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: simple:Talk:Amitabha | revid=10561656 --&gt;
== The lede must 'start encyclopedic' ==

This article does not.--If that idea is helpful, then fine.--Good luck (while i fix other articles, for now.) [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:08, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:@[[User:~2025-27778-01|~2025-27778-01]] How do you suggest I fix it? [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 19:11, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
&lt;br&gt;
I put 'ten, new words at the beginning of the lede'.--'''Encyclopedic''', 'and i sourced it'.--Not sure that i will be back to this thread. Have a nice day. [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:20, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:I don't get what you mean but happy it seems okay [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 21:10, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>cechmupdtgzv0elurrmottnnp4k90nt</sha1>
    </revision>
    <revision>
      <id>3617456</id>
      <parentid>3416031</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-22T14:52:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmmaBot</username>
        <id>703</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Project:History cleanup|Offloading history due to miraheze stability concerns]] many contributors, see [https://emmaleonhart.github.io/shintowiki-scripts/wikihistory.html?page=Amit%C4%81bha here] for full history [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24756154998|commit triggered pipeline]]</comment>
      <origin>3617456</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="24399" sha1="puak32nabbcp5ocpk9nsflkgc63pv6m" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- History offloaded: due to miraheze stability concerns, the edit history of this page has been offloaded to the XML archive. See https://emmaleonhart.github.io/shintowiki-scripts/wikihistory.html?page=Amit%C4%81bha for full history. Last refreshed: [[github:EmmaLeonhart/shintowiki-scripts/actions/runs/24756154998|commit triggered pipeline]] --&gt;
{{talk page header}}

&lt;!-- This talk page covers the main article and all associated namespace layers --&gt;
&lt;!-- Imported from Japanese/English/Simple English Wikipedia talk pages on 2026-02-26 (UTC) when available. --&gt;

== Local discussion ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 22:44, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 21:30, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 20:29, 25 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Add local discussion below this line. --&gt;

== Imported from Japanese Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/24756131 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: ja:Talk:阿弥陀如来 | revid=24756131 --&gt;
「四十八願」と第十八願を付け加えました。[[User:マイコン坊主|booze]] 22:59 2003年7月9日 (UTC)
　
*阿弥陀如来の[[梵字]]付け足しました。--[[User:Enthousiasme|ﻞﺠﺮ ﻲﺎﻔﺻ]] 2006年4月11日 (火) 06:42 (UTC)

== 浄土真宗のサブセクションについて ==

{{コメント}}
;浄土真宗のサブセクションについて
:IPユーザー60.37.114.186により、セクション「概要」のサブセクション「浄土真宗」が、要約欄・ノートに理由を示さないまま削除されたので、差し戻しました。
:削除の理由などは、下記にお願いします。--[[User:Resto1578|Resto1578]] 2009年3月8日 (日) 16:35 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/1216970422 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: en:Talk:Amitābha | revid=1216970422 --&gt;
{{WikiProject banner shell|class=C|vital=yes|1=
{{WikiProject East Asia|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject China|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibet|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|importance=Top}}
}}

==Good Question==

In response to the below question, I have to simply say, I really don't know.  I have no authority to answer this question, as I am but a layman, and not so well educated on the finer points of Buddhism as I'd like to be, but perhaps I can shed some possible light on this problem.  

I suppose we may have a sort of vertical ladder mindset when it comes to placing Buddhas and Bodhisattvas in a sort of power structure.  I believe that thinking in this dichotomy may be fundamentally wrong.  There really is no difference between a Bodhisattva, a Buddha, and for that matter, a sentient being.  At least, I come to this conclusion on based on my personal interpretation of the dharma.

Still, being that we live in the real world, we linguistically define and separate Buddhas and Bodhisattvas.  I will address this matter in just a moment, but let me talk about that particular vow.  If the vow does in fact say that Amitabha forestalls perfect enlightenment until all beings are saved in the Western paradise, then I can see where the paradox comes from.  However, it's been a long time since I read the Amitabha sutras, and I can't remember if the vow was to build a place where people could easily reach enlightenment, or to actually enlighten everyone through those means.  If it were the former, it could mean that he has fulfilled that vow.  If it is in fact the latter, as you stated, then Amitabha would join the host of hundreds of other popular Bodhisattvas who have made similar vows.  In my personal opinion, I think it may be the pure heart and intention behind making the vow, not neccessarily the completion of a certain task.

Now, for the fun part.  I think if we look at the name Amitabha itself, the Sanskrit meaning something like boundless, infinite light - then I think the implication here is Buddhahood.  In the Chinese name, the character "Fo" is present, meaning "Buddha".  That character does not appear in the names of deities who are typically assigned the role of Bodhisattva, but it does also appear in the Chinese translations of [[Shakyamuni]] and [[Maitreya]], who are Buddhas.  Phew.  Basically, I guess, there is no easy answer.  Everything is, and is not, everything else.  It's really quite Buddhistic, actually![[User:Iluvchineselit|Iluvchineselit]] 06:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Sex==
Throughout the article there are numerous uses of "his" and "him" to refer to  Amitābha but the Pure Land Buddhist monk that I know claimed she is neither male nor female, or both.

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Why not a Bodhisattva==
Why is Amitabha not regarded to be a Bodhisattva, since according to the article ''he promises not to achieve supreme perfect enlightenment until he has saved all sentient beings in his paradise.'' I thought that's by definition a Bodhisattva? Thanxs for answering [[User:Gugganij|gugganij]] 20:18, 22 July 2005 (UTC)
::The real reason that Amitabha is not regarded as a Bodhisattva is that the article's characterization of the 48 vows is ''wrong''.  According to the sutra, Amitabha ''has'' fulfilled all 48 vows, and accordingly ''has'' achieved supreme perfect enlightenment (''anuttarasamyaksambodhi'').  The text should read something like "until all beings can, by aspiration to be reborn there, achieve birth in his Pure Land". [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 03:24, 20 March 2006 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Amitabha and Mithraism==
I removed the below comments (which were what were left after I edited out some POV and irrelevancies):
::Some scholars have claimed a connection between the Iranian cult of Mithra and Buddha Amitabha. Richard C. Foltz, in "Religions of the Silk Road" claims that Amitabha "seems to be understood as the Iranian god of light, equated with the sun".

But even after editing, I can't see the relevance to the article, and I'm not even sure Foltz has been accurately quoted. The connection is in any case purely speculative, and it's not even clear what it means historically: did Mithra-worshipping Iranians accept Amitabha as a substitute for Mithra?  Did they endow Amitabha with Mithra-like qualities?  What is actually being claimed?

Leaving aside the question of whether it's fair to call Mithra a "solar deity", it is very clear that Amitabha is not one. It is true that the name Amitabha means "unlimited light", but the association between good deities, wisdom, and light is a common one, capable of being made independently by different peoples, and implies nothing about a historical relationship. 

More to the point, there is no written or archaeological evidence to indicate that anything about Amitabha was borrowed from a non-Buddhist source; the initial evidences for belief in Amitabha come from within India. The ''name'' Amitabha is certainly not Iranian.  The ''appearance'' of Amitabha follows other Buddhist iconography, and while that certainly may have some extra-Indian influences they are more likely Greek than Iranian. The ''functions'' of Amitabha are only intelligible in a Buddhist setting, and owe nothing to any type of Iranian religion. What, then, is left for Mithra to supply? [[User:RandomCritic|RandomCritic]] 13:21, 20 March 2006 (UTC)


I wouldn't say that the connection between Amida and Persian religion is entirely unfounded. In fact, I was under the impression that this was an established accepted (if somewhat obscure) view. Writes Joseph Campbell:

“And of these [meditation Buddhas], by far the most popular and important is Amitabha, the Buddha of ‘immeasurable (''a-mita'') light (''abha'')’... who is produced purely of Buddhist thought, yet bears the marks of an ultimate derivation from Iran.”
-''The Masks of God Volume II, Oriental Mythology'' p.303

and,

“Obviously, a gentle purgatory [of Amida’s Pure Land] has here superseded the usual Indian image of spiritual progress by reincarnation, and were the date of the doctrine not so early, one could suppose that a Christian influence might have come into play. However, as things stand, the more plausible view is that the influence of Iran and the doctrine of Zoroaster... ‘It is not to be forgotten,’ states an excellent recent monograph on this subject,

&lt;blockquote&gt;that the first apostle to bring Amida worship to China was a Parthian prince, Ngan Che-Kao, and that the Kushana empire where Amida worship first arose was no less Iranian than Indian, no less Mazdaen than Buddhist. Ngan Che-Kao was an Arsacid who lived in China from 148 to 170 A.D. ... Furthermore, the work of translation sacred texts and of peddling and fashioning sacred images was in the second and third centuries AD carried on principally by Bactrian and Sogdian subjects of Yueh-chi. ... Hence, it is not in India proper that the factors contributing to the victory of Amida must be sought, but in the intermediate Chinese-Indian Zone, where the prevailing influence was of Iran. ... [siting Marie-Therese de Mallmann, ''Introduction a l’etude d’Avalokitec-vara''
(Paris: Civilization du Sud, 1948), pp 90-91]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

“Dr. Marie-Therese de Mallmann, the author of this important study, has shown that the names Amitabha and Amitayus correspond to the usual characterizations of the Persian creator-god Ahura Mazda, as the lord both of light and unending time; furthermore, that throughout the broad domain of Persian religious influence (which, as we know, reached with the Roman army into Gaul and Britain), divine triads matching that of Amitabha seated between his two great standing Bodhisattvas appear at many sites.”

Ibid, pp 306-307

Now, this all seems to a be a scholarly and convincing argument, at least to me. I think a section on the link between Amida and Ahura Mazda (although with Mithras seems suspect), is well worth considering.

[[User:74.71.120.81|74.71.120.81]] 21:22, 4 July 2007 (UTC)

:Personally I don't buy it.  Taken by itself, one could contrive a theory that the iconography matches gods and deities in other religions, but if you read the larger Mahayana canon, you'll see that Amida and the Pure Land are part of a bigger picture.  Also, don't forget that there is another Buddha related to the Sun and Light: Mahavairocana.  This is just some weak scholarship by someone who wants to try to unify all religions on the Asian continent, while ignoring the subtle details between them.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:07, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
==Ikko Ikki==
I think a mention of the Ikko Ikki monks would be an interesting and relevant tidbit of trivia.

:I do not.  There already is a wikipedia article on that.  --[[User:Ph0kin|Ph0kin]] ([[User talk:Ph0kin|talk]]) 06:04, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Merge Articles ==

I propose to Merge the Articles {{PAGENAME}} and [[Amitayus]], for reasons obvious, As the Articles itself says //He is frequently invoked in Tibet either as Buddha Amithaba - especially in the Powa practices or as Amitāyus - especially in practices relating to longevity and preventing an untimely death//. Hence Amitayus is nothing but a different Name of Amitbha Buddha [[User:Vinodh.vinodh|Vinodh.vinodh]] ([[User talk:Vinodh.vinodh|talk]]) 09:59, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

Amitabha is considered the [[Emanation Body|Nirmanakaya]] aspect of Buddha's [[aggregate of discrimination|Saññā]] while Amitayus is the [[Enjoyment Body|Sambhogakaya]] aspect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.himalayanart.org/search/set.cfm?setID=130&lt;/ref&gt;. I'm removing your suggestion to merge these articles.[[User:Peaceful5|Peaceful5]] ([[User talk:Peaceful5|talk]]) 08:50, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

: Please don't remove the tag until a clear consensus is achieved.  Why would two articles be necessary, when Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here? [[User:Jpatokal|Jpatokal]] ([[User talk:Jpatokal|talk]]) 11:36, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

:: It was promised that "Amitayus could be perfectly well covered in a paragraph or two here". But now we find no mention of Amitayus in this article, while Amitayus, not Amitabha, is one of the three Longevity Buddhas along with Sita Tara and Usnisavijaya. Could someone add in the article the character of relationship of Amitayus and Amitabha? When is he Amitabha and when is he Amitayus? Please excuse me if this question sounds illiterate. [[User:Gantuya eng|Gantuya eng]] ([[User talk:Gantuya eng|talk]]) 03:43, 13 May 2010 (UTC)

There is a difference between Amitayus and Amitabha, (in Tibetan Buddhism) Amitayus~the Buddha of Infinite '''Life'''  and Amitabha~ the Buddha of Infinite '''Light''' are essentially identical, being reflective images of one another. Sutras in which Shakyamuni expounds the glories of Sukhavati, the Pure Lands, speak of the presiding Buddha sometimes as Amitabha and sometimes as Amitayus. When depicted as Amitayus he is depicted in fine clothes and jewels and as Amitabha in simple monk's clothing. They are also simply known as Amida in the Chinese and Japanese tradition. The image of the gold colored statue in the article is of Amitayus as he is wearing a 5 pointed crown, which is the easiest way to distinguish them. Amitayus is an emanation of Amitabha. Amitabha is the head of the Lotus family, where as Amitayus is not the head of the Lotus Family. &lt;ref&gt;Images of Enlightenment by Landaw and Weber page 75,80,96&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]]) 16:09, 9 March 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class="autosigned"&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:David baronet|David baronet]] ([[User talk:David baronet|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/David baronet|contribs]]) 16:00, 9 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{reflist-talk}}

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Anime Reference ==

I removed the Anime reference.  Given the high profile of Amitabha in Chinese and Japanese culture it would be pointless to list every such reference, and the one given was not special in anyway.
--[[User:Nio-guardian|Nio-guardian]] ([[User talk:Nio-guardian|talk]]) 08:46, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Academic validation of..... ==

Vipaśyanā Amitāyus Sūtra....???
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;newwindow=1&amp;q=Vipasyana%20Amitayus%20Sutra%20Amitabha&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws
* http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Vipa%C5%9Byan%C4%81+Amit%C4%81yus+S%C5%ABtra+Amit%C4%81bha&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_sdt=2000&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_vis=0
--[[Special:Contributions/58.38.43.99|58.38.43.99]] ([[User talk:58.38.43.99|talk]]) 03:22, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Minor typo ==

There is a minor typo for this entry:

"Dharmakāra" should be --&gt; Dharmākara

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678427360 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710021539/http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org:80/5_dhyani_buddhas.html to http://buddhism.kalachakranet.org/5_dhyani_buddhas.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:29, 29 August 2015 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Amitābha]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712594892 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.bdk.or.jp/pdf/bdk/digitaldl/dBET_ThreePureLandSutras_2003.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style="color:green;font-family:Courier"&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style="margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS"&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style="color:green"&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:49, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== A Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion ==
The following Wikimedia Commons file used on this page has been nominated for deletion:
* [[commons:File:Amitabha.png|Amitabha.png]]&lt;!-- COMMONSBOT: discussion | 2019-03-18T19:22:22.832805 | Amitabha.png --&gt;
Participate in the deletion discussion at the [[commons:Commons:Deletion requests/File:Amitabha.png|nomination page]]. —[[User:Community Tech bot|Community Tech bot]] ([[User talk:Community Tech bot|talk]]) 19:22, 18 March 2019 (UTC)

:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
== Mantras ==

In the mantra section, it states "The Sanskrit form of the mantra of Amitābha is ॐ अमिताभ ह्रीः (Devanagari: oṃ amitābha hrīḥ), which is pronounced in Japanese as Namu Amida Butsu ...". 

While the recitation of the mantra "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ", "om ami dewa hrih", or "om amideva hrih"  is often compared as a similar practice to nembutsu or nianfo, it is not strictly the same.

Nembutsu/Nianfo involves reciting "Namo Amitabha Buddha" in their respective languages, but "oṃ amitābha hrīḥ" or "om ami dewa hrih" is typically practiced in the context of Vajrayana, where it is a yidam practice (sometimes a phowa practice, depends on context) that involves generation as the deity Amitabha, rather than just praising Amitabha and taking refuge in him. 

For example, in Tibetan, the closest equivalent to "Namo Amitabha Buddha" that I know of would be "öpakmé la chaktsal lo | འོད་དཔག་མེད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ" (English: "Amitabha, I prostrate/pay homage to you") instead of "om ami dewa hrih", though the former is not a common practice by itself (usually seen within prayers or sadhanas).

Even ignoring the Vajrayana practice of yidam generation, I think it makes sense to have the "Namo Amitabha Buddha" equivalents in Japanese and Chinese listed in the second paragraph, as "Namo Amida Butsu" and "Namo Amituofo" are directly the same 1:1 practice, just in different languages. [[Special:Contributions/2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F]] ([[User talk:2603:9001:4D07:85D8:59C9:A775:8ED3:555F|talk]]) 21:15, 27 July 2023 (UTC)

:Please provide reliable citations for mantra translations, as there are variations within every language, and sources are necessary. For example, your Tibetan translation does not use the standard Wylie rendering method. This has nothing to do with the “Vajrayana practice of yidam generation,” it is standard citation practice for linguistic research. [[User:Jellocube27|Jellocube27]] ([[User talk:Jellocube27|talk]]) 03:14, 28 July 2023 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)

== Imported from Simple English Wikipedia (2026-02-26, [https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:PermanentLink/10561656 revision]) ==
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)
&lt;!-- Source: simple:Talk:Amitabha | revid=10561656 --&gt;
== The lede must 'start encyclopedic' ==

This article does not.--If that idea is helpful, then fine.--Good luck (while i fix other articles, for now.) [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:08, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:@[[User:~2025-27778-01|~2025-27778-01]] How do you suggest I fix it? [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 19:11, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
&lt;br&gt;
I put 'ten, new words at the beginning of the lede'.--'''Encyclopedic''', 'and i sourced it'.--Not sure that i will be back to this thread. Have a nice day. [[Special:Contributions/&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|&amp;#126;2025-27778-01]] ([[User talk:&amp;#126;2025-27778-01|talk]]) 19:20, 9 October 2025 (UTC)

:I don't get what you mean but happy it seems okay [[User:Immanuelle|'''Immanuel'''le]] ❤️💚💙 [[User_talk:Immanuelle|(please tag me)]] 21:10, 9 October 2025 (UTC)
:Dummy comment added by script to avoid immediate auto-archive of a fresh page.[[User:Immanuelle|Immanuelle]] ([[User talk:Immanuelle|talk]]) 00:46, 26 February 2026 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>puak32nabbcp5ocpk9nsflkgc63pv6m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
